<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-31T22:59:13-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Book review: The Passenger by Lisa Lutz</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/23/book-review-the-passenger.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book review: The Passenger by Lisa Lutz" /><published>2022-06-23T15:57:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-23T15:57:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/23/book-review-the-passenger</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/23/book-review-the-passenger.html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;aside&quot;&gt;Spoiler warning: spoilers for The Passenger by Lisa Lutz, and In the Cart, by Anton Chekhov.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I took up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26154406-the-passenger&quot;&gt;this book&lt;/a&gt; looking for a page-turner. It was, but hours before the end I thought its main contribution to my mental life would be the visceral knowledge that page-turners can be undelicious. It felt cold, and getting into its world felt bad. The protagonist slunk around dark and uncomfortable places, killing people, scheming harshly, perceiving low beams as dangers to the heads of tall men, and that sort of thing. With some amount of fretting about what she was becoming. I wanted to turn the pages, but I also kind of wanted it to end, and for me to read something more squarely enjoyable next time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--ex--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then the end was different, and kept coming back to me in the day, and turned the rest around and gave it new meaning. Like the image of a long dark tunnel becomes something different if you step away and see that it starts in the loveliest of fields. After a long dark tunnel of a book, we turn around and see where the heroine came from, and her teenage innocence and goodness newly fills out the potentially empty person we have been watching. And her past isn’t really discordant—I think I just wrote her off fast. This endless night began in that day, and seeing so makes the full picture both warm and intense, where it had seemed like cheap suspense and violence.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In that abstract description, I suppose it is a bit like ‘In The Cart’ by Chekhov: we watch a dreary life, then at last that life is pulled into a perspective where we see its warm and hopeful start, unreachably distant. And it changes the flavor.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have not much idea if what I saw was what Lisa Lutz was going for, but if she was, and if other readers are like me (haha) then I think having 85% of the book be unpleasant was probably called for.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="book" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Spoiler warning: spoilers for The Passenger by Lisa Lutz, and In the Cart, by Anton Chekhov. I took up this book looking for a page-turner. It was, but hours before the end I thought its main contribution to my mental life would be the visceral knowledge that page-turners can be undelicious. It felt cold, and getting into its world felt bad. The protagonist slunk around dark and uncomfortable places, killing people, scheming harshly, perceiving low beams as dangers to the heads of tall men, and that sort of thing. With some amount of fretting about what she was becoming. I wanted to turn the pages, but I also kind of wanted it to end, and for me to read something more squarely enjoyable next time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An inquiry into the thoughts of twenty-five people in India</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/28/inquiry-twenty-five-people-in-india.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An inquiry into the thoughts of twenty-five people in India" /><published>2022-05-28T01:13:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-28T01:13:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/28/inquiry-twenty-five-people-in-india</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/28/inquiry-twenty-five-people-in-india.html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I get excited about running surveys. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1UzZf_1j7BmaacE60Sl6YbSdMMldWr8REVTXJDIVKkws/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.positly.com/&quot;&gt;Positly&lt;/a&gt; one from November 2020 in which I asked the following questions, to participants from India:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are you looking forward to this week?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you think of as the most important thing going on in the world right now?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you had a spare half hour right now, what would you do with it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is something you changed your mind about recently?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What in life is more important than other people realize?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone gave you $5 right now, what would you do with it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who is someone you think of as a hero?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you paying attention to the US election?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What was the biggest news story this year?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don’t recall any notable constraints other than the location requirement, but I barely remember doing this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="survey" /><summary type="html">Sometimes I get excited about running surveys. Here is a Positly one from November 2020 in which I asked the following questions, to participants from India: What are you looking forward to this week? What do you think of as the most important thing going on in the world right now? If you had a spare half hour right now, what would you do with it? What is something you changed your mind about recently? What in life is more important than other people realize? If someone gave you $5 right now, what would you do with it? Who is someone you think of as a hero? Are you paying attention to the US election? What was the biggest news story this year? I don’t recall any notable constraints other than the location requirement, but I barely remember doing this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Podcast: with Spencer Greenberg on groupstruckness and boundedness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/19/podcast-clearer-thinking-groupstruck.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcast: with Spencer Greenberg on groupstruckness and boundedness" /><published>2022-05-19T20:57:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-19T20:57:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/19/podcast-clearer-thinking-groupstruck</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/19/podcast-clearer-thinking-groupstruck.html">&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;https://clearerthinkingpodcast.com/episode/105&quot;&gt;talked to Spencer Greenberg&lt;/a&gt; a little while ago for his podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://clearerthinkingpodcast.com/&quot;&gt;Clearer Thinking&lt;/a&gt;. The recording is out today. According to his website we discussed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What does it mean to be “groupstruck”? How does groupstruck-ness differ from the bystander effect, normalcy bias, and other related cognitive biases? How do we break people out of being groupstruck? What does it mean to be a “bounded” person? How can we build up better decision-making heuristics? What sorts of decisions do people usually not quantify but should (and vice versa)? How can we make rational relationship decisions without coming across as “calculating” or cold? How does anthropic reasoning affect our hypotheses about the nature of the universe and life within it (i.e., the Fermi paradox, the simulation hypothesis, etc.)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen or read the transcript &lt;a href=&quot;https://clearerthinkingpodcast.com/episode/105&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="podcast" /><category term="sociology" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="decisionmaking" /><category term="anthropics" /><summary type="html">I talked to Spencer Greenberg a little while ago for his podcast Clearer Thinking. The recording is out today. According to his website we discussed: What does it mean to be “groupstruck”? How does groupstruck-ness differ from the bystander effect, normalcy bias, and other related cognitive biases? How do we break people out of being groupstruck? What does it mean to be a “bounded” person? How can we build up better decision-making heuristics? What sorts of decisions do people usually not quantify but should (and vice versa)? How can we make rational relationship decisions without coming across as “calculating” or cold? How does anthropic reasoning affect our hypotheses about the nature of the universe and life within it (i.e., the Fermi paradox, the simulation hypothesis, etc.)? You can listen or read the transcript here.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/markus-winkler-afW1hht0NSs-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/markus-winkler-afW1hht0NSs-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Proposal: Twitter dislike button</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/17/twitter-dislike-button.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Proposal: Twitter dislike button" /><published>2022-05-17T12:21:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-17T12:21:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/17/twitter-dislike-button</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/17/twitter-dislike-button.html">&lt;p&gt;The popular story of Twitter’s role in the ruin of civilization is that it is a runaway trash fire of reciprocal anger and offense, where otherwise nice people are possessed by overwhelming outrages, and drawn into throwing their own energy behind creating the vilest and most vindictive responses to what they see, turning away from reason and hurting others in turn, and so the place continues.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how much of Twitter activity this accounts for (apparently &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/michael_nielsen/status/975884635535101952&quot;&gt;Michael Nielsen enjoys an entirely different place&lt;/a&gt;, and my experience seems pretty nice too). But I think there’s a real pattern of this kind, which makes game theoretic sense, and goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People say things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People read these things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If anything seems objectionable to any of these people, then they repost those things with commentary, and everyone else reads them extra.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the next round, people (or the ones who who get attention) say objectionable things (that they expect will get attention), about objectionable things (that they have their attention on from the last round)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To lay out the effects of all this more clearly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People disproportionately read things they don’t like, which is presumably bad for them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People get the visceral sense that others are disproportionately writing things they don’t like, which is misleading, and not in a helpful-for-public-friendship way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things people don’t like get extra space in the public conversation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who tend to write things that others don’t like get extra power and attention instead of less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing things other people don’t like is incentivized (if you want attention, writing things other people don’t like is probably somewhat better than writing things people do like, and way better than writing things they don’t feel strongly about).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supposing something like this model is true, and bad, it seems to me that there is a really simple solution: &lt;strong&gt;add a dislike button.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, what if when a person sees a thing they don’t like, instead of broadcasting it to others, they register their disapproval by quietly clicking a different button next to the heart, and then Twitter shows it to other people less instead of more? You can still retweet it if you especially want other people to see it more, but adding attention wouldn’t be the default disapproval vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an original idea, and the other major websites that do it have not, to my knowledge, been run out of business by a dearth of disagreement. I think they are also not so much known for the above dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posit that a Twitter downvote button would be great. What am I missing?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="institutiondesign" /><category term="twitter" /><summary type="html">The popular story of Twitter’s role in the ruin of civilization is that it is a runaway trash fire of reciprocal anger and offense, where otherwise nice people are possessed by overwhelming outrages, and drawn into throwing their own energy behind creating the vilest and most vindictive responses to what they see, turning away from reason and hurting others in turn, and so the place continues.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/downvote2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/downvote2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fighting in various places for a really long time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/10/fighting-for-a-really-long-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fighting in various places for a really long time" /><published>2022-05-10T18:24:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-10T18:24:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/10/fighting-for-a-really-long-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/10/fighting-for-a-really-long-time.html">&lt;p&gt;The first time someone raved to me about seeing Everything Everywhere All at Once, I thought they were actually suggesting I see everything everywhere all at once, and I was briefly excited by the implication that this exhilarating possibility was somehow on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that disappointment I heard about it several times more, and warmed to the idea of seeing the movie anyway, especially on account of it being the most roundly recommended one I remember. The third time someone invited me to see it with them, I went.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it seemed so astonishingly lacking to both of us that I left severely confused, and remain so. Like: I know people have different tastes. I know that I’m not the biggest movie appreciator (my ideal movie probably has a small number of visually distinct characters and nobody dies or does anything confusing, and I’ve already seen it twice). But usually I have some abstract guess about what other people are liking. Or, more realistically, a name for the category of mysterious attraction (“ah yes, you are into the ‘action’, and that means it’s good when helicopters crash or people shoot each other”). Yet here, I’m grasping even for that. “You like it because.. it has much more prolonged fighting than usual and you like fighting?…or…it is some kind of irony thing about other movies?” I could believe that it was some kind of mediocre action movie. But usually my friends don’t go crazy for mediocre action movies. And here for instance one of my best friends, who I generally take to have subtle and sensitive and agreeable tastes, and who knows me extremely well, told &lt;em&gt;me in particular&lt;/em&gt; to see it. And the strongest criticism I have seen of it outside of our post-movie discussion is another friend’s apparently sincere complaint on Facebook that it is probably only among the top hundred movies ever, not the top ten like people say. And it’s not that I just wasn’t wowed by it: it’s hard to remember the last time I was less compelled by a movie. (Though perhaps one doesn’t remember such things.) Like, I was really sitting there in the cinema thinking something along the lines of, ‘movies usually grab my attention somehow, yet this is doing some special thing differently to not have that happen? Huh?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if I can spoil this movie, because whatever was good in it, I totally missed. But here I attempt spoilers. This is what happens in the movie, as far as I can tell:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Ok my companion and I actually failed to notice when it started, so maybe there was something important there. Oops.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A woman and her family run a laundromat, and are also working on their taxes. Her life is disappointing to her. A version of her husband appears from a different dimension and relays some kind of dimly coherent plot involving lots of dimensions and the need for her to jump between them and fight or something. Then they fight and jump between dimensions for about two hours. Their fighting involves some repeating motifs: 1) There is a humorous conceit that in order to jump between dimensions you have to do a strange action, for instance bite off and chew some lip balm. This joke is repeated throughout most of the fighting. One time the traveler has to put an object up their bottom, so that is pretty exciting humorwise. 2) Things often look cool. Like, there are lots of evocative objects and people are wearing make-up and neat costumes. 3) There is lots of jumping between dimensions. At some point it becomes clear that a baddie is actually the woman’s daughter, who has turned to nihilism as a result of either seeing everything all at once and that being kind of intrinsically nihilism-provoking due to its lack of permitting anything else, or as a result of having her lesbianism disrespected by her mother earlier. The fighting takes on a more nihilism vs. appreciating life flavor, and then it turns out that being friendly and warm is good, as represented by the father, and now appreciated by the mother. Then…actually I forget what happens at the end, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m all for ‘nihilism vs. something something existential something something, life, kindness’ as a theme, but this seemed like such a shallow treatment of it. It just seemed like a bunch of fighting labeled ‘deep plot about nihilism etc’, and I don’t think caused me to have any interesting thoughts about such themes, except perhaps by reminding me of the general topic and leaving me without anything to distract my mind from wandering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clearly too violent for my liking, so that’s idiosyncratic, but it’s not like I’m always opposed to violence—some of the fighting in Lord of the Rings was quite moving, and I watched the whole of Game of Thrones in spite of also at other times using scenes from it in exposure therapy. But I posit that you need some sort of meaningful context to make violence interesting or moving, and I don’t think I caught that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also speculate that some humor is meant to come from the protagonist being a middle aged immigrant Chinese woman, instead of the more standard young man. Which seems rude: as though it is asking for the props generally offered for featuring atypical demographics in films, yet is doing so as a joke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, it seemed to me to be a bunch of fairly meaningless fighting interspersed with repetitive lowbrow humor and aesthetically pleasing props.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked a couple of my friends to explain their alternate takes to me, but I don’t think I can do their explanations justice, due to not really understanding them. At a high level they disagreed with me about things like ‘was it extremely humorous?’ and ‘was it unusually engaging vs. unusually unengaging?’, but I didn’t understand why, at a lower level. Probably we all agree that it was visually cool, but I wasn’t actually stunned by that. Maybe visual attractiveness alone counts for less with me (though I recently saw Everything is Illuminated, which I found awesome in a confusingly soul-electrifying way and whose merit seems somehow related to visualness). One interesting thing that this discussion with EEAAO appreciators added was the point that there is something moving about the thought that in a different dimension you and the odious tax lady might be tender lovers. I agree that that’s a nice thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hesitant to criticize here, because it is sweet of my friends to try to give me a nice movie recommendation, and I appreciate it. Also, I think in general that if Alice loves a thing and Bob doesn’t, it is much more likely that Bob is missing something wonderful than that Alice is imagining such a thing. (Though conversely if they agree that the thing is pretty good in ways, and Bob just hates it because it also has some overriding problem, then my guess would be the reverse: probably Alice is missing a thing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So probably, somehow, other people are right. Please other people, help enlighten me more? (And thanks to some of my friends for trying!)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="review" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">The first time someone raved to me about seeing Everything Everywhere All at Once, I thought they were actually suggesting I see everything everywhere all at once, and I was briefly excited by the implication that this exhilarating possibility was somehow on the table. After that disappointment I heard about it several times more, and warmed to the idea of seeing the movie anyway, especially on account of it being the most roundly recommended one I remember. The third time someone invited me to see it with them, I went.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/iStock-1221217976.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/iStock-1221217976.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stuff I might do if I had covid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/10/covid-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stuff I might do if I had covid" /><published>2022-05-10T16:50:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-10T16:50:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/10/covid-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/10/covid-list.html">&lt;p&gt;In case anyone wants a rough and likely inaccurate guide to what I might do if I had covid to mitigate it, I looked into this a bit recently and wrote notes. It’s probably better than if one’s plan was to do less than a few hours of research, but is likely flawed all over the place and wasn’t written with public sharing in mind, and um, isn’t medical advice [ETA May 11: also safety-relevant improvements are being made in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/11cF4k9NUltfiEYv8yhsw2Ku8qRITQY5IqxJ71jFpVO4/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt; version, so I recommend looking at that.]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/0dc9afd2-c217-4caa-8921-429331332c31&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2022-05-07_at_1.35.17_PM.png?width=960&amp;amp;height=720&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;Screen_Shot_2022-05-07_at_1.35.17_PM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/11cF4k9NUltfiEYv8yhsw2Ku8qRITQY5IqxJ71jFpVO4/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Here’s&lt;/a&gt; a Google doc version, where any comments you leave might be seen by the next person looking (and you might see comments added by others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/10awWMz3DyJi2OibnVlMg-2sipWfZ3jm8P_MyLUbK_ZE/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Here’s&lt;/a&gt; a much longer doc with the reasoning, citations and more comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I continue to guess that long covid is worth avoiding.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="covid" /><category term="advice" /><summary type="html">In case anyone wants a rough and likely inaccurate guide to what I might do if I had covid to mitigate it, I looked into this a bit recently and wrote notes. It’s probably better than if one’s plan was to do less than a few hours of research, but is likely flawed all over the place and wasn’t written with public sharing in mind, and um, isn’t medical advice [ETA May 11: also safety-relevant improvements are being made in the doc version, so I recommend looking at that.]:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2022-05-07_at_1.35.17_PM.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2022-05-07_at_1.35.17_PM.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why do people avoid vaccination?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/10/why-not-vaccinate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do people avoid vaccination?" /><published>2022-02-10T11:17:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-10T11:17:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/10/why-not-vaccinate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/10/why-not-vaccinate.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been fairly confused by the popularity in the US of remaining unvaccinated, in the face of seemingly a non-negligible, relatively immediate personal chance of death or intense illness. And due to the bubbliness of society, I don’t actually seem to know unvaccinated people to ask about it. So in the recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2022/02/04/long-covid-survey-2.html&quot;&gt;covid survey&lt;/a&gt; I ran, I asked people who hadn’t had covid (and thus for whom I didn’t have more pressing questions) whether they were vaccinated, and if not why not. (Note though that these people are 20-40 years old, so not at huge risk of death.)&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their responses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don’t think I need it, I don’t think covid is a big deal, I don’t think the vaccine works and the more the government/media pushes it the more I don’t want to ever get it.  It should be a private decision between someone and their doctor, not Joe Biden and CNN saying comply or be kicked out of society.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I still dont trust the information and safety claims made by the crooked FDA and CDC. Needs more research and study.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I had a scary vaccine reaction previously.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I am only 32 years old and in decent health so I think I would be fine if I caught COVID. It has almost been two years since the pandemic started and I haven’t gotten sick besides some minor colds. I would rather rely on natural immunity instead of the vaccine.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;dont want one
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Other health issues where my Doctor wants me to wait to get vaccinated.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I think it is poison at worst and ineffective at best. Also the way the pushed it came off like a homeless man trying to lure me into an ally. The vaccine issue has made me lose 100% trust and faith in media and government i do not believe or trust anything from them anymore
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I have anxiety problems and other health issues.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I‚Äôm actually scheduled to get a vaccination, I‚Äôm simply waiting for my appointment date.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The places where the vaccination is available are always crowded and I am somewhat afraid of being outdoors or indoors in large crowds for too long these days.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I am extremely skeptical of this “vaccine”, which has been proven ineffective (vaccinated people keep getting it, and what’s with all of the boosters?!) and has caused too many deaths and/or serious health issues/emergencies. I’ll take my chances on Covid any day over a “vaccine” that magically appeared from 8+ pharmaceutical companies in such an astonishingly short time. That is unheard of, and there is no way to know what is really in it, and what kind of problems those who are ignorant and fearful enough to get it will face later on down the road (that is, if they don’t die from the “vaccinations” themselves. The fact that the government has bribed, coerced, and is trying to FORCE everyone to get this “vaccine” is unprecedented, and quite frankly terrifying and sinister to me. I will NEVER allow a forced injection of god knows what into my own body, as that is wrong in every way there is. Vaccines allegedly keep those who get them safe from contracting whatever it is the vaccine is made for, so why would it be anyone’s business whether or not someone else is vaccinated? The Let’s Go Brandon administration and the dumbocrats that were fearmongering before the administration was even in place have done this by design. Spread fear, mistrust, and divisiveness, and lock people down to isolate them and make them suspicious and fearful of one another. Divide and conquer, because the fascist wannabe communists know that it is the only way to indulge their scummy self-serving agendas. United we stand.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;For health reasons.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I’m not at high risk, so I don’t need it immediately. Waiting to see how effective it is.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don’t think it’s efficient…the prospect of being jabbed by endless boosters doesn’t appeal to me
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I’ve never had covid.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don’t trust the vaccine and have not have gotten covid since the pandemic started. Plus all of the misinformation surrounding covid, from the news media to social media sites. I just don’t know what to believe anymore but I feel that not getting vaccinated is the best option for me.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I am still skeptical of the vaccine since people are still catching covid and its variants
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It doesn’t stop the transmission, or stop you from getting covid.  I am at low risk anyways.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I am at very low risk of infection as I do not work and wouldn’t accept any non-remote work. I also do not have any friends or family in the state where I moved to last year and I do not drink so I don’t go out to bars or events, or even restaurants.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I simply have no trust in the big pharmacy and little more in the government. Throw in the fact that the vaccine was created too quickly and while it claims to have lowered infection rates and the severity of COVID-19, I’ve known several people who have been infected and they were fully vaccinated. In addition, I’ve seen many news articles reporting the same. Why should I receive a vaccine that provides such weak protection?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Transportation and access. If a pill form or some self-administering option were available, I would.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don’t trust it.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I have chosen not to take the vaccine
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Because I think its the Governments agenda to start killing people. I don’t trust Big Pharma or the Government. Also, people still get covid with the vaccine, seems like a waste of time.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I live in Ohio, kinda wanna die. Also, it doesnt even dent the new variants; you still ge tit.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;do not trust them
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Because I believe that the vaccine is part of a either depopulation plan, or a tracking device. Either way there is no logical reason to get it.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I am hesitant because of the possible side effects long-term because not much is known about it.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don‚Äôt see the benefit since I am not really at risk from covid.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It’s against my religion.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I don’t need a covid vaccination.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I’m concerned about possible serious side effects from the vaccine that may show up some time down the road.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Normally, I would consider it, but the talk of forced mandates has really soured me to it. I dont believe in taking away people’s health freedoms like that. I think it’s an insane intursion on civil liberties, and I fear if we all just accept it, we will become like Australia
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I only leave the house once or twice a week so it never really felt necessary to me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest themes mentioned here seem to be distrust or hostility regarding the government and media and their various pro-vaccination pressurings, and the impression that the vaccine doesn’t work. (I wonder how much that one is relative to an expectation of ‘very occasional breakthrough cases’ that one might also trace to someone’s questionable communication choices.) An unspoken theme is arguably being in possession of relatively little information (like, what’s going on with the person who is still waiting to find out if the vaccines are effective? And do people just not know that the vaccine reduces the downside of covid, even if it is still possible to get it? Or do all of these people know things I don’t?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if much good could be done in this kind of situation with some kind of clearly independent and apolitical personal policy research institution, who prioritized being trustworthy and accurate. Like, I don’t trust the government or media especially either on this, but I and people I do trust have a decent amount of research capacity and familiarity with things like academic papers, so we arguably have an unusually good shot at figuring out the situation without having to make reference to the government or media much (assuming there aren’t more intense conspiracies afoot, in which case we will end up dead or tracking-deviced, I suppose). If I wasn’t in such a position, I feel like I’d pay a decent amount for someone to think about such things for me. I guess this is related to the service that doctors are meant to provide, though the thing I imagine would look very different to real doctors in practice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="covid" /><category term="survey" /><summary type="html">I’ve been fairly confused by the popularity in the US of remaining unvaccinated, in the face of seemingly a non-negligible, relatively immediate personal chance of death or intense illness. And due to the bubbliness of society, I don’t actually seem to know unvaccinated people to ask about it. So in the recent covid survey I ran, I asked people who hadn’t had covid (and thus for whom I didn’t have more pressing questions) whether they were vaccinated, and if not why not. (Note though that these people are 20-40 years old, so not at huge risk of death.)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/daniel-schludi-mAGZNECMcUg-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/daniel-schludi-mAGZNECMcUg-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bernal Heights: acquisition of a bicycle</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/09/bernal-bicycle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bernal Heights: acquisition of a bicycle" /><published>2022-02-09T11:46:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-09T11:46:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/09/bernal-bicycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/09/bernal-bicycle.html">&lt;p&gt;The measure of a good bicycle, according to me, is that you can’t ride it without opening your mouth in joy and occasionally exclaiming things like ‘fuck yeah bicycle’. This is an idiosyncratic spec, and I had no reason to think  that it might be fulfilled by any electric bicycle—a genre I was new to—so while I intended to maybe search through every electric bicycle in The New Wheel for one that produced irrepressible, physically manifest joy, I also expected this to likely fail, and to be meanwhile embarrassingly inexplicable and irritating to bike shop employees—people who often expect one’s regard for bikes to map fairly well to facts about their price, frame shape, and whether the gears are Shimano. But several bikes in, when I uncomfortably explained to a guy there that, while the ones I had tried so far were nice, bicycles had been known to make me, like, very happy, he said of course we should find the bicycle that I loved. So I at least felt somewhat supported in my ongoing disruption of his colleague’s afternoon, with requests that bicycle after bicycle be brought out for me to pedal around the streets of Bernal Heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guy would maneuver each bike out of the crowded shop and to the sidewalk, and adjust it to fit me, and we would chat, often about his suggestion that I maybe ride up to the hill on the other side of the main road. Which I would agree might be a good idea, before riding off, deciding that turning left was too hard, and heading in the other direction, through back streets and around a swooping circle park with a big ring road, where I would loop a few times if the mood took me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some bicycles were heavy, and rode like refrigerators. Most bicycles were unsteady, and urged even my cycling-seasoned bottom to the seat while pedaling. Most bicycles added considerable assistance to going up hills.  Many bicycles seemed fine.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernal Heights, on the other hand, seemed awesome. As I paused before my habitual turn-in-the-wrong-direction one time, the house kitty-corner to me was playing music louder than I recall ever hearing anything play music that wasn’t a large-concert speaker. It was truly not considerate. And a middle-aged guy on my corner was having a great time, laughing, and was like, ‘Welcome to Cortland Avenue’. I pulled up and said that I hadn’t been here before actually, and didn’t know what he was talking about. He explained that Cortland Avenue was some kind of peaceful and placid place, and that they could use more of whatever this was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole street felt old-fashioned-okay somehow, and not really like my sense of modern America. I wanted to say it was a bit like the 80s in Hobart (the capital city of Tasmania, where I grew up) but since I’ve barely experienced the 80s in Hobart, I probably shouldn’t say that. Nothing shiny, nothing preying. Yellow things, sincere things, people who care about rock music, people who bought some vegetables, people talking to friends in streets and outdoor restaurants. So many electric bicycles—do I just not notice all the electric bicycles when I’m not on one? On one outing from the shop, a woman called out to me to say that she had also tried the bicycle that I was now riding, the other day, and wasn’t it good? I pulled up to tell her that I was actually struggling to find the ‘on’ switch, and she showed it to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To be clear, I converse with strangers in streets quite rarely in my normal life about three miles away.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a headache from all the bike-trying, and requested a lunch pause. Then I explored further down the street, and found a dineresque crêperie. I was practicing making imperfect choices fast, so in an uncharacteristic snap of decision I went in to get a lemon sugar crepe (which is only a potentially imperfect choice on axes other than deliciousness).  The place was some kind of institution, and the man behind the counter seemed to be savoring the motions of crepe-provision. I had fun ordering, and sat outside. It was so nice there that I repeatedly tried to photograph it, but it wasn’t a kind of niceness that my phone could capture it seemed. Perhaps the fact that I was sitting in the street and didn’t look mildly distressed would convey something to an experienced viewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back at the bike shop, I had a bike in mind for if no amazing bike materialized, and continued working through the tail of the bike options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there was an amazing bike. There was not much visual foreshadowing of this: it was an unsleek thing, painted in an impure grey with questionable red highlights. But it felt like freedom. I could stand up on it. It moved as an extension of my body. An extension full of energy and exhilaration. My smile became round with delight and I swore gleefully. I rocketed up steep streets and to the circle park. I flew around it, elated, bumping over speed bumps, pedaling passionately around the upward side and flying down around the down. Then after quite a relatively long investigation into a bike for which there was no actual open question, I made my way back to the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said I’d buy it.  They looked at their records, and their back storage, and their records and determined that they didn’t have one to sell. This was the floor bike, for trying, and not to be sold. Though they had a slightly bigger red one to sell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They carefully measured me, with a platform and a springed thing between my thighs and such, and determined that the red one was actually the right size for me, and the one I had ridden was too small. I wasn’t meant to ride the red one because it was a new bike for selling, not a floor model. But they would let me take it out a little anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was nice. Was it as nice as the other one? I didn’t know—it seemed maybe less nice, but also now that I was obsessively paying attention to signs of ineffable goodness, and worried, I was probably just having less fun, no fault of the bike. It was basically the same as my perfect bike, but the right size, and possible to buy, and more beautiful, and not obviously less awesome, so probably I should get it and stop engaging in such fun-dampening neurosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back. Then it occurred to me that I could still try that grey bike one more time. I did. It was awesome. It seemed obviously better than the red bike. It didn’t matter if I was caught in some tangle of neuroses: such joy would not be smothered. I stopped by the road and relayed my problem by text to my boyfriend, who wisely started googling for other stores that might have such a bike. Then I took photographs of the bike from all sides in the sun by the park. Then my phone with connectivity died. (For reasons to do with my own forgetfulness re phone charging and complications of phone plans, I had brought two phones: one with power, and one with connectivity.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rode around and mentally rehearsed purchasing the floor bike. Did they need a floor bike for which they have no actual corresponding salable bikes? I’d pay as much as for a new bike. I’d pay more. They would be astonished and grateful. I’d talk to the manager, who would be free to disregard floor bike protocol, for such an exceptional case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to the store.  No, they would not sell me the floor bike. It didn’t belong to them. I could buy it in months, when floor bikes get replaced or something. I was also told: don’t do that—I hadn’t seen what the customers did to floor bikes. (What could customers possibly be doing to floor bikes to warrant such fear?) ‘Months’ was also about how long it would take them to order in a new bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They let me use their wifi, and I reached my boyfriend again with my charged phone, and he had actually phoned a bunch of bike shops, like some kind of hero (or some kind of superhero with the ability to just talk to people in shops on the phone—if I phoned a bike shop, they might say something like “phh shu anganga mph ghe?” and I’d say I couldn’t hear them, but they wouldn’t hear me, and we’d go back and forth like that a few times, until it became too embarrassing to be borne). He had located a couple of very similar bikes, possibly one of them identical, at other bike shops in San Francisco and nearby Berkeley. I decided to go home and charge my phone, and so ended my and The New Wheel’s long afternoon together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At home, I charged my phone and acknowledged my failings re phone charging, and bravely acted on my boyfriend’s claim that it would be reasonable to just phone the most promising bike shop back to check it really was the same bike they had, before spending over an hour driving to Berkeley. It also became apparent that my other boyfriend would not hate taking me on a long bicycle-pursuing excursion in his car that evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we set out, me feeling kind of defensive and silly, because I could have got a bike that was better on every front except for ‘ineffable greatness’ hours earlier and with a lot less bothering other people. I vaguely attempted to defend myself as we went over the bridge, but it didn’t seem very necessary, and we got on to more interesting conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bike shop, it turned out, was a few doors away from a house I used to live in, between a coffee shop with romantic memories, and a bench with different romantic memories, from multiple ancient times. Stepping into the thick past, I left my boyfriend to park the car and walked up to the new shop. It was a big warmly lit warehouse room, which I didn’t remember seeing when I lived here. Friendly: a place of children in baskets and wholesome rolled-up-trouser types. I read out the string identifying my desires to a plump, friendly man: “Gazelle ultimate T10+ 46inch”. He went looking for the corresponding item amidst the central sea of handlebars and frames. He couldn’t find it. Strange. He consulted his records, and the back storage, and his records, and another bike shop man. At last, it was right there—the problem had been that the record said that the bike was ‘dust’ colored, and he understandably hadn’t considered that someone would come up with that name for my beloved bike’s reddish-grey tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relieved but further paranoid for the preservation of the hard-to-measure magic, I got out my photographs from earlier, and asked him if there was anything different between the photograph and this bike. There was! The other bike had had some kind of fancy suspension seat post installed. They had the same for sale, so I asked for it. I rode the bike around half the block and back, and couldn’t tell if it was amazing, but it really was a short and constrained ride, and what more could I reasonably do? I bought it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could barely push its giant, heavy body into the back of the car, and it made an alarming cracking sound, which hopefully was just the light changing position. We took it home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day, I took it out for a little ride, and it was great to power up the hills of San Francisco, and shoot along the flats. It’s the kind of bike that only adds power when you pedal, so it seemed that riding was still a lot of exercise, but your exertions got you all around the city, instead of half way up the nearest hill. And while I just meant to have a little ride, I went further around the city than I may have ever been on a single outing. What had been an intractable country of mountainous slopes and distances and intersections like war zones was shrunk to my scale. And I felt safer, though faster, because usually getting out of the way of things requires my own feeble strength, which might be completely overcome by starting on a little bit of a bump or something. Now I could more move when I wanted. And I could go fast enough to feel no guilt riding in the middle of the car lane, rather than the door-prone bicycle lane. I was as about as fast as cars, and nimble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to admit though that it wasn’t the joy I had sought so hard. It was merely mundanely good. And I was tense, and San Francisco was frightening, and cars were everywhere, and it was all exhausting. Maybe now I was just too stressed, and it would be good later? Or maybe the bike was somehow adjusted slightly wrong, and the potential for that same joy could never be found among the myriad possible positional combinations? About twenty minutes from home, I realized that I actually couldn’t leave the bike and walk without my back hurting a lot. So, questionably, I got back on it, which was bearable, and rode home. I spent the next day or so in bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shorter rides favored the hypothesis that it was fun but not extraordinary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned to the first bike shop, and asked a man there to adjust my new bike to be exactly like their floor bike, ignoring the very likely possibility that they had adjusted the floor bike since my visit. He didn’t seem to obviously understand either the situation or my request, but was willing to make some changes, and phone me when done. He also sold me an expensive lock and some neat (and expensive) panniers. I went and tried to buy crepes, but the store was closed. But then I found a cafe and a restaurant next door to each other with back patios, a recent passion of mine, and took a nice iced coffee from one to the other, where I ate fries and read about words for an hour, in the company of a cat, someone else reading a book, and some kind of raw European music. It was pretty good. My phone died, because my life is too complicated and/or I’m an idiot. I went back to the bike store. He had changed some things, such as—promisingly—the angle of the handlebars. I rode home via the circle park, detouring to fly around it, iced coffee lodged in my front gear cables. It seemed amazing. But I’m uncertain, and doesn’t that mean it wasn’t? Well I smiled a lot on the way home, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="bernalheights" /><category term="mundane" /><summary type="html">The measure of a good bicycle, according to me, is that you can’t ride it without opening your mouth in joy and occasionally exclaiming things like ‘fuck yeah bicycle’. This is an idiosyncratic spec, and I had no reason to think that it might be fulfilled by any electric bicycle—a genre I was new to—so while I intended to maybe search through every electric bicycle in The New Wheel for one that produced irrepressible, physically manifest joy, I also expected this to likely fail, and to be meanwhile embarrassingly inexplicable and irritating to bike shop employees—people who often expect one’s regard for bikes to map fairly well to facts about their price, frame shape, and whether the gears are Shimano. But several bikes in, when I uncomfortably explained to a guy there that, while the ones I had tried so far were nice, bicycles had been known to make me, like, very happy, he said of course we should find the bicycle that I loved. So I at least felt somewhat supported in my ongoing disruption of his colleague’s afternoon, with requests that bicycle after bicycle be brought out for me to pedal around the streets of Bernal Heights. The guy would maneuver each bike out of the crowded shop and to the sidewalk, and adjust it to fit me, and we would chat, often about his suggestion that I maybe ride up to the hill on the other side of the main road. Which I would agree might be a good idea, before riding off, deciding that turning left was too hard, and heading in the other direction, through back streets and around a swooping circle park with a big ring road, where I would loop a few times if the mood took me. Some bicycles were heavy, and rode like refrigerators. Most bicycles were unsteady, and urged even my cycling-seasoned bottom to the seat while pedaling. Most bicycles added considerable assistance to going up hills. Many bicycles seemed fine.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/iStock-871204870.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/iStock-871204870.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Positly covid survey 2: controlled productivity data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/long-covid-survey-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Positly covid survey 2: controlled productivity data" /><published>2022-02-03T22:20:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T22:20:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/long-covid-survey-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/long-covid-survey-2.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This continues data from the survey I did the other day on Positly (some other bits &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2022/01/14/preliminary-long-covid-survey.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2022/01/18/covid-survey.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before asking everyone whether they had had covid, or have ongoing problems from it, or anything else, I asked them about their recent productivity relative to 2019. I was hoping to minimize the influence of their narratives about their covid situation and how it should affect their productivity on their productivity estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clearest takeaway, I think: people who would later report ongoing post-covid symptoms also reported being way less productive on average than people who didn’t report any covid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- tell from this data whether people who had covid were overall less productive - this data alone seems consistent with covid-infected people having a similar range of outcomes, but reporting long covid when the outcomes are bad, or covid somehow improving people&apos;s productivity. --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--ex--&gt;

&lt;!-- The first question of the survey was about how productive people were lately relative to their 2019 productivity.  --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps stupidly, I asked people about their productivity in one of three randomly selected ways, to better tell if results were sensitive to misunderstandings, wording or other vagaries of survey taking. While I stand by this for higher commitment surveys, here it meant trying to aggregate a bunch of slightly mismatched claims about how unproductive a year people are having, when I could have just been averaging a column of numbers. And people did give different-looking distributions of answers for different questions, and different numbers of people with covid got randomized into different kinds of questions, so combining them is messy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The different questions were these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How productive were you this week, relative to your average in 2019?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More than twice as productive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;About 1.5x as productive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;About as productive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;About three quarters as productive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Less than half as productive&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How productive were you this week, as a percentage of average for you in 2019?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;(slider: 0-200%; instruction: For more than 200%, just put 200%)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Were you much less productive in 2021 than in 2019?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Yes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the answers, divided up by question type. Note that the numbers of respondents involved are tiny and things are noisy. For example, the category question only got two long covid sufferers, and one of them was the nurse apparently working 200% as much as in 2019 but fatigued to the point of crashing her car. (In general, productivity varying because of demand as well as supply is an obvious-in-retrospect theme, according to my reading of the long answers to later questions.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;0-200% slider (average %)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Not ‘much less’ productive (fraction of people)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Category choice (average 1st-5th option, higher more productive)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Productivity of demographic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;All respondents&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;106%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;48%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.15&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;108%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;54%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.09&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.28&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Covid &amp;amp; not long covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;109%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;29%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Long covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;70%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.50&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;n in demographic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Total n&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;85&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;54&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Covid n&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Long covid n&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Probably I should have given you the ‘people who had covid more than two months ago’ numbers, but I didn’t and I’m short on time for this, sorry! All the data is available at the end.)
&lt;!-- |if no LC	|115 | 108 |50 | --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be nice to combine all these answers. A natural way to do it might be to assign plausible seeming numerical values to all the answers to 1 and 3 , then average all these values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Maybe that explains why for the category choice question, having covid makes you substantially more productive than not having covid, and why only one of the three questions returned the answer that if you have covid, it&apos;s worse to also have long covid? Not sure.  --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, let’s use the following conversion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More than twice as productive: 200%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 1.5x as productive: 150%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About as productive: 100%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About three quarters as productive: 75%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less than half as productive: 50%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question 3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yes (i.e. much less productive): 80%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No: 100%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- I expect this could be done better, but I am already spending too long on it. I didn&apos;t mess around with these to get more desirable answers. The only thing I fiddled with was changing &apos;No&apos; to question 3 from 120% to 100%, because after a little more thought it seemed more reasonable as a guess for how productive a person is if they say they aren&apos;t way less productive. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Respondents&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Average productivity relative to 2019*&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;n&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;All&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;106%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;106%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Long covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;89%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Covid &amp;amp; not LC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;110%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;106%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;*According to above described questionable quantification procedure (for those of you skipping to the table)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;!-- We can possibly make this slightly better by supposing that the different groups should have had the same average, and dividing everything by the average productivity for that question:

|Respondents | Productivity relative to 2019* | n |
|--|--|--|
|All |	106%| 228 |
|Covid |	106%| 56 |
|Long covid|	89%| 12 |
|Covid &amp; not LC |	110%| 44 |
|No covid|	106%| 172 | --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different thing to do is call everything below 80% ‘much less productive’ then convert everything into fraction of people avoiding that fate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Demographic&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;P(not much less productive)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;n&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;All&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;68%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;228&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Long covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Covid &amp;amp; not LC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;75%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No covid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;69%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘covid &amp;amp; not LC’ category is notably more productive than the ‘no covid’ category in both combinings, which seems interesting. Some things that might be going on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Covid is overall negligibly bad for productivity, and the quarter of people whose lives would have gotten worse lately anyway classify it as ‘long covid’, leaving the other covid sufferers unusually productive. (This being the main thing going on seems inconsistent with other evidence to me, but maybe there’s some of that, or maybe my understanding of the other evidence is mistaken.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who get long covid are disproportionately those whose productivities were on a less uphill trajectory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who get covid and not long covid have a relatively productive time because they are freed from avoiding covid, whereas people without covid are often paying costs that are a large fraction of the cost of having covid to avoid it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maybe people’s sense of their own productivity is higher when they had reason that it might be low.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maybe people with covid but no ongoing problems are disproportionately in households with other people who have some kind of problem from covid (including for instance having died, or having lost income from a brief illness), and capable of helping, and so are being more productive by necessity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This data is so meagre and messy that reading anything into it that’s not about a huge effect is a mistake, and this is already too much thought on the topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to think it’s the latter, but if anyone wants to actually do statistics, or anything else with this data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1RcGe3ZiizCkSnCPtLE7UiYQr7TdNTxF1kdJpoWM8j-A/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- , but I&apos;m just saying the data here seems to suggest it. Though not that strongly I think, because all of this is so noisy that even if that was the story I wouldn&apos;t expect it to line up that nicely.) --&gt;

&lt;!-- It&apos;s interesting that covid and no covid come out the same here, in spite of huge variation in general, and covid being comprised one quarter by long covid sufferers who are 15% less productive. In particular, it isn&apos;t just that the &apos;covid&apos; category is full of people who don&apos;t have long covid, bringing it up to normal. The people who don&apos;t report long covid are actually claiming to be more productive than people without covid at all, and what&apos;s more, exactly enough more to make up for how unproductive the long covid sufferers are.

xxx[but this isn&apos;t even right, because the covid should be &gt;2mo old, which makes covid even better, so no more the coincidence]

These two things&amp;mdash;that the non-LC folks are more productive, and that they are exactly the balancing amount more productive&amp;mdash;point at a story where covid is negligibly bad for people, and the quarter of people whose lives would have gotten worse lately anyway classify it as &apos;long covid&apos;. (This sounds fairly implausible to me for other reasons, but I&apos;m just saying the data here seems to suggest it. Though not that strongly I think, because all of this is so noisy that even if that was the story I wouldn&apos;t expect it to line up that nicely.)

Is that what&apos;s going on? Some other things that might be going on:
- The bizarro question where the more covid you have the better has disproportionately many covid-havers randomized into it, and disproportionately few long-covid-havers. It also has substantially higher average numbers. Supposing the higher numbers for that question are an artifact of the question somehow, this increases the apparent productivity of people who had covid but not long covid. xxx

Maybe looking at the data separately first will help.



However this seems like a coincidence of the numbers I chose, which doesn&apos;t show up otherwise (xxx check). We can tell these numbers are bad, because they lead to very different average productivities based on which category you are randomized into. (Though possibly there is no way to rectify this.)

Note that two of the kinds of questions find that no covid is better than covid. Though only one of the three finds that no long covid is better than long covid. The category choice column is pretty weird, getting both of these counterintuitive answers. It also has an unusually high rate of covid cases and low rate of long covid cases, and generally very high productivity numbers. So probably this is just making people with covid and no long covid look extra productive.

On second thought, I think combining them may be too hard to do well.

but my first attempt to quickly correct for this error still has the pattern, so that&apos;s interesting.

&lt;!-- A different thing to do:

|Situation per later answers | P(not much less productive) | n |
|--|--|--|
|All |	68% | 228 |
|Covid |	64%| 56 |
|Long covid|	25%| 12 |
|Covid &amp; not LC |	75%| 44 |
|No covid|	69%| 172 | --&gt;

&lt;!-- This thing where people who had covid and didn&apos;t have long covid are more productive than people without covid seems at least a bit consistent, and is interesting. One hypothesis it suggests is that some amount of badness that would happen anyway is being counted as long covid.




(Note that I didn&apos;t remove the nurse who was at 200% productivity and attributed crashing her car to fatigue, though that seems like an example that shouldn&apos;t really be bringing the average expected outcome of long covid up a lot.)

Note that productivity is a weird thing to measure, and that the data seems to include various people whose productivity is being impacted by the need for productivity rather than the ease of it: the twice-infected nurse who says she has long covid but also that she is twice as productive as in 2019 (though does attribute a recent car crash to fatigue). People become sole supporters of families when their partners get sick or lose jobs, workplaces become short staffed, people need to look after children on top of whatever of their usual responsibilities can be salvaged. Glancing through the longer answers for people with covid who are more productive, I don&apos;t know what&apos;s going on. xxx[true?] Glancing through the longer answers for people with long covid who are less productive, it&apos;s also not always super clear what&apos;s going on, but a fair bit seems to have the straightforward narrative you might expect.  --&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="covid" /><category term="survey" /><summary type="html">(This continues data from the survey I did the other day on Positly (some other bits here and here.) Before asking everyone whether they had had covid, or have ongoing problems from it, or anything else, I asked them about their recent productivity relative to 2019. I was hoping to minimize the influence of their narratives about their covid situation and how it should affect their productivity on their productivity estimates. The clearest takeaway, I think: people who would later report ongoing post-covid symptoms also reported being way less productive on average than people who didn’t report any covid.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/ad7dcf12-e166-4214-a4fa-6e7ff1f4972a" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/ad7dcf12-e166-4214-a4fa-6e7ff1f4972a" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Positly covid survey: long covid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/covid-survey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Positly covid survey: long covid" /><published>2022-01-17T21:05:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T21:05:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/covid-survey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/17/covid-survey.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some more careful results from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2022/01/14/preliminary-long-covid-survey.html&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; I ran the other day on &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.positly.com/&quot;&gt;Positly&lt;/a&gt;, to test whether it’s trivial to find people who have had their lives seriously impacted by long covid, and to get a better sense of the distribution of what people mean by things like ‘brain fog’, in bigger, vaguer, research efforts.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respondents are from the US, aged 20-40, and decided to take the survey—entitled ‘Lifestyle 2022’ with a longer description mentioning the pandemic—when offered good compensation for doing so, a couple of days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;most-basic-results&quot;&gt;Most basic results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;228 responses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;56 people thought they have had covid; seven or eight of them on multiple occasions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 had ongoing health problems or symptoms after recovering from acute illness (21% of those infected)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the basic long covid question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do you seem to have ongoing health problems or symptoms after recovering from acute covid illness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, it seems misinterpretable, but looking at other responses (see very bottom for all questions, or section ‘How bad are these long covid cases’ for more details on most of them), I don’t think they misinterpreted it much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-covid-from-cases-over-two-months-ago-by-vaccination-status&quot;&gt;Long covid from cases over two months ago, by vaccination status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most basic results are not so telling, because maybe all of those people with ongoing problems are among the masses recovering in recent weeks, and will recover from everything before long. So here we’ll just look at people who were infected more than two months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let’s divide up rates by vaccination status at the time of infection.
&lt;!-- (It&apos;s nice to have results for people as close to one&apos;s own reference class as possible, so that one doesn&apos;t have to make a bunch of iffy adjustments to figure out what to expect.)  --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minor details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These results are about cases rather than people, i.e. people with two cases are registered twice below (I asked about the date, vaccination status and health consequences for each, so e.g. one person says they got long covid from the second case, so the first is counted under ‘no LC’).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;‘Vaccinated’ = at least a full one or two shot course for two weeks&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;All&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Vac&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;No vac&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(Vac N/A)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;All&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;LC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;no LC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;P(LC)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.23&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.23&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, in this (small) group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around quarter of cases of covid &amp;gt;2 months ago were reported to precede some kind of ongoing health problems or symptoms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around a sixth of covid cases happened to people vaccinated at the time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For vaccinated cases, the rate of long covid was about the same as for unvaccinated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or to put it visually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/ad7dcf12-e166-4214-a4fa-6e7ff1f4972a&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/LCvac.png?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;LCvac&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-bad-are-these-long-covid-cases&quot;&gt;How bad are these long covid cases?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A thing I wanted to know was how bad these ongoing symptoms are for people. So I asked some more quantitative questions, as well as for open-ended descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only nine cases of long covid from more than two months ago, and I asked people a few different things about them, so it seems easier to tell you their answers than to try to summarize, especially because I think it’s helpful to see all of a person’s answers together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/ec1a1890-1e39-4a2b-843d-c8a475232ddc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2022-01-17_at_10.25.31_PM.png?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;Screen_Shot_2022-01-17_at_10.25.31_PM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/6c0225a5-5cbf-4dfa-96d3-e352e8f0357c&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;full-width&quot; src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2022-01-17_at_10.26.00_PM.png?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;Screen_Shot_2022-01-17_at_10.26.00_PM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(8th column heading ends: “…you were on average in 2019”; for the second column, other options that nobody in this group agreed to were ‘I am unable to walk up stairs without resting afterward’, and ‘A doctor has diagnosed me with having specific organ damage’.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking answers at face value, about eight of these sound pretty bad to me, just on column Q grounds. However it seems likely that some amount of miscommunication is going on, so I trust more impressions coming from several questions. On that basis, maybe half sound like very likely a big deal to me, holistically (and most of the others plausibly so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be maybe continued later…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Maybe coming up later: What’s going on with all these people who don’t want to be vaccinated? Are people still taking many precautions? Which ones? What fraction of people’s covid-infected acquaintances seem to be severely ongoingly unwell from it? —I had a lot of prepaid survey-taking minutes from people who didn’t have covid with which to satisfy some of my pandemic curiosities.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-guidedtrackcom-code-for-this-survey&quot;&gt;Full guidedtrack.com code for this survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;*randomize: 1
	*group
		*question: How productive were you this week, relative to your average in 2019?
			More than twice as productive
			About 1.5x as productive
			About as productive
			About three quarters as productive
			Less than half as productive
	*group
		*question: How productive were you this week, as a percentage of average for you in 2019?
			*type: slider
			*after: %
			*max: 200
			*before: For more than 200%, just put 200%
			*save: slidersave
	*group
		*question: Were you much less productive in 2021 than in 2019?
			Yes
			No

*question: Have you had covid?
	Yes
		*set: covid
	No
		*set: nocovid
	Unsure
		*set: unsurecovid

*if: covid
	*question: Have you had covid more than once?
		No
		Yes
			*set: multicovid
		Unsure

	*if: not multicovid
		*question: When did you get covid, roughly?
			*type: calendar

	*if: multicovid
		*question: When did you get covid each time, roughly?
			*type: paragraph

	*question: Were you vaccinated when you got covid?
		No
		Partially
		Yes, I&apos;d had a full 1 or 2 shot course of vaccination for more than two weeks
		Yes, and boosted for more than two weeks
		I&apos;ve had covid multiple times, and the answer is different for different times

	*question: Do you seem to have ongoing health problems or symptoms after recovering from acute covid illness?
		Yes
			*set: longcovid
		No
		Too soon to say
		*tip: If you have had covid more than once, answer yes if any bout of covid led to ongoing health problems


*if: not covid
	*question: How much are you taking precautions to avoid covid at the moment?
		Not at all
		A little
		Some
		A lot
		Very intensely
		*save: cautionlevelslider

	*question: Where do you think you fit among the population in taking precautions to avoid covid at the moment?
		Among the least cautious 20% of people
		Among the second least cautious 20% of people
		In the middle 20% of people
		Among the second most cautious 20% of people
		Among the most cautious 20%
		*save: cautionlevelslider

	*question: What precautions are you taking lately to avoid covid?
		*type: checkbox
		Avoiding indoor crowds
		Wearing masks indoors
		Wearing masks outdoors
		Reducing time indoors with friends
		Avoiding offices
		Caring for children to keep them from a high exposure setting
		Wearing high quality masks, such as N95, KN95 or P100 masks
		Washing or hand sanitizing extra
		Reducing travel
		Reducing time in stores
		Using rapid tests before spending time together
		Moving activities outdoors

	*question: How many people do you know who had covid at least two months ago and survived?
		*type: number
		*tip: A rough guess is fine.

	*question: How many of them are less than 40 years old?
		*type: number
		*tip: a rough guess is fine

	*question: How many of those people (under 40 years old, survived covid at least two months ago) seem to be having longer term health problems as a result, that probably reduce their productivity by more than 20%?
		*type: number
		*tip: For instance, if your friends Alice (37 years old), Bob (24 years old) and Mary (92 years old) all had covid in 2020, and Alice and Mary have both been too tired to do anything since their infections, then the answer would be &apos;1&apos; (Alice). A rough guess is fine.

	*question: Have you had a covid vaccination?
		Yes
		No
			*set: novax

	*if: novax
		*question: Why haven&apos;t you had a covid vaccination?
			*type: paragraph



*if: longcovid
	*question: Which of these things are true for you, as a result of having covid?
		*type: checkbox
		I feel substantially cognitively damaged
		I had no covid symptoms at all, and have had no ongoing covid-related health problems
		I am unable to read things I used to be able to read
		I am unable to walk up stairs without resting afterward
		My life is miserable
		I am markedly less able to think clearly, more than half of the hours of the day
		I had a really bad time for over a month
		I have lingering symptoms, but nothing that makes my life more than 10% worse
		My senses of taste and smell continue to be off
		A doctor has diagnosed me with having specific organ damage
		*tip: If you have had covid more than once, take into account the results of all bouts of covid you have had
	*question: How much do your ongoing health problems from covid reduce your capacity to do things you would have normally done in a day?
		*type: slider
		*after: %

	*if: multicovid
		*question: Which bout(s) of covid led to ongoing health problems for you?
			*type: paragraph
			*tip: e.g. &quot;second&quot;, or &quot;both&quot;

	*question: Would you rather:
		A) be rid of ongoing covid related health issues and symptoms forever
			*set: prefcovone
		B) a 10% increase in your income this year
		C) Not applicable

	*if: prefcovone
		*question: Would you rather:
			A) be rid of ongoing covid related health issues and symptoms forever
				*set: prefcovtwo
			B) a 50% increase in your income this year

	*if: prefcovtwo
		*question: Would you rather:
			A) be rid of ongoing covid related health issues and symptoms forever
			B) a 200% increase in your income this year


*question: Are you currently working less as a result of the covid pandemic?
	*type: checkbox
	Yes, because I had covid and it left me with ongoing problems with physical or mental health
	Yes, because of reduced availability of work
	Yes, to avoid covid risks at work
	Yes, to care for others (e.g. children)
	Yes, because of other distractions, burdens or mental health issues stemming from the situation
	Yes, for other reasons
	No, I work as much as usual
	*save: work

*question: Roughly how many fewer hours do you think you are working per week than you were on average in 2019?
	*type: number
	*after: hours
	*tip: e.g. If you used to work about 40 hours per week, and recently work about 35 hours per week, put &quot;5 hours&quot;

*question: Do you have any chronic illness unrelated to covid?
	Yes
	No
	Prefer not to say

*if: covid
	*question: In words, please tell us about the biggest impacts that having covid has had on your life
		*type: paragraph
		*blank
		*tip: Numbers are especially helpful, e.g. &apos;I probably lose about ten minutes a day to coughing fits&apos;, or &apos;20% reduction in my ability to work&apos;, or &apos;I used to run two miles a day, but now I can only manage one&apos;.

*question: In words, please tell us about the biggest impacts that the pandemic has had on your life
	*type: paragraph
	*blank
	*tip: Numbers are especially helpful, e.g. &apos;I lose about twenty hours a week looking after my children because I can&apos;t send them to childcare&apos;, or &apos;50% reduction in income, due to lack of available work&apos;, or &apos;I used to go to the gym twice a week, but it has mostly been closed&apos;.


*question: Anything else you&apos;d like to say?
	*type: paragraph
	*blank

Thank you!

*program: EndOfActivityButton
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bla&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="covid" /><category term="advice" /><summary type="html">Here are some more careful results from a survey I ran the other day on Positly, to test whether it’s trivial to find people who have had their lives seriously impacted by long covid, and to get a better sense of the distribution of what people mean by things like ‘brain fog’, in bigger, vaguer, research efforts.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/ad7dcf12-e166-4214-a4fa-6e7ff1f4972a" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://photobucket.com/u/katjasgrace/p/ad7dcf12-e166-4214-a4fa-6e7ff1f4972a" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>