<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-21T03:49:15-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Elephant seal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/elephant-seal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elephant seal" /><published>2020-12-21T02:49:12-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-21T02:49:12-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/elephant-seal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/21/elephant-seal.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/seaelephant2(1).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elephant seal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="seals" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/seaelephant2(1).jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/seaelephant2(1).jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Opposite attractions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/19/opposite-attractions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opposite attractions" /><published>2020-12-19T13:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-19T13:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/19/opposite-attractions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/19/opposite-attractions.html">&lt;p&gt;Is the opposite of what you love also what you love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s a general pattern where if you value A you tend to increase the amount of it in your life, and you end feeling very positively about various opposites of A—things that are very unlike A, or partially prevent A, or undo some of A’s consequences—as well. At least some of the time, or for some parts of you, or in some aspects, or when your situation changes a bit. Especially if you contain multitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alice values openness, so tends to be very open: she tells anyone who asks (and many people who don’t) what’s going on in her life, and writes about it abundantly on the internet. But when she is embarrassed about something, she feels oppressed by everyone being able to see her so easily. So then she hides in her room, works at night when nobody is awake to think of her, and writes nothing online. Because for her, interacting with someone basically equates to showing them everything, her love of openness comes with a secondary love of being totally alone in her room.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bob values connecting with people, and it seems hard in the modern world, but he practices heartfelt listening and looking people in the eye, and mentally jumping into their perspectives. He often has meaningful conversations in the grocery line, which he enjoys and is proud of. He goes to Burning Man and finds thousands of people desperate to connect with him, so that his normal behavior is quickly leading to an onslaught of connecting that is more than he wants. He finds himself savoring the impediments to connection—the end of an eye-gazing activity, the chance to duck out of a conversation, the walls of his tent—in a way that nobody else at Burning Man is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An extreme commitment to honesty and openness with your partner &lt;a href=&quot;https://meteuphoric.com/2010/11/10/know-thyself-vs-know-one-another/&quot;&gt;might&lt;/a&gt; leads to a secondary inclination away from honesty and openness with yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who loves travel also loves being at home again afterward, with a pointed passion absent from a person who is a perpetual homebody.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who loves jumping in ice water is more likely to also love saunas than someone who doesn’t.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who loves snow is more likely to love roaring fires.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who loves walking has really enjoyed lying down at the end of the day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who surrounds themselves with systems loves total abandonment of them during holiday more than he who only had an appointment calendar and an alarm clock to begin with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person with five children because they love children probably wants a babysitter for the evening more than the person who ambivalently had a single child.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who loves hanging out with people who share an interest in the principles of effective altruism is often also especially excited to hang out with people who don’t, on the occasions when they do that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who directs most of their money to charity is more obsessed with the possibility of buying an expensive dress than their friend who cares less about charity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who is so drawn to their partner’s company that they can’t stay away from them at home sometimes gets more out of solitary travel than someone more solitariness-focused in general.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person craving danger also cares about confidence in safety mechanisms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who loves the sun wants sunglasses and sunscreen more than a person who stays indoors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pattern makes sense, because people and things are multifaceted, and effects are uncertain and delayed. So some aspect of you liking some aspect of a thing at some time will often mean you ramp up that kind of thing, producing effects other than the one you liked, plus more of the effect that you liked than intended because of delay. And anyway you are a somewhat different creature by then, and maybe always had parts less amenable to the desired thing anyway. Or more simply, because in systems full of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Negative_feedback&quot;&gt;negative feedbacks&lt;/a&gt;, effects tend to produce opposite effects, and you and the world are such systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Is the opposite of what you love also what you love?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/pexels_taryn_elliott_4231477.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/pexels_taryn_elliott_4231477.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Theasauring</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/18/thesauring.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Theasauring" /><published>2020-12-18T23:10:27-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-18T23:10:27-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/18/thesauring</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/18/thesauring.html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I really enjoy opening a thesaurus. I don’t know why. It’s just a moment of opening it, anticipating feeling around amongst the meanings of different words, weighing their rightnesses, which seems like a kind of heavenliness, sometimes. I think it was better in 2018, and now I’m mostly remembering that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="mundane" /><summary type="html">Sometimes I really enjoy opening a thesaurus. I don’t know why. It’s just a moment of opening it, anticipating feeling around amongst the meanings of different words, weighing their rightnesses, which seems like a kind of heavenliness, sometimes. I think it was better in 2018, and now I’m mostly remembering that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Genetic magic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/genetic-magic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Genetic magic" /><published>2020-12-17T20:13:12-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-17T20:13:12-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/genetic-magic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/genetic-magic.html">&lt;p&gt;23andMe are now willing to guess where one’s ancestors are from at the level of counties. For instance, as well as thinking I have 19% Swedish ancestry, they now guess that it is primarily from Västra Götaland County. Which is in fact where my current Swedish relatives cluster. Their guesses in Ireland center on Cork, with Limerick and Tipperary next door 4th and 8th most likely (of 26 counties), and those two are where the few 17th-19th Century relatives I know about seem to have come from in Ireland, so that also seems pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2020_12_17_at_8.08.56_PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;swedish_ancestry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much as I believe all that stuff about one’s body being full of cells that contain genetic code that is shared by one’s relatives, and about historic movement and mixing of populations being low, it’s awesome to actually see someone take a fairly good guess at what part of what country your obscure relatives lived hundreds of years ago by examining your spit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">23andMe are now willing to guess where one’s ancestors are from at the level of counties. For instance, as well as thinking I have 19% Swedish ancestry, they now guess that it is primarily from Västra Götaland County. Which is in fact where my current Swedish relatives cluster. Their guesses in Ireland center on Cork, with Limerick and Tipperary next door 4th and 8th most likely (of 26 counties), and those two are where the few 17th-19th Century relatives I know about seem to have come from in Ireland, so that also seems pretty good.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2020_12_17_at_8.08.56_PM.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2020_12_17_at_8.08.56_PM.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Some things I’m looking forward to in 2021: probable post-pandemic edition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/some-things-im-looking-forward-to-in-2021.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some things I'm looking forward to in 2021: probable post-pandemic edition" /><published>2020-12-16T23:12:08-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T23:12:08-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/some-things-im-looking-forward-to-in-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/some-things-im-looking-forward-to-in-2021.html">&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fewer deaths all around&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A giant party at my house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A portion of the research I feel bad about not doing just becoming irrelevant (e.g. what’s the evidence about surfaces now? Are we badly underestimating the harms of long covid?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leaving my house in an unprepared fashion and seeing where it takes me&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever it was that I used to do in places other than my house, that I actually can’t seem to remember or explicitly pinpoint and plan from a distance, but which I vaguely miss (possibly this is basically just 4)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeing friends who live in faraway places such as Berkeley&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going on a cross-country train and embracing the general lack of hygiene and space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeing non-household friends without inadvertently spending a fraction of my attention on air dynamics and mask stability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The stakes of everyday personal choices being lowered enough that people being thoughtless or foolish isn’t a critical threat to friendliness, harmony or anyone’s life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping the economy of restaurants and cafes recover&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Casual minor encounters and non-encounters with strangers in shops, streets and cafes (and these being more of the meeting places of the world, and internet comments being less, for more people)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meeting new people regularly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More distinct places and place-vibes to conveniently be in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One fewer area to worry that I should be doing something better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listening to an audiobook on crowded public transit on the way to my downtown office, and then being at my office&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reading and writing in notebooks in cafes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The world feeling so big that you can go to other places and find people thinking about entirely different things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being dirty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Crowded, dimly lit places with atmosphere and mild uncertainty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resolution of this episode&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Watching everyone else enjoy things coming back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="list" /><summary type="html">Fewer deaths all around A giant party at my house A portion of the research I feel bad about not doing just becoming irrelevant (e.g. what’s the evidence about surfaces now? Are we badly underestimating the harms of long covid?) Leaving my house in an unprepared fashion and seeing where it takes me Whatever it was that I used to do in places other than my house, that I actually can’t seem to remember or explicitly pinpoint and plan from a distance, but which I vaguely miss (possibly this is basically just 4) Seeing friends who live in faraway places such as Berkeley Going on a cross-country train and embracing the general lack of hygiene and space Seeing non-household friends without inadvertently spending a fraction of my attention on air dynamics and mask stability The stakes of everyday personal choices being lowered enough that people being thoughtless or foolish isn’t a critical threat to friendliness, harmony or anyone’s life Helping the economy of restaurants and cafes recover Casual minor encounters and non-encounters with strangers in shops, streets and cafes (and these being more of the meeting places of the world, and internet comments being less, for more people) Meeting new people regularly More distinct places and place-vibes to conveniently be in One fewer area to worry that I should be doing something better Listening to an audiobook on crowded public transit on the way to my downtown office, and then being at my office Reading and writing in notebooks in cafes The world feeling so big that you can go to other places and find people thinking about entirely different things Being dirty Crowded, dimly lit places with atmosphere and mild uncertainty Resolution of this episode Watching everyone else enjoy things coming back</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20171208_101559.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20171208_101559.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is it good for? But actually?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/war.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is it good for? But actually?" /><published>2020-12-16T00:09:35-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-16T00:09:35-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/war</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/16/war.html">&lt;p&gt;I didn’t learn about history very well prior to my thirties somehow, but lately I’ve been variously trying to rectify this. Lately I’ve been reading Howard Zinn’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00O2YH8EQ/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1&quot;&gt;People’s History of the United States&lt;/a&gt;, listening to Steven Pinker’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Better-Angels-Our-Nature-Violence/dp/0670022950/ref=tmm_hrd_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=&amp;amp;sr=&quot;&gt;the Better Angels of Our Nature&lt;/a&gt;, watching Ken Burns and Lynn Novick’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pbs.org/kenburns/the-vietnam-war/home/&quot;&gt;documentary about the Vietnam War&lt;/a&gt; and watching &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/Webzwithaz&quot;&gt;Oversimplified&lt;/a&gt; history videos on YouTube (which I find too lighthearted for the subject matter, but if you want to squeeze extra history learning in your leisure and dessert time, compromises can be worth it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a basic feature of all this that I’m perpetually confused about: how has there been so much energy for going to war?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to explain my confusion, because in each particular case, there might be plenty of plausible motives given–someone wants ‘power’, or to ‘reunite their country’, or there is some customary enemy, or that enemy might attack them otherwise–but overall, it seems like the kind of thing people should be extremely averse to, such that even if there were plausibly good justifications, they wouldn’t just win out constantly, other justifications for not doing the thing would usually be found. Like, there are great reasons for writing epic treatises on abstract topics, but somehow, most people find that they don’t get around to it. I expect going to some huge effort to travel overseas and die in the mud to be more like that, intuitively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I’m not confused here about people fighting in defense of things they care a lot about—joining the army when their country is under attack, or joining the Allies in WWII. And I’m not confused by people who are forced to fight, by conscription or desperate need of money. It’s just that across these various sources on history, I haven’t seen much comprehensible-to-me explanation of what’s going on in the minds of the people who volunteer to go to war (or take part in smaller dangerous violence) when the stakes aren’t already at the life or death level for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also not criticizing the people whose motives I am confused by–I’m confident that I’m missing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like if I woke up tomorrow to find that half the country was volunteering to cut off their little finger for charity, I’d be pretty surprised. And if upon inquiring, each person had something to say—about how it was a good charity, or how suffering is brave and valiant, or how their Dad did it already, or how they were being emotionally manipulated by someone else who wanted it to happen, or they how wanted to be part of something—each one might not be that unlikely, but I’d still feel overall super confused, at a high level, at there being enough total energy behind this, given that it’s a pretty costly thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, the historical people heading off to war don’t feel surprising. But I feel like this is because it is taken for granted as what historical people do. Just as in stories about Christmas, it is taken for granted that Santa Clause will make and distribute billions of toys, because that’s what he does, even though his motives are actually fairly opaque. But historical people presumably had internal lives that would be recognizable to me. What did it look like from the inside, to hear that WWI was starting, and hurry to sign up? Or to volunteer for the French military in time to fight to maintain French control in Vietnam, in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Indochina_War&quot;&gt;First Indochina War&lt;/a&gt;, that preceded the Vietnam War?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d feel less surprised in a world where deadly conflict was more like cannibalism is in our world. Where yes, technically humans are edible, so if you are hungry enough you can eat them, but it is extremely rare for it to get to that, because nobody wants to be on any side of it, and they have very strong and consistent feelings about that, and if anyone really wanted to eat thousands or millions of people, say to bolster their personal or group power, it would be prohibitively expensive in terms of money or social capital to overcome the universal distaste for this idea.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="social-science" /><summary type="html">I didn’t learn about history very well prior to my thirties somehow, but lately I’ve been variously trying to rectify this. Lately I’ve been reading Howard Zinn’s People’s History of the United States, listening to Steven Pinker’s the Better Angels of Our Nature, watching Ken Burns and Lynn Novick’s documentary about the Vietnam War and watching Oversimplified history videos on YouTube (which I find too lighthearted for the subject matter, but if you want to squeeze extra history learning in your leisure and dessert time, compromises can be worth it.)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/museums_victoria_udKsjyYNDnQ_unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/museums_victoria_udKsjyYNDnQ_unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The wild</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/15/art.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The wild" /><published>2020-12-15T00:15:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-15T00:15:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/15/art</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/15/art.html">&lt;p&gt;The idea of art about nature doesn’t sound exciting to me in the abstract. Perhaps I remember that I am evolutionarily supposed to see it and go, ‘oh fantastic, it’s green and blue near each other, maybe I’m in for some reproductive success’, and that doesn’t sound very inspiring. (Yes, I know that simple evolutionary situations can feel inspiring from the inside.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a kind of art about nature that I can especially get behind is that which to me evokes some of wild alien vigor of nature, that I sometimes experience for instance sitting in my overgrown back garden, contending with a flock of ascendent giant poppy faces and a stilled frenzy of branches gaining ground and sky about my seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a sharp exotic aliveness, an electric intent for living that wants to overwhelm the strictures of physical space and come curling and unfolding through the air, with an explosive energy that has no truck with time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not alien like an alien mind, but more like an alien spirituality, that doesn’t know anything so mundane as minds. But while you revere under the perfect spires of goodness, it comes in unexpected and unintelligible from the edges and without looking you in the eye, just overwhelms you with how what really made the world is intensely here and intensely not in your understanding. This was always the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Everything wants to live”, my botanist grandfather would explain to me. Perhaps for plants it is often more borderline whether living is in store. Regardless, their unrelenting striving for it is more visceral to me than that of animals. Animals are more placidly set in their bodies. Plants take every opportunity to push outwards, expanding into new limbs and thickening out old ones in their unthinking, unfailing fervor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of nature in art isn’t like this. Often it is idyllic, or evocative at a landscape level, or sleepy furniture for a human story. But here is some art that does portray it somewhat, for me, though I don’t know if the artists actually meant to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/sisley_hillside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Hill Path, Ville d Avray, by Alfred Sisley&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Hill Path, Ville d Avray, by Alfred Sisley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/van_gogh_irises.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Irises, Vincent Van Gogh (1889)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Irises, Vincent Van Gogh (1889)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nla.gov.au/nla.obj-147222502/view&quot;&gt;Myrtle tree in rainforest at Mount Anne, southwest Tasmania, 1984 , by Peter Dombrovskis (under copyright)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some of the same image with these lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Reduced to a Gothic skeleton, the abbey is penetrated by beauty from above and below, open to precisely those elements it had once hoped to frame for pious young men, as an object for their patient contemplation. But that form of holy concentration has now been gone longer than it was ever here. It was already an ancient memory two hundred years ago, when Wordsworth came by. Thistles sprout between the stones. The rain comes in. Roofless, floorless, glassless, “green to the very door”—now Tintern is forced to accept the holiness that is everywhere in everything.” - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jonimitchell.com/Library/originals/jmOriginal_2543.pdf&quot;&gt;Zadie Smith, Some notes on Attunement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="art" /><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">The idea of art about nature doesn’t sound exciting to me in the abstract. Perhaps I remember that I am evolutionarily supposed to see it and go, ‘oh fantastic, it’s green and blue near each other, maybe I’m in for some reproductive success’, and that doesn’t sound very inspiring. (Yes, I know that simple evolutionary situations can feel inspiring from the inside.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blog plant</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/14/blog-plant.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog plant" /><published>2020-12-14T02:28:35-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-14T02:28:35-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/14/blog-plant</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/14/blog-plant.html">&lt;p&gt;I like to have plants in honor of things I’ve done. I’m not consistent or proportionate about it, and admittedly I also have quite a few plants that I intend to be in honor of things I haven’t yet done. But now that &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/&quot;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt; has apparently functional comments and images and analytics, as well as words on pages on the internet, I declare it fully bloggy, and my &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/10/25/new-blog.html&quot;&gt;effort to make&lt;/a&gt; a blog complete. Here’s my blog plant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201214_082858652.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;blog-plant&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome perspectives on good marginal improvements toward WSSP being a pleasing blog to interact with. (I’m aware that the subscription possibilities are not as salient as they could be.) It is a static site made using Jekyll and kept on Github, with its comments looked after by Disqus and its analytics by Google and its pictures by Photobucket.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="mundane" /><summary type="html">I like to have plants in honor of things I’ve done. I’m not consistent or proportionate about it, and admittedly I also have quite a few plants that I intend to be in honor of things I haven’t yet done. But now that this blog has apparently functional comments and images and analytics, as well as words on pages on the internet, I declare it fully bloggy, and my effort to make a blog complete. Here’s my blog plant:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201214_082858652.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201214_082858652.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why quantitative methods are heartwarming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/heartwarming-quantitative-methods.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why quantitative methods are heartwarming" /><published>2020-12-12T12:38:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T12:38:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/heartwarming-quantitative-methods</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/heartwarming-quantitative-methods.html">&lt;p&gt;From Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;If you listened to my podcast w/Michael Sandel, you know we have very different views on whether markets are &amp;quot;degrading&amp;quot;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One thing I didn&amp;#39;t mention to him: This bit in his book cracked me up -- because I remember my friends &amp;amp; I found this aspect of Moneyball SO HEARTWARMING &amp;lt;3 &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/9W6Op30vF8&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/9W6Op30vF8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Galef (@juliagalef) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/juliagalef/status/1337097616639864832?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 10, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t actually seen Moneyball, but it does sound heartwarming, and I have had to hide my tears when someone described a payment app their company was working, so I’m probably in Julia’s category here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I didn’t feel this way though, reading this I might imagine it as some alien nerdly aberration, and not a way that I could feel from the inside, or that would seem the ‘right’ way to feel unless I became brain-damaged. Which I think is all wrong—such feelings seem to me to be a warm and human response to appreciating the situation in certain ways. So I want to try to describe what seems to be going on in my mind when my heart is warmed by quantitative methods and efficient algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using good quantitative methods makes something better, it means that there wasn’t any concrete physical obstacle to it being better in the past. We were just making the wrong choices, because we didn’t know better. And often suffering small losses from it at a scale that is hard to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose the pricing algorithm for ride sharing isn’t as good as it could be. Then day after day there will be people who decide to walk even though they are tired, people who wait somewhere they don’t feel safe for a bit longer, countless people who stand in their hallway a bit longer, people who save up their health problems a bit more before making the expensive trip to a doctor, people who decide to keep a convenient car and so have a little bit less money for everything else. All while someone who would happily to drive each of them at a price they would happily pay lives nearby, suffering for lack of valuable work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not too concerned if we make bad choices in baseball, but in lots of areas, I imagine that there are these slow-accreting tragedies, in thousands or millions or billions of small inconveniences and pains accruing each day across the country or the world. And where this is for lack of good algorithms, it feels like it is for absolutely nothing. Just unforced error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily efforts and suffering for nothing are a particular flavor of badness. Like if someone erroneously believed that it was important for them to count to five thousand out loud at 10am each day, and every day they did this—and if they traveled they made sure there would be somewhere non-disturbing to do it, and if they stayed up late they got up by 10am; and if they were doing something they stepped out—there would be a particular elation in them escaping this senseless waste of their life, perhaps mixed with sorrow for what had been senselessly lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, having found the better method, you can usually just do it at no extra cost forever. So it feels reelingly scalable in a way that a hero fighting a bad guy definitively does not. This feels like suddenly being able to fly, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/11/26/air-walls-and-empty-currents.html&quot;&gt;walk through walls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, it is some combination of escape from a senseless corrosion of life, effortlessly, at a scale that leaves me reeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that might be going on, is that it is a triumph of what is definitely right over what is definitely wrong. Lots of moral issues are fraught in some way. No humans are absolutely bad and without a side to the story. But worse quantitative methods are just straightforwardly wrong. The only reason for picking baseball players badly is not knowing how to do it better. The only reason for using worse estimates for covid risk is that you don’t have better ones. So a victory for better quantitative methods is an unsullied victory for light over darkness in a way that conflicts between human forces of good and bad can’t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another thing is that a victory for quantitative methods &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; always a victory for people. And if you don’t know who they are, that means that they quietly worked to end some ongoing blight on humanity, and did it, and weren’t even recognized. Often, even the good they did will look like a boring technical detail and won’t look morally important, because saving every American ten seconds doesn’t look like saving a life. And I’m not sure if there is anything more heartwarming than someone working hard to do great good, relieving the world from ongoing suffering, knowing that neither they nor and what they have given will be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="feelings" /><summary type="html">From Twitter:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/1jpz3n0x2nfffih/roofs-from-above.jpg?raw=1" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/1jpz3n0x2nfffih/roofs-from-above.jpg?raw=1" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The institution of email</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/the-institution-of-email.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The institution of email" /><published>2020-12-12T01:25:33-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T01:25:33-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/the-institution-of-email</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/the-institution-of-email.html">&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a common phenomenon where people get messages, then fail to respond to them, then feel bad. And the rarer strategy of actually dealing with all of one’s emails promptly doesn’t even seem obviously better. Was that how things were with letters or telegrams? Is it just that there are so many messages now, because they are easy to send?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could email, say, have gone a different way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I act as though I’m assuming email involves implied norms, though I didn’t agree to them. For instance, if someone writes me a personal message, I think I should not delete it without reading it, unless they deserve my disregard for some reason. If someone sends me a message asking me to do something, I act like I think I should do it in a timely fashion, if it is a reasonable request. If I write to someone, I feel like I should make it less terse than ‘ok.’. At least, many people seem to constantly feel bad for failing to uphold &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; standards that are I guess implicitly bought into by having an email address. (And not having an email address would be pretty wild.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was this bad luck, and we could instead have developed happier norms? For instance, that there is no expectation that one read emails, or that responding in about a month is proper, or that tersity is expected, like text messages? Or the norm that you are meant to respond within a few seconds, or consider it dead, like verbal speech? Or the norm where if you want to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thicketforte.com/2019/01/23/information-and-money/&quot;&gt;put something in someone else’s to-do list&lt;/a&gt;, you find a slot in their Calendly and send them money for it? My guess is no - the norms are mostly implied by the length and cost and permanence of the form. Could we have a form that better implies happier norms in that case?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="social-institutions" /><category term="why-this" /><summary type="html">There seems to be a common phenomenon where people get messages, then fail to respond to them, then feel bad. And the rarer strategy of actually dealing with all of one’s emails promptly doesn’t even seem obviously better. Was that how things were with letters or telegrams? Is it just that there are so many messages now, because they are easy to send?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/nth1rr9r5mdg31c/mathyas-kurmann-fb7yNPbT0l8-unsplash.jpg?raw=1" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/nth1rr9r5mdg31c/mathyas-kurmann-fb7yNPbT0l8-unsplash.jpg?raw=1" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>