<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-17T22:18:31-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Schelling points amidst communication</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/schelling-points-amidst-communication.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Schelling points amidst communication" /><published>2020-11-17T09:17:45-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-17T09:17:45-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/schelling-points-amidst-communication</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/schelling-points-amidst-communication.html">&lt;p&gt;If two people are trying to meet in New York City, and they forgot to pick a spot, and both of their phones are dead, so they both just go and stand under the clock in Grand Central Station, hoping that the other will expect them to do that, guessing that if they were going to pick a spot to do this, it would be that one, then what you have is a Schelling point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty contrived circumstance, and I usually hear Schelling points talked of as if they are neat but only relevant in those rare cases when communication is impossible. For instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Focal_point_(game_theory)&quot;&gt;Wikipedia says&lt;/a&gt; ‘In game theory, a focal point (or Schelling point) is a solution that people tend to choose by default in the absence of communication.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was falling asleep last night, somewhere after imagining a kind of house made from genetically engineered trees that just grew into pleasing rounded house shapes roofed with massive leaves, it occurred to me that actually Schelling points are perfectly applicable and even very interesting in cases with communication. It’s just that when there is some combination of a relatively small amount of communication and clear norms about how to respond to communication, then communication often provides a particularly salient Schelling point, so there is not much of a question of what to do, and Schelling points don’t seem relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When many things are being said, or there are other salient Schelling points, or it isn’t clear that everyone’s motives are trustworthy, or probably in other cases, there is no longer a determinate Schelling point necessarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ten thousand oppressed people have to decide when to launch a revolution against a tyrant. If a small number try to revolt alone, they are probably captured by the oppressors and useless to the revolution. So all ten thousand would like to coordinate to fight at once. They can communicate perfectly freely with one another. However there are constantly suggestions that it happen tonight from the youngest and least strategic members of the group, so if such a suggestion is made, everyone has to guess whether this is the one that everyone is going to get behind. Even if Alice is wise and makes such a suggestion, and Bob knows her to be wise, if Bob doesn’t think everyone will be sure enough that everyone will be sure enough, then he won’t want to go out tonight.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Charles and Dick are in a fight, and both would strongly like to not be in a fight, however would not like to stop fighting before their opponent, because then they might get punched extra. They also don’t really want to fight beyond when their opponent is fighting, because if they punch him extra, he will hold a grudge. So ideally they would stop at the same time. But there is another Nash equilibrium at both continuing to fight (i.e. if both were going to fight more, neither would want to stop earlier). So they have to try to coordinate on one of the Nash equilibria. Charles says that he is going to stop now, but that doesn’t inform Dick much, because of course Charles wants Dick to think Charles is stopping, since then he too will stop. But Charles always wants Dick to stop sooner, regardless of his own plans. So the communication is hopeless in normal terms, and at least not automatically a Schelling point.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Here is the table of payoffs for one punch:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;stop&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;punch&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;stop&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5, 5&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;-5, 3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;punch&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;3, -5&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;4, 4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ellen and Frederick are meeting in New York City, and their phones are working fine, and Ellen texts ‘I’ll meet you outside the station in ten?’ and Fred texts ‘yeah’. But Ellen is somewhat tempted to go in and wait under the clock because she and Fred met there once before under highly romantic circumstances, and she is interested in going back there, as it were, but from their current platonic situation, it would be weird to just ask him to meet under the clock again, or to immediately proposition him. She figures that if he feels the same way, and their coordination game is on point, he will actually wait for her under the clock, then come outside if she doesn’t show up. And if he’s not there, well, she tried, and will be a minute late outside. Frederick also figures he might be able to risk-free learn if she feels the same way, and waits inside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might argue that these are not all ‘communication’ in some strict sense of genuine information in fact being cheap to convey. Fair enough probably, but in that strict sense, limits to communication are more common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might argue that these are still all very contrived examples. Which is fair, but I suspect it stems at least partly from how hard it is to come up with examples, especially if they are examples of a game theoretic situation you recently thought of being manifest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume this is not an original point, but don’t know who it is unoriginal because of. If you liked this post, you might like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Strategy-Conflict-New-Preface-Author/dp/0674840313&quot;&gt;The Strategy of Conflict&lt;/a&gt;, which for all I know literally has this point in it, but at least has a lot more good discussion of Schelling points, including introducing the concept.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="game-theory" /><summary type="html">If two people are trying to meet in New York City, and they forgot to pick a spot, and both of their phones are dead, so they both just go and stand under the clock in Grand Central Station, hoping that the other will expect them to do that, guessing that if they were going to pick a spot to do this, it would be that one, then what you have is a Schelling point.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Octobillionupling effort</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/octobillionupling-effort.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Octobillionupling effort" /><published>2020-11-17T00:10:21-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-17T00:10:21-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/octobillionupling-effort</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/octobillionupling-effort.html">&lt;p&gt;When basically everyone in the world faces the same problem, it is interesting if everyone does their own working out to solve it. Even if there isn’t a one-size-fits-all answer, you might think it would be massively more efficient to do a good job of answering once with some free variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, my impression is that even before covid, basically everyone was sometimes possibly a bit sick and had to decide whether to go to an event, given that they might be contagious. The usual thing to do, I think, was to consider the question for a bit yourself (or not, depending on conscientiousness), and to maybe mention it to the host and try to guess how annoyed the other guests would be, and then to make a call. But this isn’t a highly personal question—if someone who knew more about infectious disease contagion than most people (which wouldn’t be hard) made a form to tell you what to do based on your symptoms and the number of people at the event, you would probably already be making a better choice, faster, than most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why doesn’t this happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some answers I can think of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would be great, but it isn’t anyone’s job, and it’s hard to profit from it because hardly anyone will give you a cent for making their judgment for them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would be more effort to open the calculator than the thought most people put into this. (Relatedly, all apparent examples of this are just ‘how worried should I be about X’ where X is something that actually nobody is worried about unless they have an anxiety disorder. There is a form for solving this and it is called a psychiatry intake form.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone made such a thing, there is no way that more than a minuscule fraction of the world would come to know about it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Such things exist all over the place, and everyone else is using them and have just never mentioned them to me&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Such things really do involve a lot of personal information somehow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Few people would trust such a tool enough to do what it said&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This sort of thing just isn’t a thing, and people mostly do things that are things. The market isn’t efficient. Everyone’s personal lives are currently like pre-Moneyball baseball.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nobody knows the answers to these questions. It’s possible to have a better answer than most people’s made up ones (e.g. by averaging most people’s made up answers, or having an expert make something up), but nobody wants to either stand behind that, or pay for it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This case is a mysterious anomaly, but there aren’t many such cases. For instance, can you think of more good ones right now? No.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figuring out the covid risk of different activities is another example of massive potential replication of effort, though in that case &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microcovid.org/&quot;&gt;microcovid.org&lt;/a&gt; (and perhaps others) stepped up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a similar feeling at a smaller scale about speculating about the future of AI, which is perhaps why I run &lt;a href=&quot;http://aiimpacts.org/&quot;&gt;aiimpacts.org&lt;/a&gt; and other people don’t. (While that enlightens me on some specific things that might go wrong with trying to do this, it’s hard for a particular project to shed light on the problems with a category it is in, since it is in many categories and presumably might have problems from all of them.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Yes, I believe the word is ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Numeral_prefix&quot;&gt;octobillion&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuple#Names_for_tuples_of_specific_lengths&quot;&gt;upling&lt;/a&gt;’&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="CATEGORY-1" /><category term="CATEGORY-2" /><summary type="html">When basically everyone in the world faces the same problem, it is interesting if everyone does their own working out to solve it. Even if there isn’t a one-size-fits-all answer, you might think it would be massively more efficient to do a good job of answering once with some free variables.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Schedules versus momentum</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/task-conflict.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Schedules versus momentum" /><published>2020-11-15T14:42:13-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T14:42:13-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/task-conflict</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/task-conflict.html">&lt;p&gt;A mundane issue that arises endlessly in my life, but which I haven’t heard that much advice on: what to do when your schedule says you should do one thing, but you have momentum on a different thing? Or more broadly, what to do when scheduling and energy for a task conflict?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often have schedules (or other intentions around times or orders of activities), and often have momentum or excitement about activities, so I assume these also conflict for others. I include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when a period intended for something ends, and you haven’t finished it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when a period for starting something occurs, and you haven’t finished the last thing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when a period for something occurs and you really don’t feel like it relative to something else that is perfectly productive, but not the intended activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If it’s ‘bed time’, but you are making a lot of progress on writing, should you go to bed?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you mean to stop work and go outside at 5pm, and now it is 5pm and you are in the middle of something that will be annoying to get back to, do you stop and go outside?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you meant to set aside 3h on Sunday for working on some self-improvement things, and it is now an hour into that period because you woke up late, and also you haven’t finished figuring out what you need to do today at all, should you move immediately to the planned time block or finish planning your day and getting up?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you meant to write in your planner every morning before work, and it is work time and you haven’t done it, should you start work fifteen minutes late?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the answer is ‘it depends’: there are some circumstances where you should stick with what you are doing or excited about, and others you should stick to the plan. But I wonder how far to lean one way or the other, or what it should depend on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think in practice it is a thing I make many judgments about without a lot of thought, and without remembering or learning from the huge number of other such judgments I’ve made. Has anyone else done better?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="life-strategy" /><summary type="html">A mundane issue that arises endlessly in my life, but which I haven’t heard that much advice on: what to do when your schedule says you should do one thing, but you have momentum on a different thing? Or more broadly, what to do when scheduling and energy for a task conflict?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The day of Hellfire</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/the-day-of-hellfire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The day of Hellfire" /><published>2020-11-15T00:04:55-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-15T00:04:55-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/the-day-of-hellfire</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/15/the-day-of-hellfire.html">&lt;p&gt;With the 2020 reduction of variety in places and companionship that might set the days apart, there is a risk of swathes of time blending together and seeming short. One solution is to substitute other sources of visceral variety. Yesterday I had the song &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U3NoDEu7kpg&quot;&gt;Hellfire&lt;/a&gt; from Disney’s The Hunchback of Notre Dame stuck in my head all day, which I can recommend as intense and a different vibe from normal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="mundane" /><category term="advice" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">With the 2020 reduction of variety in places and companionship that might set the days apart, there is a risk of swathes of time blending together and seeming short. One solution is to substitute other sources of visceral variety. Yesterday I had the song Hellfire from Disney’s The Hunchback of Notre Dame stuck in my head all day, which I can recommend as intense and a different vibe from normal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Overlooking the obvious</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/13/doing-the-obvious.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overlooking the obvious" /><published>2020-11-13T10:20:21-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-13T10:20:21-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/13/doing-the-obvious</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/13/doing-the-obvious.html">&lt;p&gt;One can feel stupid for not having tried the obvious thing. For instance, if you have terrible anxiety, and you tell your friend, and your friend is like, ‘um, have you considered anxiety drugs?’, and somehow it hasn’t occurred to you, you can feel stupid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is often wrong, because there are so many obvious things. The implicit assumption in the line of reasoning suggesting that you should be embarrassed is that you should have thought of the obvious thing first. But there is at least one obvious thing for every way of looking at a situation. So you can’t think of all of them first because there are so many of them. For instance, having framed your recent life as ‘having an anxiety disorder’, obvious things to do might include therapy, psychiatry, trusting your own assessment of what is alarming less, doing exposure therapy on your own, reading self-help books, exercise, trying to be less anxious.. And if a few days ago you were thinking of your situation as more ‘not being on top of things’, then the obvious things would be different. If earlier today you were thinking of the situation as ‘I really don’t want to leave the house today, for this thing’, then other options will be obvious. And these are all just ways of framing a particular thread in your life. At the same time, there will be obvious things to do about the fact that you don’t have an office chair, and to do about how you like musicals, and to do about being unfit, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t think of every obvious thing immediately, because there are so many of them. You can spend all day doing things that would obviously improve your life, and then have someone tell you another obvious thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An upshot of this is that in my ideal world, people would not refrain from suggesting solutions because they seem too obvious, because nobody would be offended that their friend really thinks it might not have occurred to them to try anxiety drugs if they have a bad anxiety disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible that I’m just uniquely bad at considering all obvious things at all times, in which case that last point just applies to me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="life-strategy" /><summary type="html">One can feel stupid for not having tried the obvious thing. For instance, if you have terrible anxiety, and you tell your friend, and your friend is like, ‘um, have you considered anxiety drugs?’, and somehow it hasn’t occurred to you, you can feel stupid.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Misalignment and misuse: whose values are manifest?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/13/misalignment-and-misuse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Misalignment and misuse: whose values are manifest?" /><published>2020-11-13T00:25:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-13T00:25:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/13/misalignment-and-misuse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/13/misalignment-and-misuse.html">&lt;p&gt;AI related disasters are often categorized as involving misaligned AI, or misuse, or accident. Where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;misuse means the bad outcomes were wanted by the people involved,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;misalignment means the bad outcomes were wanted by AI (and not by its human creators), and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accident means that the bad outcomes were not wanted by those in power but happened anyway due to error.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In thinking about specific scenarios, these concepts seem less helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a likely scenario leading to bad outcomes is that AI can be made which gives a set of people things they want, at the expense of future or distant resources that the relevant people do not care about or do not own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider autonomous business strategizing AI systems that are profitable additions to many companies, but in the long run accrue resources and influence and really just want certain businesses to nominally succeed, resulting in a worthless future. Suppose Bob is considering whether to get a business strategizing AI for his business. It will make the difference between his business thriving and struggling, which will change his life. He suspects that within several hundred years, if this sort of thing continues, the AI systems will control everything. Bob probably doesn’t hesitate, in the way that businesses don’t hesitate to use gas vehicles even if the people involved genuinely think that climate change will be a massive catastrophe in hundreds of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the business strategizing AI systems finally plough all of the resources in the universe into a host of thriving 21st Century businesses, was this misuse or misalignment or accident? The strange new values that were satisfied were those of the AI systems, but the entire outcome only happened because people like Bob chose it knowingly (let’s say). Bob liked it more than the long glorious human future where his business was less good. That sounds like misuse. Yet also in a system of many people, letting this decision fall to Bob may well have been an accident on the part of others, such as the technology’s makers or legislators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outcomes are the result of the interplay of choices, driven by different values. Thus it isn’t necessarily sensical to think of them as flowing from one entity’s values or another’s. Here, AI technology created a better option for both Bob and some newly-minted misaligned AI values that it also created—‘Bob has a great business, AI gets the future’—and that option was worse for the rest of the world. They chose it together, and the choice needed both Bob to be a misuser and the AI to be misaligned. But this isn’t a weird corner case, this is a natural way for the future to be destroyed in an economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Joe Carlsmith for conversation leading to this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai-safety" /><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">AI related disasters are often categorized as involving misaligned AI, or misuse, or accident. Where: misuse means the bad outcomes were wanted by the people involved, misalignment means the bad outcomes were wanted by AI (and not by its human creators), and accident means that the bad outcomes were not wanted by those in power but happened anyway due to error.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Migraine basket</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/migraine-basket.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Migraine basket" /><published>2020-11-12T03:24:32-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T03:24:32-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/migraine-basket</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/migraine-basket.html">&lt;p&gt;I get migraines about once a week. They aren’t as bad as migraines are classically understood to be—in fact they always start out pretty mild—but they sometimes become terrible by the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are always various things I could do to improve such situations, I have often failed to do them promptly. Which seems pretty weird, but I suppose I am not at my most energetic and mentally functional. Also, none of the interventions I know of actually resolve migraines instantaneously, so my sense that I should for instance take painkillers is more of an intellectual one than a felt urge. And I think suffering drains my interest in upholding vague intellectual senses that I should do things. Then even if I did remember, it’s a further effort to even recall what else might be good, let alone go and find the relevant objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved this a fair bit with a retrospectively obvious innovation: the migraine basket. It’s a diaper caddy which typically contains all things that might help with migraines, or some physical symbol of them if they don’t fit (e.g. a pick stands for playing guitar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/migraine-basket.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;migraine-basket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if I remember at all to do anything, I am reminded of, and handed, everything. And the motion to make this happen is like ‘grab or ask for visually obvious basket’ not ‘try to remember if you put your painkillers in your bag and also where you put your bag’. I’ve had it for several months, and it seems good.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="self-improvement" /><category term="mundane" /><summary type="html">I get migraines about once a week. They aren’t as bad as migraines are classically understood to be—in fact they always start out pretty mild—but they sometimes become terrible by the evening.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">And you’ll never hear the wolf cry to the blue corn moon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/11/youll-never-hear-the-wolf-cry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And you'll never hear the wolf cry to the blue corn moon" /><published>2020-11-11T02:21:47-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-11T02:21:47-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/11/youll-never-hear-the-wolf-cry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/11/youll-never-hear-the-wolf-cry.html">&lt;p&gt;Over toothbrushing tonight, my boyfriend and I analyzed the song ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O9MvdMqKvpU&quot;&gt;Colors of the Wind&lt;/a&gt;’, from Pocahontas, which we had just listened to in curiosity over Roger Ebert’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/the-hunchback-of-notre-dame-1996&quot;&gt;claim&lt;/a&gt; that The Hunchback of Notre Dame has a better message than Pocahontas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pair of lines that caught my attention were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Come roll in all the riches all around you&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And for once, never wonder what they’re worth’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suggests that wondering what everything is worth negates what is valuable about it, which is to say, makes it worth less to you. Is it true that looking out for value like this is self-undermining? It sounds plausible to me, but why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first idea we had is that some goals are self-reinforcing. For instance, if you consume things a lot, then you want to consume even more next time, and when that’s hard then you get even more desperate to consume, and so just increasingly focused on consuming, and therefore maybe inattentive to other potentially good things. Similarly for some other goals, such as making money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought is that ‘what they’re worth’ means ‘what you can sell them for’, and what you can sell them for is often a subset of the values on the table. So if you look out for what things are worth and then sell them for that, you will lose a lot of other value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite explanation is that the world is very complicated, so in order to interact with it at all, you have to make much simpler summary versions for use in your head. For instance, you might think of there being a drawer in the kitchen with flour and sugar in it, rather than thinking of there being a whole conglomeration of specks of wheat and splinters of wood and screws and glues and plastics, or of a massive cloud of atoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of different ways of simplifying the same scene, and for different purposes, you probably want different ones. If you are drawing a picture of the kitchen, you might simplify the same part of it to a grainy brown rectangle cupboard front. If you are showing your parents around your apartment, it might just be one of several ‘safe to open’ cupboards, that isn’t holding anything rapidly hidden and alarming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is like a gameboard on which you can play a multitude of different games, but for each one you only pay attention to the few aspects of the board that are relevant to that game. Sometimes you use the chess squares and ignore the snakes and ladders between them, sometimes you just put Go stones on the corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supposing that your brain automatically adjusts the salience of parts of the gameboard for the game you are playing, this means that what game you are playing affects what you see. For instance, if at a party you are playing the game, ‘come up with good insights and say them’, you are less likely to see your friend Fred glance momentarily at your friend Serena than you are if you are playing the game, ‘observe everything about Fred’, or the game, ‘check how people are doing at the party’. In none of these cases will you see the beautiful walnut chair, but you might if you were playing ‘locate beautiful things’ or ‘figure out how rich the hosts are now’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the basic issue is that if you play games like, ‘how much can I sell this for?’, or even ‘what can this do for me?’, you end up living in a simplified world that emphasizes financial and pragmatic possibilities but lacks a lot of richness that would bring value not via either being sold or doing something tangible. Which is arguably a lot of the richness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then a sad thing is that from this vantage, you don’t appear to be missing anything. So indeed it seems the best you can do is collect up that which can be sold or tangibly leveraged, since that is all the world has to offer. Similarly, if you are so hungry for potato chips that all you can see is whether a thing is potato chips, you might conclude that this is a reasonable way to be, what with everything either being potato chips or not, and potato chips being better than not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="review" /><category term="spirituality" /><summary type="html">Over toothbrushing tonight, my boyfriend and I analyzed the song ‘Colors of the Wind’, from Pocahontas, which we had just listened to in curiosity over Roger Ebert’s claim that The Hunchback of Notre Dame has a better message than Pocahontas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tweet markets for impersonal truth tracking?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/tweet-markets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tweet markets for impersonal truth tracking?" /><published>2020-11-09T10:01:22-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T10:01:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/tweet-markets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/tweet-markets.html">&lt;p&gt;Should social media label statements as false, misleading or contested?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s approach it from the perspective of what would make the world best, rather than e.g. what rights do the social media companies have, as owners of the social media companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic upside seems to be that pragmatically, people share all kinds of false things on social media, and that leads to badness, and this slows that down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic problem with it is that maybe we can’t distinguish worlds where social media companies label false things as false, and those where they label things they don’t like as false, or things that aren’t endorsed by other ‘official’ entities. So maybe we don’t want such companies to have the job of deciding what is considered true or false, because a) we don’t trust them enough to give them this sacred and highly pressured job forever, or b) we don’t expect everyone to trust them forever, and it would be nice to have better recourse when disagreement appears than ‘but I believe them’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there were a way to systematically inhibit or label false content based on its falseness directly, rather than via a person’s judgment, that would be an interesting solution that perhaps everyone reasonable would agree to add. If prediction markets were way more ubiquitous, each contentious propositional Tweet could say under it the market odds for the claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or what if Twitter itself were a prediction market, trading in Twitter visibility? For just-posted Tweets, instead of liking them, you can bet your own cred on them. Then a while later, they are shown again and people can vote on whether they turned out right and you win or lose cred. Then your total cred determines how much visibility your own Tweets get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like this would solve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for prediction markets where it is illegal to bet money and hard to be excited about fake money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for prediction markets where it’s annoying to go somewhere to predict things when you are doing something else, like looking at Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for Twitter where it is full of fake claims&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for Twitter users where they have to listen to fake claims all the time, and worry about whether all kinds of things are true or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be pretty imperfect, since it throws the gavel to future Twitter users, but perhaps they are an improvement on the status quo, or on the status quo without the social media platforms themselves making judgments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="discourse-improvement" /><category term="society" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">Should social media label statements as false, misleading or contested?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the fifth day of election</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/election-day-five.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the fifth day of election" /><published>2020-11-08T18:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-08T18:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/election-day-five</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/election-day-five.html">&lt;p&gt;I was woken yesterday by cheering and whooping in the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Which was overall great, though I think replacing the part of the day, [get enough sleep and then wake up and remember who you are and what you were doing and then do some familiar morning rituals while your brain warms up] with [abrupt emergence into city-wide celebration] was disorienting in a way that I failed to shake all day.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some music, Champagne, party hats, chatting with the housemates, and putting on our best red-white-and-blue outfits, my boyfriend and I set out for a walk in the city, tentatively toward b. patisserie, legendary and inconveniently distant producer of kouignoù amann.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a few blocks we found cars and pedestrians breaking into rounds of cheering and waving at each other, and a general sense that the whole street was a party to this. We still had our party hats, one with an American flag sticking out of the top, so there was no ambiguity for other street-goers about whether we were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a detour for downtown Castro, to see if it was more exciting. Apparently that was in fact the Schelling point for being excited together. When we got to the intersection with Castro street, cars were still going through it slowly, but each one seemed like an event somehow. While we watched, the crowd overcame the road entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://photos.google.com/share/AF1QipMCa9vDPnFFj_bvlkjKYfxDVDFCY8tliZ29oN7VRFP5aMDyJqebh3RWVUSajUxIMw/photo/AF1QipNorZHqiyOGLq_5ruTe6OwXolcKcysu94ZJfrc_?key=cmRCcUxaWV82RXpMRDUwS2hYcDJxbzhJNFpCZGxR&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/castroparty.png&quot; alt=&quot;Castro party&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(click for video)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t keen to walk through this, due to my poor imagination for how aerosols work in large outdoor crowds, so we turned back up a side street and went around. Roads seemed fuller than they have been since March, I think with people just driving around for the revelry. I soon wished that I had brought a musical instrument, when my hands were tired from clapping. A couple passed us with little bells in each hand to tinkle. We received compliments on our (very minimal) cardboard hats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Away from the Castro it was a bit more normal. We stopped to get coffee and a woman outside the cafe asked us if we were celebrating the election. “Uh, yes?” “Does that mean it’s been called?” “Yes!” She was glad. She had been aggressively avoiding the election coverage apparently, and I suppose the scene in the park outside the cafe could also be explained by it being a surpassingly pleasant Saturday on normal weather related grounds. The cafe was selling Champagne. We bought a bottle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next park we got to was even less celebratory—at a glance, more full of inert young people at very safe distances, engaged in solitary phones and music and such. But over the hill a group of women were playing loud music and called out to us. ‘It’s our fuck Trump playlist! Enjoy!’ We stood a while on the crest of the hill and looked out over the city. A band of dogs frolicked in the sun, the light making a halo in the white mane of a golden retriever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What are the chances they actually have kouign amann?” For some reason places generally say they will sell kouignoù amann, but then don’t actually have any, or only have one, or are closed at all of the times you ever want a kouign amann. Philz Coffee has been out of kouignoù amann for at least a month. I had a better feeling about this place though. The one time I went there years ago, it had more of a kouign amann production outlet vibe, and veritable mounds of kouignoù amann of different flavors. Still, approaching the bakery at last, we hardly dared hope. I put 55% on kouignoù amann, but admitted that that probably meant 40%, empirically. He was much less optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we reached the bakery, and it had stand after stand of them. We asked if we could really buy like ten of them, or whether this would deprive others. We could. We noticed another case with as many kouignoù amann again. We got eleven, and some cookies and cake too. Then on the way home we stumbled upon another noted kouignoù amann bakery, and got one more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A kouig amann (plural kouignoù amann) is a kind of French buttery sugary pastry. It’s a bit like toffee with quite a lot of pastry in it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="us-election" /><category term="mundane" /><category term="journal" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I was woken yesterday by cheering and whooping in the streets.</summary></entry></feed>