<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-12T23:05:16-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Migraine basket</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/migraine-basket.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Migraine basket" /><published>2020-11-12T03:24:32-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T03:24:32-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/migraine-basket</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/migraine-basket.html">&lt;p&gt;I get migraines about once a week. They aren’t as bad as migraines are classically understood to be—in fact they always start out pretty mild—but they sometimes become terrible by the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are always various things I could do to improve such situations, I have often failed to do them promptly. Which seems pretty weird, but I suppose I am not at my most energetic and mentally functional. Also, none of the interventions I know of actually resolve migraines instantaneously, so my sense that I should for instance take painkillers is more of an intellectual one than a felt urge. And I think suffering drains my interest in upholding vague intellectual senses that I should do things. Then even if I did remember, it’s a further effort to even recall what else might be good, let alone go and find the relevant objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved this a fair bit with a retrospectively obvious innovation: the migraine basket. It’s a diaper caddy which typically contains all things that might help with migraines, or some physical symbol of them if they don’t fit (e.g. a pick stands for playing guitar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/migraine-basket.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;migraine-basket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if I remember at all to do anything, I am reminded of, and handed, everything. And the motion to make this happen is like ‘grab or ask for visually obvious basket’ not ‘try to remember if you put your painkillers in your bag and also where you put your bag’. I’ve had it for several months, and it seems good.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="self-improvement" /><category term="mundane" /><summary type="html">I get migraines about once a week. They aren’t as bad as migraines are classically understood to be—in fact they always start out pretty mild—but they sometimes become terrible by the evening.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">And you’ll never hear the wolf cry to the blue corn moon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/11/youll-never-hear-the-wolf-cry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And you'll never hear the wolf cry to the blue corn moon" /><published>2020-11-11T02:21:47-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-11T02:21:47-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/11/youll-never-hear-the-wolf-cry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/11/youll-never-hear-the-wolf-cry.html">&lt;p&gt;Over toothbrushing tonight, my boyfriend and I analyzed the song ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O9MvdMqKvpU&quot;&gt;Colors of the Wind&lt;/a&gt;’, from Pocahontas, which we had just listened to in curiosity over Roger Ebert’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/the-hunchback-of-notre-dame-1996&quot;&gt;claim&lt;/a&gt; that The Hunchback of Notre Dame has a better message than Pocahontas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pair of lines that caught my attention were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Come roll in all the riches all around you&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And for once, never wonder what they’re worth’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suggests that wondering what everything is worth negates what is valuable about it, which is to say, makes it worth less to you. Is it true that looking out for value like this is self-undermining? It sounds plausible to me, but why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first idea we had is that some goals are self-reinforcing. For instance, if you consume things a lot, then you want to consume even more next time, and when that’s hard then you get even more desperate to consume, and so just increasingly focused on consuming, and therefore maybe inattentive to other potentially good things. Similarly for some other goals, such as making money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought is that ‘what they’re worth’ means ‘what you can sell them for’, and what you can sell them for is often a subset of the values on the table. So if you look out for what things are worth and then sell them for that, you will lose a lot of other value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite explanation is that the world is very complicated, so in order to interact with it at all, you have to make much simpler summary versions for use in your head. For instance, you might think of there being a drawer in the kitchen with flour and sugar in it, rather than thinking of there being a whole conglomeration of specks of wheat and splinters of wood and screws and glues and plastics, or of a massive cloud of atoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of different ways of simplifying the same scene, and for different purposes, you probably want different ones. If you are drawing a picture of the kitchen, you might simplify the same part of it to a grainy brown rectangle cupboard front. If you are showing your parents around your apartment, it might just be one of several ‘safe to open’ cupboards, that isn’t holding anything rapidly hidden and alarming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is like a gameboard on which you can play a multitude of different games, but for each one you only pay attention to the few aspects of the board that are relevant to that game. Sometimes you use the chess squares and ignore the snakes and ladders between them, sometimes you just put Go stones on the corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supposing that your brain automatically adjusts the salience of parts of the gameboard for the game you are playing, this means that what game you are playing affects what you see. For instance, if at a party you are playing the game, ‘come up with good insights and say them’, you are less likely to see your friend Fred glance momentarily at your friend Serena than you are if you are playing the game, ‘observe everything about Fred’, or the game, ‘check how people are doing at the party’. In none of these cases will you see the beautiful walnut chair, but you might if you were playing ‘locate beautiful things’ or ‘figure out how rich the hosts are now’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the basic issue is that if you play games like, ‘how much can I sell this for?’, or even ‘what can this do for me?’, you end up living in a simplified world that emphasizes financial and pragmatic possibilities but lacks a lot of richness that would bring value not via either being sold or doing something tangible. Which is arguably a lot of the richness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then a sad thing is that from this vantage, you don’t appear to be missing anything. So indeed it seems the best you can do is collect up that which can be sold or tangibly leveraged, since that is all the world has to offer. Similarly, if you are so hungry for potato chips that all you can see is whether a thing is potato chips, you might conclude that this is a reasonable way to be, what with everything either being potato chips or not, and potato chips being better than not.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="review" /><category term="spirituality" /><summary type="html">Over toothbrushing tonight, my boyfriend and I analyzed the song ‘Colors of the Wind’, from Pocahontas, which we had just listened to in curiosity over Roger Ebert’s claim that The Hunchback of Notre Dame has a better message than Pocahontas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tweet markets for impersonal truth tracking?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/tweet-markets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tweet markets for impersonal truth tracking?" /><published>2020-11-09T10:01:22-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T10:01:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/tweet-markets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/tweet-markets.html">&lt;p&gt;Should social media label statements as false, misleading or contested?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s approach it from the perspective of what would make the world best, rather than e.g. what rights do the social media companies have, as owners of the social media companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic upside seems to be that pragmatically, people share all kinds of false things on social media, and that leads to badness, and this slows that down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic problem with it is that maybe we can’t distinguish worlds where social media companies label false things as false, and those where they label things they don’t like as false, or things that aren’t endorsed by other ‘official’ entities. So maybe we don’t want such companies to have the job of deciding what is considered true or false, because a) we don’t trust them enough to give them this sacred and highly pressured job forever, or b) we don’t expect everyone to trust them forever, and it would be nice to have better recourse when disagreement appears than ‘but I believe them’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there were a way to systematically inhibit or label false content based on its falseness directly, rather than via a person’s judgment, that would be an interesting solution that perhaps everyone reasonable would agree to add. If prediction markets were way more ubiquitous, each contentious propositional Tweet could say under it the market odds for the claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or what if Twitter itself were a prediction market, trading in Twitter visibility? For just-posted Tweets, instead of liking them, you can bet your own cred on them. Then a while later, they are shown again and people can vote on whether they turned out right and you win or lose cred. Then your total cred determines how much visibility your own Tweets get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like this would solve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for prediction markets where it is illegal to bet money and hard to be excited about fake money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for prediction markets where it’s annoying to go somewhere to predict things when you are doing something else, like looking at Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for Twitter where it is full of fake claims&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem for Twitter users where they have to listen to fake claims all the time, and worry about whether all kinds of things are true or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be pretty imperfect, since it throws the gavel to future Twitter users, but perhaps they are an improvement on the status quo, or on the status quo without the social media platforms themselves making judgments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="discourse-improvement" /><category term="society" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">Should social media label statements as false, misleading or contested?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the fifth day of election</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/election-day-five.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the fifth day of election" /><published>2020-11-08T18:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-08T18:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/election-day-five</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/election-day-five.html">&lt;p&gt;I was woken yesterday by cheering and whooping in the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Which was overall great, though I think replacing the part of the day, [get enough sleep and then wake up and remember who you are and what you were doing and then do some familiar morning rituals while your brain warms up] with [abrupt emergence into city-wide celebration] was disorienting in a way that I failed to shake all day.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some music, Champagne, party hats, chatting with the housemates, and putting on our best red-white-and-blue outfits, my boyfriend and I set out for a walk in the city, tentatively toward b. patisserie, legendary and inconveniently distant producer of kouignoù amann.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a few blocks we found cars and pedestrians breaking into rounds of cheering and waving at each other, and a general sense that the whole street was a party to this. We still had our party hats, one with an American flag sticking out of the top, so there was no ambiguity for other street-goers about whether we were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a detour for downtown Castro, to see if it was more exciting. Apparently that was in fact the Schelling point for being excited together. When we got to the intersection with Castro street, cars were still going through it slowly, but each one seemed like an event somehow. While we watched, the crowd overcame the road entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://photos.google.com/share/AF1QipMCa9vDPnFFj_bvlkjKYfxDVDFCY8tliZ29oN7VRFP5aMDyJqebh3RWVUSajUxIMw/photo/AF1QipNorZHqiyOGLq_5ruTe6OwXolcKcysu94ZJfrc_?key=cmRCcUxaWV82RXpMRDUwS2hYcDJxbzhJNFpCZGxR&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/castroparty.png&quot; alt=&quot;Castro party&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(click for video)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t keen to walk through this, due to my poor imagination for how aerosols work in large outdoor crowds, so we turned back up a side street and went around. Roads seemed fuller than they have been since March, I think with people just driving around for the revelry. I soon wished that I had brought a musical instrument, when my hands were tired from clapping. A couple passed us with little bells in each hand to tinkle. We received compliments on our (very minimal) cardboard hats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Away from the Castro it was a bit more normal. We stopped to get coffee and a woman outside the cafe asked us if we were celebrating the election. “Uh, yes?” “Does that mean it’s been called?” “Yes!” She was glad. She had been aggressively avoiding the election coverage apparently, and I suppose the scene in the park outside the cafe could also be explained by it being a surpassingly pleasant Saturday on normal weather related grounds. The cafe was selling Champagne. We bought a bottle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next park we got to was even less celebratory—at a glance, more full of inert young people at very safe distances, engaged in solitary phones and music and such. But over the hill a group of women were playing loud music and called out to us. ‘It’s our fuck Trump playlist! Enjoy!’ We stood a while on the crest of the hill and looked out over the city. A band of dogs frolicked in the sun, the light making a halo in the white mane of a golden retriever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What are the chances they actually have kouign amann?” For some reason places generally say they will sell kouignoù amann, but then don’t actually have any, or only have one, or are closed at all of the times you ever want a kouign amann. Philz Coffee has been out of kouignoù amann for at least a month. I had a better feeling about this place though. The one time I went there years ago, it had more of a kouign amann production outlet vibe, and veritable mounds of kouignoù amann of different flavors. Still, approaching the bakery at last, we hardly dared hope. I put 55% on kouignoù amann, but admitted that that probably meant 40%, empirically. He was much less optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we reached the bakery, and it had stand after stand of them. We asked if we could really buy like ten of them, or whether this would deprive others. We could. We noticed another case with as many kouignoù amann again. We got eleven, and some cookies and cake too. Then on the way home we stumbled upon another noted kouignoù amann bakery, and got one more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A kouig amann (plural kouignoù amann) is a kind of French buttery sugary pastry. It’s a bit like toffee with quite a lot of pastry in it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="us-election" /><category term="mundane" /><category term="journal" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I was woken yesterday by cheering and whooping in the streets.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where are the concept factories?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/Where-are-the-concept-factories.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where are the concept factories?" /><published>2020-11-08T01:43:52-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-08T01:43:52-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/Where-are-the-concept-factories</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/08/Where-are-the-concept-factories.html">&lt;p&gt;Concepts are arguably critical to our success as humans, our recent success as rich and productive humans, and many of our individual successes at whatever we each individually do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why don’t we produce them in an industrial fashion?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="economics" /><category term="sociology" /><category term="society-strategy" /><summary type="html">Concepts are arguably critical to our success as humans, our recent success as rich and productive humans, and many of our individual successes at whatever we each individually do.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Calling it</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/07/calling-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calling it" /><published>2020-11-07T00:39:26-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-07T00:39:26-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/07/calling-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/07/calling-it.html">&lt;p&gt;In an atmosphere of general thirst for someone calling something, I’ll call some stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience and current judgment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best non-inert art is the musical Hamilton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best place in the San Francisco Bay Area is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldlypositions.tumblr.com/post/172912945074/experimental-ethics-hot-tub-adventure&quot;&gt;Essex Hot Tub&lt;/a&gt;, and the best place near it is Bodega Bay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best undergraduate degree to wish you had done is computer science&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best non-committal snack is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Nutrition-Healthy-Snickerdoodle-Supplement-10-count/dp/B07YYLJL3Y/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_product_top?ie=UTF8&quot;&gt;Mewe snickerdoodle peanut butter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best committal snack is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jonnypops.com/cherry-chocolate&quot;&gt;Jonny Pop’s chocolate dipped cherries ice cream bar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best YouTube videos to watch while you eat Jonny Pops are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLZHQObOWTQDPD3MizzM2xVFitgF8hE_ab&amp;amp;app=desktop&quot;&gt;3Blue1Brown’s series on linear algebra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing about elaborate covid facial getup aside from not getting covid is that nobody can see you crying, which means you can expand your casual Hamilton-listening all the way through the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best underwear is &lt;a href=&quot;https://boodywear.com/collections/women-underwear&quot;&gt;boody&lt;/a&gt; and the best work trousers are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.betabrand.com/collections/dress-pant-yoga-pants-by-leg-opening&quot;&gt;BetaBrand dresspant yoga pants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best morning routine component ignoring costs is a tight race between doing something you have never done before, dancing on a rug outside, and acquiring coffee, won by the first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most beautiful thing is everything, in the right frame of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best color is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/pin/86061042849452453/&quot;&gt;orangey green&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best person to be argued with by is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overcomingbias.com/&quot;&gt;Robin Hanson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best mode of transit is the bicycle, with the train close behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best tourist experience is the do-it-yourself Leo Szilard themed tour of Budapest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best Twitter presence is Lin Manuel Miranda’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best common time is 7:50pm, and the best rare time is 4:55am.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="review" /><summary type="html">In an atmosphere of general thirst for someone calling something, I’ll call some stuff.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Trump? A survey</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/why-trump.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Trump? A survey" /><published>2020-11-06T03:36:27-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T03:36:27-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/why-trump</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/why-trump.html">&lt;p&gt;It felt strange going into this US election so hopeful for Biden to win while so at a loss regarding why comparably many Americans were badly hoping for the opposite. I heard people &lt;a href=&quot;https://samharris.org/podcasts/224-key-trumps-appeal/&quot;&gt;speculating&lt;/a&gt; about the possible motives, and I considered plausible steelmen. But why should I be guessing about what half of people think? I &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/11/05/election-survey.html&quot;&gt;figured out&lt;/a&gt; how to survey some Americans beyond my vicinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I surveyed about 63 people, asking them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who did you vote for in the US presidential election 2020?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What was the reasoning behind your choice?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would be the worst thing about your least favorite candidate winning?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who do you think is going to win?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What went through your head when Trump said that he had won the election already on Tuesday night?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20 out of 63 preferred Trump (19 voted plus one would have chosen Trump if forced to vote). Here is the reasoning they gave for their choices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HE SUPPORTS FOR WELFARE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;spite&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I want a better America!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I like the presidency over the lead of the Donald Trump.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;THE SOCIETY VERY CAREFUL PERSON OF THE ELECTION VOTE TRUMP AND VERY GOOD ELECTION&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SUPPORTING THE WELFARE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the only of good electionship of a best moment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He has been a good ;leader delivering on all his promises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m a republican and i just have to vote for trump because he represents the republican party even though he’s not smart.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IT IS MY OPINION&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;he was an trusted person and good one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe in what Donald Trump stands for. I cannot vote Democrat because I am a Christian who is Pro-Life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He is the most qualified to lead the country, regardless of his character that many hate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I support his America First agenda&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I feel he is the better choice to lead us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supreme court, guns, political correctness.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With the economy precociousending radical race theory, creating peace in the middle east, and working with Americans so that we are treated fairly locally and globally, I believe he deserves a second term to continue his work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trump is saving america from the chi com globalists.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trump has done some good things for the economy. I also believe he has strengthened our national security.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what would go badly if Trump loses, according to these respondents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HE OPPOSES&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fraud against the American electorate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unsure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choosing the right ecommerce platform for the business digital presence is critical. Also to find the one that meets the needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TRUMP WINNING&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HE OPPOSE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He’s not likely to win in South Carolina it is the good election&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The country will be destroyed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Democratic candidate would probably increase the tax on the rich which i think is not fair.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I DONT KNOW&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they will not interact with people directly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turning this country into a socialist country.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A rebellion may start in the country.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Massive increase of illegal immigration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The direction he will take our country&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Political correctness winning, them thinking that since they won, they can go to even more extremes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More wars, corruption in government, and media suppression on conservative thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;China becomes the world super power.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe Joe Biden’s policies would move America away from nationalism and toward socialism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What to make of that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noted yesterday that &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/11/05/election-survey.html&quot;&gt;everyone thinks their candidate will win&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable thing is that a large number of responses are hard to make sense of. A friend suggested many are bots, but none of the apparent Biden-leaning responses are like this, and would bots always claim to vote Trump? (Also, aren’t bots good at writing now?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few arbitrarily chosen answers to the reasoning question from Biden supporters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am a democrat, and I love their policies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I felt we need a traditional U.S president. I also felt he might bring some stability to the U.S.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trump is the worse leader in US history. We need a strong leader now that unites us and helps us move forward rather than creating division.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biden is a Democrat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am a democrat. But more importantly, I am so sick of Trump’s lies, manipulation, and general hateful divisive attitude. We need to get the country together and reassert ourselves as a respectable nation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joe Biden’s policies actually aim to help Americans as well as protecting the environment while Trump is a pseudo dictator who’s broken countless laws and continues to do so, on top of being a racist, misogynistic, terrible person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1m3c13EOE2nlqQVU-1Ekilcz-wxxZVrUEe8Jm7qjsjLo/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is all of the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my summary of the issues that Biden and Trump supporters care about, by number of mentions [ETA: including all that at least two people cared about]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/issues.png&quot; alt=&quot;voter issues&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(There are really about half as many Trump supporters as Biden supporters, but they are under-represented in the graph because I was less able to make out particular issues in what they wrote, whereas Biden supporters often mentioned multiple issues.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="us-election" /><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">It felt strange going into this US election so hopeful for Biden to win while so at a loss regarding why comparably many Americans were badly hoping for the opposite. I heard people speculating about the possible motives, and I considered plausible steelmen. But why should I be guessing about what half of people think? I figured out how to survey some Americans beyond my vicinity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Everyone headed to win</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/05/election-survey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Everyone headed to win" /><published>2020-11-05T13:00:47-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-05T13:00:47-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/05/election-survey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/05/election-survey.html">&lt;p&gt;Last night I was especially curious about why people vote as they do, and whether they were experiencing the election similarly to me. So I set up a survey in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.positly.com/&quot;&gt;Positly&lt;/a&gt; and paid a bunch of people to tell me about such things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t read all of the responses yet, but a notable feature of them so far is the extent to which people expected their own favorite candidate to win the presidency.  If someone said both who they voted for (or would vote for if forced to vote) and who they thought would win, these were the same person 87% of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this just ‘wishful thinking’ (whatever that is) or some more interesting phenomenon?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="us-election" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Last night I was especially curious about why people vote as they do, and whether they were experiencing the election similarly to me. So I set up a survey in Positly and paid a bunch of people to tell me about such things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Election night</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/03/election-night.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Election night" /><published>2020-11-03T21:08:45-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-03T21:08:45-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/03/election-night</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/03/election-night.html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the evening, I reasoned that I should not ‘watch’ the election, since I will learn the result in the end and experiencing the uncertainty in the meantime doesn’t seem productive at all, let alone competitive with other things I could do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This attitude somehow felt unfriendly though, or like being the kind of spoilsport who says ‘there is no reason to celebrate Christmas, or to celebrate anything for that matter’—both failing to add to the fun, and implicitly asking others to defend their own enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s related to how everyone is experiencing this thing together, and whether or not anyone has fun per se, there is something good in sharing it. And I do appreciate being part of a country-sized crowd looking the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish the evening involved more familiarity with voters dissimilar to me though. The evolving plot would be more interesting if every time something surprising happened at a vast statistical level, a camera zoomed in to three random voters from that place who behaved surprisingly, for a short interview on what they were actually thinking. My guess is that it is often more inspiring than suspected, and it would be nice to know the nation better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="us-election" /><category term="mundane" /><category term="journal" /><summary type="html">Earlier in the evening, I reasoned that I should not ‘watch’ the election, since I will learn the result in the end and experiencing the uncertainty in the meantime doesn’t seem productive at all, let alone competitive with other things I could do.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why are bananas not my brothers?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/03/why-isnt-a-banana-my-brother.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why are bananas not my brothers?" /><published>2020-11-03T01:27:20-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-03T01:27:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/03/why-isnt-a-banana-my-brother</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/03/why-isnt-a-banana-my-brother.html">&lt;p&gt;It is said that we share &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/what-does-the-fact-that-w/&quot;&gt;99.9%&lt;/a&gt; of our genes with one another, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/what-does-the-fact-that-w/&quot;&gt;95%&lt;/a&gt; with chimpanzees, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.breakthroughs.com/foundations-science/how-genetically-related-are-we-bananas&quot;&gt;60%&lt;/a&gt; with bananas. (It is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.howstuffworks.com/life/genetic/people-bananas-share-dna.htm&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; that this isn’t quite right about bananas, but reading about that did not quell my confusion.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is further said that I share 50% of my genes with my brother, and that this is why I like him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, I seem to be more closely related to my brother than to a banana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A natural way to resolve this incongruity is to suppose that my brother and I share 50% of the 0.01% of genes that might possibly vary between two humans, which we call ‘50% of my genes’ as a shorthand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this raises a problem. The usual explanation for familial affection evolving is that since my brother shares half of my genes, from a genetic perspective it is half-selfish for me to look after his welfare. So genes that make me care about my brother tend to spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on this new model where ‘50%’ is shorthand for ‘50% of the way between virtually all and all’, taking care of my brother is about as good as taking care of myself (genetically). And a banana is worthy of my kin affection more than I thought my brother was. All living creatures are my family, and all humankind is myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not describe my feelings about bananas, and to learn of a basic biological drive for selflessness across vast swathes of the tree of life would be a bit of a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this actually work?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="science" /><category term="questions" /><summary type="html">It is said that we share 99.9% of our genes with one another, 95% with chimpanzees, and 60% with bananas. (It is also said that this isn’t quite right about bananas, but reading about that did not quell my confusion.)</summary></entry></feed>