<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-10T19:13:29-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Survey of 2,778 AI authors: six parts in pictures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/04/survey-of-2778-ai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Survey of 2,778 AI authors: six parts in pictures" /><published>2024-01-04T17:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-04T17:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/01/04/survey-of-2778-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/04/survey-of-2778-ai.html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Crossposted from&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.aiimpacts.org/p/2023-ai-survey-of-2778-six-things&quot;&gt; AI Impacts blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The 2023 Expert Survey on Progress in AI is&lt;a href=&quot;https://aiimpacts.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Thousands_of_AI_authors_on_the_future_of_AI.pdf&quot;&gt; out&lt;/a&gt;, this time with 2778 participants from six top AI venues (up from&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.aiimpacts.org/ai_timelines/predictions_of_human-level_ai_timelines/ai_timeline_surveys/2022_expert_survey_on_progress_in_ai#population&quot;&gt; about 700&lt;/a&gt; and two in the&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.aiimpacts.org/ai_timelines/predictions_of_human-level_ai_timelines/ai_timeline_surveys/2022_expert_survey_on_progress_in_ai&quot;&gt; 2022 ESPAI&lt;/a&gt;), making it probably the biggest ever survey of AI researchers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People answered in October, an eventful fourteen months after the 2022 survey, which had mostly identical questions for comparison.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://aiimpacts.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Thousands_of_AI_authors_on_the_future_of_AI.pdf&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the preprint. And here are six interesting bits in pictures (with figure numbers matching paper, for ease of learning more):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;1. Expected time to human-level performance dropped 1-5 decades since the 2022 survey. &lt;/strong&gt;As always, our questions about ‘high level machine intelligence’ (HLMI) and ‘full automation of labor’ (FAOL) got very different answers, and individuals disagreed a lot (shown as thin lines below), but the aggregate forecasts for both sets of questions dropped sharply. For context, between 2016 and 2022 surveys, the forecast for HLMI had only shifted about a year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/kvngwylqnpf0tvlf8g8a&quot; width=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Probability assigned to HLMI over time&quot; title=&quot;image_tooltip&quot; /&gt;
(Fig 3)

&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/nllvn2ilyfuifmyoboa2&quot; width=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Probability assigned to FAOL over time&quot; title=&quot;image_tooltip&quot; /&gt;
(Fig 4)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--ex--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2. Time to most narrow milestones decreased, some by a lot. &lt;/strong&gt;AI researchers are expected to be professionally fully automatable a quarter of a century earlier than in 2022, and NYT bestselling fiction dropped by more than half to ~2030. Within five years, AI systems are forecast to be feasible that can fully make a payment processing site from scratch, or entirely generate a new song that sounds like it’s by e.g. Taylor Swift, or autonomously download and fine-tune a large language model.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/lkogl5wintmggyw4upeg&quot; width=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Change in guesses about time to specific narrow capabilities&quot; title=&quot;image_tooltip&quot; /&gt;
(Fig 2)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;3. Median respondents put 5% or more on advanced AI leading to human extinction or similar, and a third to a half of participants gave 10% or more. &lt;/strong&gt;This was across four questions, one about overall value of the future and three more directly about extinction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/czh3xjxt7w1hwtojijeh&quot; width=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Around 40% of participants gave at least 10% chance to human extinction from AI&quot; title=&quot;image_tooltip&quot; /&gt;
(Fig 10)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;4. Many participants found many scenarios worthy of substantial concern over the next 30 years.&lt;/strong&gt; For every one of eleven scenarios and ‘other’ that we asked about, at least a third of participants considered it deserving of substantial or extreme concern.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/pkrmpgh619mzaa703ncu&quot; width=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;Level of concern warranted by different scenarios&quot; title=&quot;image_tooltip&quot; /&gt;
(Fig 9)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;5. There are few confident optimists or pessimists about advanced AI: high hopes and dire concerns are usually found together.&lt;/strong&gt; 68% of participants who thought HLMI was more likely to lead to good outcomes than bad, but nearly half of these people put at least 5% on extremely bad outcomes such as human extinction, and 59% of net pessimists gave 5% or more to extremely good outcomes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/zusla2aogk561nuoejku&quot; width=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;800 responses to how likely the future being different levels of good is after HLMI&quot; title=&quot;image_tooltip&quot; /&gt;
(Fig 11: a random 800 responses as vertical bars, higher definition below)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.aiimpacts.org/api/v1/file/29c9bfb8-5d57-4b5f-9ffe-e50691268b4d.pdf&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;6. 70% of participants would like to see research aimed at minimizing risks of AI systems be prioritized more highly.&lt;/strong&gt; This is much like 2022, and in both years a third of participants asked for “much more”—more than doubling since 2016.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/zk5xgvtclrtpeuc8ymkh&quot; width=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;how much should safety research be prioritized?&quot; title=&quot;image_tooltip&quot; /&gt;
(Fig 15)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you enjoyed this,&lt;a href=&quot;https://aiimpacts.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Thousands_of_AI_authors_on_the_future_of_AI.pdf&quot;&gt; the paper&lt;/a&gt; covers many other questions, as well as more details on the above. What makes AI progress go? Has it sped up? Would it be better if it were slower or faster? What will AI systems be like in 2043? Will we be able to know the reasons for its choices before then? Do people from academia and industry have different views? Are concerns about AI due to misunderstandings of AI research? Do people who completed undergraduate study in Asia put higher chances on extinction from AI than those who studied in America? Is the ‘alignment problem’ worth working on?
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">Crossposted from AI Impacts blog The 2023 Expert Survey on Progress in AI is out, this time with 2778 participants from six top AI venues (up from about 700 and two in the 2022 ESPAI), making it probably the biggest ever survey of AI researchers. People answered in October, an eventful fourteen months after the 2022 survey, which had mostly identical questions for comparison. Here is the preprint. And here are six interesting bits in pictures (with figure numbers matching paper, for ease of learning more): 1. Expected time to human-level performance dropped 1-5 decades since the 2022 survey. As always, our questions about ‘high level machine intelligence’ (HLMI) and ‘full automation of labor’ (FAOL) got very different answers, and individuals disagreed a lot (shown as thin lines below), but the aggregate forecasts for both sets of questions dropped sharply. For context, between 2016 and 2022 surveys, the forecast for HLMI had only shifted about a year. (Fig 3) (Fig 4)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/zusla2aogk561nuoejku" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/lesswrong-2-0/image/upload/f_auto,q_auto/v1/mirroredImages/6uJBqeG5ywE6Wcdqw/zusla2aogk561nuoejku" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I put odds on ends with Nathan Young</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/07/i-put-odds-on-ends-with-nathan-young.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I put odds on ends with Nathan Young" /><published>2023-11-07T21:25:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-07T21:25:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/07/i-put-odds-on-ends-with-nathan-young</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/07/i-put-odds-on-ends-with-nathan-young.html">&lt;p&gt;I forgot to post this in August when we did it, so one might hope it would be out of date now but luckily/sadly my understanding of things is sufficiently coarse-grained that it probably isn’t much. Though all this policy and global coordination stuff of late sounds promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Zum2QTaByeo&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2023-11-16_at_9.12.15_PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;YouTube video of Odds and Ends episode&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="podcast" /><summary type="html">I forgot to post this in August when we did it, so one might hope it would be out of date now but luckily/sadly my understanding of things is sufficiently coarse-grained that it probably isn’t much. Though all this policy and global coordination stuff of late sounds promising.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/matt-power-TpHmEoVSmfQ-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/matt-power-TpHmEoVSmfQ-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A to Z of things</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/03/a-to-z-of-things.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A to Z of things" /><published>2023-11-03T01:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-03T01:25:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/03/a-to-z-of-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/03/a-to-z-of-things.html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to give my good friends’ baby a book, in honor of her existence. And I recalled children’s books being an exciting genre. Yet checking in on that thirty years later, Amazon had none I could super get behind. They did have books I used to like, but for reasons now lost. And I wonder if as a child I just had no taste because I just didn’t know how good things could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would a good children’s book be like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was about sixteen, I thought one reasonable thing to have learned when I was about two would have been the concepts of ‘positive feedback loop’ and ‘negative feedback loop’, then being taught in my year 11 class. Very interesting, very bleedingly obvious once you saw it. Why not hear about this as soon as one is coherent? Evolution, if I recall, seemed similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I finally enact my teenage self’s vision, and present A to Z of things, including some very interesting things that you might want a beautiful illustrative prompt to explain to your child as soon as they show glimmerings of conceptual thought: levers, markets, experiments, Greece, computer hardware, reference classes, feedback loops, (trees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think so far, the initial recipient is most fond of the donkey, in fascinating support of everyone else’s theories about what children are actually into. (Don’t get me wrong, I also like donkeys—when I have a second monitor, I just use it to stream donkey cams.) But perhaps one day donkeys will be a gateway drug to monkeys, and monkeys to moths, and moths will be resting on perfecttly moth-colored trees, and BAM! Childhood improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, if you want a copy, it’s now available in an ‘email it to a copy shop and get it printed yourself’ format! See below. Remember to ask for card that is stronger than your child’s bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/api/v1/file/4c7a89d7-27f8-430b-9c8c-7b8cd61c21c6.pdf&quot;&gt;Front&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/api/v1/file/2e2ed64c-4101-4f66-bf82-86920f10ee97.pdf&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F592e8439-aed4-4cbf-95a5-03f2868bf65e_2448x1590.png&quot; alt=&quot;Volcano and world&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb77660a-0a9b-4598-9452-b7f1e0e58140_2448x1590.png&quot; alt=&quot;Natural selection and orangutan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5dea6d4e-f024-4121-a335-57a47a7e1e3b_2448x1590.png&quot; alt=&quot;PFL and quantification&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5291002-4a68-4f5d-a0fa-79a012aef8dd_2448x1590.png&quot; alt=&quot;Donkey and experiment&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I wanted to give my good friends’ baby a book, in honor of her existence. And I recalled children’s books being an exciting genre. Yet checking in on that thirty years later, Amazon had none I could super get behind. They did have books I used to like, but for reasons now lost. And I wonder if as a child I just had no taste because I just didn’t know how good things could be. What would a good children’s book be like? When I was about sixteen, I thought one reasonable thing to have learned when I was about two would have been the concepts of ‘positive feedback loop’ and ‘negative feedback loop’, then being taught in my year 11 class. Very interesting, very bleedingly obvious once you saw it. Why not hear about this as soon as one is coherent? Evolution, if I recall, seemed similar. Here I finally enact my teenage self’s vision, and present A to Z of things, including some very interesting things that you might want a beautiful illustrative prompt to explain to your child as soon as they show glimmerings of conceptual thought: levers, markets, experiments, Greece, computer hardware, reference classes, feedback loops, (trees). I think so far, the initial recipient is most fond of the donkey, in fascinating support of everyone else’s theories about what children are actually into. (Don’t get me wrong, I also like donkeys—when I have a second monitor, I just use it to stream donkey cams.) But perhaps one day donkeys will be a gateway drug to monkeys, and monkeys to moths, and moths will be resting on perfecttly moth-colored trees, and BAM! Childhood improved. Anyway, if you want a copy, it’s now available in an ‘email it to a copy shop and get it printed yourself’ format! See below. Remember to ask for card that is stronger than your child’s bite. [Front] [Content]</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/5dea6d4e-f024-4121-a335-57a47a7e1e3b_2448x1590.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/5dea6d4e-f024-4121-a335-57a47a7e1e3b_2448x1590.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The other side of the tidal wave</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/02/the-other-side-of-the-tidal-wave.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The other side of the tidal wave" /><published>2023-11-02T22:25:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T22:25:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/02/the-other-side-of-the-tidal-wave</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/02/the-other-side-of-the-tidal-wave.html">&lt;p&gt;I guess there’s maybe a 10-20% chance of AI causing human extinction in the coming decades, but I feel more distressed about it than even that suggests—I think because in the case where it doesn’t cause human extinction, I find it hard to imagine life not going kind of off the rails. So many things I like about the world seem likely to be over or badly disrupted with superhuman AI (writing, explaining things to people, friendships where you can be of any use to one another, taking pride in skills, thinking, learning, figuring out how to achieve things, making things, easy tracking of what is and isn’t conscious), and I don’t trust that the replacements will be actually good, or good for us, or that anything will be reversible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we don’t die, it still feels like everything is coming to an end.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="AI" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I guess there’s maybe a 10-20% chance of AI causing human extinction in the coming decades, but I feel more distressed about it than even that suggests—I think because in the case where it doesn’t cause human extinction, I find it hard to imagine life not going kind of off the rails. So many things I like about the world seem likely to be over or badly disrupted with superhuman AI (writing, explaining things to people, friendships where you can be of any use to one another, taking pride in skills, thinking, learning, figuring out how to achieve things, making things, easy tracking of what is and isn’t conscious), and I don’t trust that the replacements will be actually good, or good for us, or that anything will be reversible. Even if we don’t die, it still feels like everything is coming to an end.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/matt-power-TpHmEoVSmfQ-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/matt-power-TpHmEoVSmfQ-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Robin Hanson and I talk about AI risk</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/03/robin-hanson-and-i-talk-about-ai-risk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robin Hanson and I talk about AI risk" /><published>2023-05-03T20:20:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-03T20:20:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/05/03/robin-hanson-and-i-talk-about-ai-risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/03/robin-hanson-and-i-talk-about-ai-risk.html">&lt;p&gt;From this afternoon: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=em0_p9eL_XE&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our previous recorded discussions are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overcomingbias.com/p/grace-hanson-podcasts-4html?utm_source=%2Fsearch%2Fgrace-hanson%2520podcasts&amp;amp;utm_medium=reader2&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="podcast" /><summary type="html">From this afternoon: here Our previous recorded discussions are here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Have we really forsaken natural selection?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/11/have-we-foresaken-natural-selection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Have we really forsaken natural selection?" /><published>2023-01-11T14:50:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-11T14:50:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/01/11/have-we-foresaken-natural-selection</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/11/have-we-foresaken-natural-selection.html">&lt;p&gt;Natural selection is often charged with having goals for humanity, and humanity is often charged with falling down on them. The big accusation, I think, is of sub-maximal procreation. If we cared at all about the genetic proliferation that natural selection wanted for us, then this time of riches would be a time of fifty-child families, not one of coddled dogs and state-of-the-art sitting rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But (the story goes) our failure is excusable, because instead of a deep-seated loyalty to genetic fitness, natural selection merely fitted humans out with a system of suggestive urges: hungers, fears, loves, lusts. Which all worked well together to bring about children in the prehistoric years of our forebears, but no more. In part because all sorts of things are different, and in part because we specifically made things different in that way on purpose: bringing about children gets in the way of the further satisfaction of those urges, so we avoid it (the story goes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is generally floated as an illustrative warning about artificial intelligence. The moral is that if you make a system by first making multitudinous random systems and then systematically destroying all the ones that don’t do the thing you want, then the system you are left with might only do what you want while current circumstances persist, rather than being endowed with a consistent desire for the thing you actually had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observing acquaintences dispute this point recently, it struck me that humans are actually weirdly aligned with natural selection, more than I could easily account for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural selection, in its broadest, truest, (most idiolectic?) sense, doesn’t care about genes. Genes are a nice substrate on which natural selection famously makes particularly pretty patterns by driving a sensical evolution of lifeforms through interesting intricacies. But natural selection’s real love is existence. Natural selection just favors things that tend to exist. Things that start existing: great. Things that, having started existing, survive: amazing. Things that, while surviving, cause many copies of themselves to come into being: especial favorites of evolution, as long as there’s a path to the first ones coming into being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So natural selection likes genes that promote procreation and survival, but also likes elements that appear and don’t dissolve, ideas that come to mind and stay there, tools that are conceivable and copyable, shapes that result from myriad physical situations, rocks at the bottoms of mountains. Maybe this isn’t the dictionary definition of natural selection, but it is the real force in the world, of which natural selection of reproducing and surviving genetic clusters is one facet. Generalized natural selection—the thing that created us—says that the things that you see in the world are those things that exist best in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did natural selection want for us? What were we selected for? Existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while we might not proliferate our genes spectacularly well in particular, I do think we have a decent shot at a very prolonged existence.  Or the prolonged existence of some important aspects of our being. It seems plausible that humanity makes it to the stars, galaxies, superclusters. Not that we are maximally trying for that any more than we are maximally trying for children. And I do think there’s a large chance of us wrecking it with various existential risks. But it’s interesting to me that natural selection made us for existing, and we look like we might end up just totally killing it, existence-wise. Even though natural selection purportedly did this via a bunch of hackish urges that were good in 200,000 BC but you might have expected to be outside their domain of applicability by 2023. And presumably taking over the universe is an extremely narrow target: it can only be done by so many things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus it seems to me that humanity is plausibly doing astonishingly well on living up to natural selection’s goals. Probably not as well as a hypothetical race of creatures who each harbors a monomaniacal interest in prolonged species survival. And not so well as to be clear of great risk of foolish speciocide. But still staggeringly well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">Natural selection is often charged with having goals for humanity, and humanity is often charged with falling down on them. The big accusation, I think, is of sub-maximal procreation. If we cared at all about the genetic proliferation that natural selection wanted for us, then this time of riches would be a time of fifty-child families, not one of coddled dogs and state-of-the-art sitting rooms. But (the story goes) our failure is excusable, because instead of a deep-seated loyalty to genetic fitness, natural selection merely fitted humans out with a system of suggestive urges: hungers, fears, loves, lusts. Which all worked well together to bring about children in the prehistoric years of our forebears, but no more. In part because all sorts of things are different, and in part because we specifically made things different in that way on purpose: bringing about children gets in the way of the further satisfaction of those urges, so we avoid it (the story goes). This is generally floated as an illustrative warning about artificial intelligence. The moral is that if you make a system by first making multitudinous random systems and then systematically destroying all the ones that don’t do the thing you want, then the system you are left with might only do what you want while current circumstances persist, rather than being endowed with a consistent desire for the thing you actually had in mind. Observing acquaintences dispute this point recently, it struck me that humans are actually weirdly aligned with natural selection, more than I could easily account for. Natural selection, in its broadest, truest, (most idiolectic?) sense, doesn’t care about genes. Genes are a nice substrate on which natural selection famously makes particularly pretty patterns by driving a sensical evolution of lifeforms through interesting intricacies. But natural selection’s real love is existence. Natural selection just favors things that tend to exist. Things that start existing: great. Things that, having started existing, survive: amazing. Things that, while surviving, cause many copies of themselves to come into being: especial favorites of evolution, as long as there’s a path to the first ones coming into being. So natural selection likes genes that promote procreation and survival, but also likes elements that appear and don’t dissolve, ideas that come to mind and stay there, tools that are conceivable and copyable, shapes that result from myriad physical situations, rocks at the bottoms of mountains. Maybe this isn’t the dictionary definition of natural selection, but it is the real force in the world, of which natural selection of reproducing and surviving genetic clusters is one facet. Generalized natural selection—the thing that created us—says that the things that you see in the world are those things that exist best in the world. So what did natural selection want for us? What were we selected for? Existence. And while we might not proliferate our genes spectacularly well in particular, I do think we have a decent shot at a very prolonged existence. Or the prolonged existence of some important aspects of our being. It seems plausible that humanity makes it to the stars, galaxies, superclusters. Not that we are maximally trying for that any more than we are maximally trying for children. And I do think there’s a large chance of us wrecking it with various existential risks. But it’s interesting to me that natural selection made us for existing, and we look like we might end up just totally killing it, existence-wise. Even though natural selection purportedly did this via a bunch of hackish urges that were good in 200,000 BC but you might have expected to be outside their domain of applicability by 2023. And presumably taking over the universe is an extremely narrow target: it can only be done by so many things. Thus it seems to me that humanity is plausibly doing astonishingly well on living up to natural selection’s goals. Probably not as well as a hypothetical race of creatures who each harbors a monomaniacal interest in prolonged species survival. And not so well as to be clear of great risk of foolish speciocide. But still staggeringly well.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/nasa-Yj1M5riCKk4-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/nasa-Yj1M5riCKk4-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">We don’t trade with ants</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/10/we-dont-trade-with-ants.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We don&apos;t trade with ants" /><published>2023-01-10T13:55:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-10T13:55:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/01/10/we-dont-trade-with-ants</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/10/we-dont-trade-with-ants.html">&lt;p&gt;When discussing advanced AI, sometimes the following exchanges happens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Perhaps advanced AI won’t kill us. Perhaps it will trade with us”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We don’t trade with ants”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s interesting to get clear on exactly why we don’t trade with ants, and whether it is relevant to the AI situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a person says “we don’t trade with ants”, I think the implicit explanation is that humans are so big, powerful and smart compared to ants that we don’t need to trade with them because they have nothing of value and if they did we could just take it; anything they can do we can do better, and we can just walk all over them. Why negotiate when you can steal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is broadly wrong, and that it is also an interesting case of the classic cognitive error of imagining that trade is about swapping fixed-value objects, rather than creating new value from a confluence of one’s needs and the other’s affordances. It’s only in the imaginary zero-sum world that you can generally replace trade with stealing the other party’s stuff, if the other party is weak enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ants, with their skills, could do a lot that we would plausibly find worth paying for. Some ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cleaning things that are hard for humans to reach (crevices, buildup in pipes, outsides of tall buildings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chasing away other insects, including in agriculture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surveillance and spying&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building, sculpting, moving, and mending things in hard to reach places and at small scales (e.g. dig tunnels, deliver adhesives to cracks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting out of our houses before we are driven to expend effort killing them, and similarly for all the other places ants conflict with humans (stinging, eating crops, ..)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(For an extended list, see ‘Appendix: potentially valuable things things ants can do’)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t take almost any of this by force, we can at best kill them and take their dirt and the minuscule mouthfuls of our foods they were eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could we pay them for all this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single ant eats about 2mg per day according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.terminix.com/blog/bug-facts/how-much-do-bugs-eat/&quot;&gt;a random website&lt;/a&gt;, so you could support a colony of a million ants with 2kg of food per day. Supposing they accepted pay in sugar, or something similarly expensive, 2kg costs around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webstaurantstore.com/domino-extra-fine-granulated-sugar-50-lb/104SUGEFG50.html&quot;&gt;$3&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps you would need to pay them more than subsistence to attract them away from foraging freely, since apparently food-gathering ants usually collect more than they eat, to support others in their colony. So let’s guess $5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My guess is that a million ants could do well over $5 of the above labors in a day. For instance, a colony of meat ants &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meat_ant#Relationship_with_humans&quot;&gt;takes ‘weeks’&lt;/a&gt; to remove the meat from an entire carcass of an animal. Supposing somewhat conservatively that this is three weeks, and the animal is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/topics/animals-and-plants/native-animals/native-animal-facts/bandicoots#:~:text=Bandicoots%20are%20about%20the%20size,of%20which%20live%20in%20NSW.&amp;amp;text=The%20long%2Dnosed%20bandicoot%20is,weighs%20up%20to%201.5kg.&quot;&gt;1.5kg&lt;/a&gt; bandicoot, the colony is moving 70g/day. Guesstimating the mass of crumbs falling on the floor of a small cafeteria in a day, I imagine that it’s less than that produced by tearing up a single bread roll and spreading it around, which the internet says is about 50g. So my guess is that an ant colony could clean the floor of a small cafeteria for around $5/day, which I imagine is cheaper than human sweeping (this site says ‘light cleaning’ costs around $35/h on average in the US). And this is one of the tasks where the ants have least advantages over humans. Cleaning the outside of skyscrapers or the inside of pipes is presumably much harder for humans than cleaning a cafeteria floor, and I expect is fairly similar for ants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at a basic level, it seems like there should be potential for trade with ants - they can do a lot of things that we want done, and could live well at the prices we would pay for those tasks being done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why don’t we trade with ants?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I claim that we don’t trade with ants because we can’t communicate with them. We can’t tell them what we’d like them to do, and can’t have them recognize that we would pay them if they did it. Which might be more than the language barrier. There might be a conceptual poverty. There might also be a lack of the memory and consistent identity that allows an ant to uphold commitments it made with me five minutes ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get basic trade going, you might not need much of these things though. If we could only communicate that their all leaving our house immediately would prompt us to put a plate of honey in the garden for them and/or not slaughter them, then we would already be gaining from trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it looks like the the AI-human relationship is importantly disanalogous to the human-ant relationship, because the big reason we don’t trade with ants will not apply to AI systems potentially trading with us: we can’t communicate with ants, AI can communicate with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You might think ‘but the AI will be so far above us that it will think of itself as unable to communicate with us, in the same way that we can’t with the ants - we will be unable to conceive of most of its concepts’. It seems unlikely to me that one needs anything like the full palette of concepts available to the smarter creature to make productive trade. With ants, ‘go over there and we won’t kill you’ would do a lot, and it doesn’t involve concepts at the foggy pinnacle of human meaning-construction. The issue with ants is that we can’t communicate almost at all.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also: ants can actually do heaps of things we can’t, whereas (arguably) at some point that won’t be true for us relative to AI systems. (When we get human-level AI, will that AI also be ant level? Or will AI want to trade with ants for longer than it wants to trade with us? It can probably better figure out how to talk to ants.) However just because at some point AI systems will probably do everything humans do, doesn’t mean that this will happen on any particular timeline, e.g. the same one on which AI becomes ‘very powerful’. If the situation turns out similar to us and ants, we might expect that we continue to have a bunch of niche uses for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, for AI systems to be to humans as we are to ants, would be for us to be able to do many tasks better than AI, and for the AI systems to be willing to pay us grandly for them, but for them to be unable to tell us this, or even to warn us to get out of the way. Is this what AI will be like? No. AI will be able to communicate with us, though at some point we will be less useful to AI systems than ants could be to us if they could communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you might argue, being totally unable to communicate makes one useless, even if one has skills that could be good if accessible through communication. So being unable to communicate is just a kind of being useless, and how we treat ants is an apt case study in treatment of powerless and useless creatures, even if the uselessness has an unusual cause. This seems sort of right, but a) being unable to communicate probably makes a creature more absolutely useless than if it just lacks skills, because even an unskilled creature is sometimes in a position to add value e.g. by moving out of the way instead of having to be killed, b) the corner-ness of the case of ant uselessness might make general intuitive implications carry over poorly to other cases, c) the fact that the ant situation can definitely not apply to us relative to AIs seems interesting, and d) it just kind of worries me that when people are thinking about this analogy with ants, they are imagining it all wrong in the details, even if the conclusion should be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there’s a thought that AI being as much more powerful than us as we are than ants implies a uselessness that makes extermination almost guaranteed. But ants, while extremely powerless, are only useless to us by an accident of signaling systems. And we know that problem won’t apply in the case of AI. Perhaps we should not expect to so easily become useless to AI systems, even supposing they take all power from humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;appendix-potentially-valuable-things-things-ants-can-do&quot;&gt;Appendix: potentially valuable things things ants can do&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean, especially small loose particles or detachable substances, especially in cases that are very hard for humans to reach (e.g. floors, crevices, sticky jars in the kitchen, buildup from pipes while water is off, the outsides of tall buildings)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chase away other insects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pest control in agriculture (they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weaver_ant#In_agriculture&quot;&gt;already been used for this&lt;/a&gt; since about 400AD)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surveillance and spying&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigating hard to reach situations, underground or in walls for instance - e.g. see whether a pipe is leaking, or whether the foundation of a house is rotting, or whether there is smoke inside a wall&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surveil buildings for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goshen.edu/blogs/2014/05/10/ants-smoke-final-survey/#:~:text=So%2C%20today%20we%20spent%20several,the%20ground%20to%20save%20themselves.&amp;amp;text=As%20far%20as%201800m%20away,over%20a%20hundred%20per%20minute!&quot;&gt;smoke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defend areas from invaders, e.g. buildings, cars (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vachellia_drepanolobium#Symbiosis_with_ants&quot;&gt;some plants have coordinated with ants in this way&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sculpting/moving things at a very small scale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/lFg21x2sj-M?t=171&quot;&gt;house-size structures&lt;/a&gt; with intricate detailing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Digging tunnels (e.g. instead of digging up your garden to lay a pipe, maybe ants could dig the hole, then a flexible pipe could be pushed through it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being used in medication (this already happens, but might happen better if we could communicate with them)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participating in war (attack, guerilla attack, sabotage, intelligence)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mending things at a small scale, e.g. delivering adhesive material to a crack in a pipe while the water is off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surveillance of scents (including which direction a scent is coming from), e.g. drugs, explosives, diseases, people, microbes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tending other small, useful organisms (‘Leafcutter ants (Atta and Acromyrmex) feed exclusively on a fungus that grows only within their colonies. They continually collect leaves which are taken to the colony, cut into tiny pieces and placed in fungal gardens.’&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leafcutter_ant#Ant%E2%80%93fungus_mutualism&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;: ‘Leaf cutter ants are sensitive enough to adapt to the fungi’s reaction to different plant material, apparently detecting chemical signals from the fungus. If a particular type of leaf is toxic to the fungus, the colony will no longer collect it…The fungi used by the higher attine ants no longer produce spores. These ants fully domesticated their fungal partner 15 million years ago, a process that took 30 million years to complete.[9] Their fungi produce nutritious and swollen hyphal tips (gongylidia) that grow in bundles called staphylae, to specifically feed the ants.’ ‘The ants in turn keep predators away from the aphids and will move them from one feeding location to another. When migrating to a new area, many colonies will take the aphids with them, to ensure a continued supply of honeydew.’
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ant#Relationships_with_other_organisms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:’Myrmecophilous (ant-loving) caterpillars of the butterfly family Lycaenidae (e.g., blues, coppers, or hairstreaks) are herded by the ants, led to feeding areas in the daytime, and brought inside the ants’ nest at night. The caterpillars have a gland which secretes honeydew when the ants massage them.’’)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measuring hard to access distances (they measure distance as they walk with an internal pedometer)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Killing plants (lemon ants &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ant#Relationships_with_other_organisms&quot;&gt;make&lt;/a&gt; ‘devil’s gardens’ by killing all plants other than ‘lemon ant trees’ in an area)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Producing and delivering nitrogen to plants (‘Isotopic labelling studies suggest that plants also obtain nitrogen from the ants.’ - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ant#Relationships_with_other_organisms&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get out of our houses before we are driven to expend effort killing them, and similarly for all the other places ants conflict with humans (stinging, eating crops, ..)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">When discussing advanced AI, sometimes the following exchanges happens: “Perhaps advanced AI won’t kill us. Perhaps it will trade with us” “We don’t trade with ants” I think it’s interesting to get clear on exactly why we don’t trade with ants, and whether it is relevant to the AI situation. When a person says “we don’t trade with ants”, I think the implicit explanation is that humans are so big, powerful and smart compared to ants that we don’t need to trade with them because they have nothing of value and if they did we could just take it; anything they can do we can do better, and we can just walk all over them. Why negotiate when you can steal? I think this is broadly wrong, and that it is also an interesting case of the classic cognitive error of imagining that trade is about swapping fixed-value objects, rather than creating new value from a confluence of one’s needs and the other’s affordances. It’s only in the imaginary zero-sum world that you can generally replace trade with stealing the other party’s stuff, if the other party is weak enough. Ants, with their skills, could do a lot that we would plausibly find worth paying for. Some ideas: Cleaning things that are hard for humans to reach (crevices, buildup in pipes, outsides of tall buildings) Chasing away other insects, including in agriculture Surveillance and spying Building, sculpting, moving, and mending things in hard to reach places and at small scales (e.g. dig tunnels, deliver adhesives to cracks) Getting out of our houses before we are driven to expend effort killing them, and similarly for all the other places ants conflict with humans (stinging, eating crops, ..) (For an extended list, see ‘Appendix: potentially valuable things things ants can do’) We can’t take almost any of this by force, we can at best kill them and take their dirt and the minuscule mouthfuls of our foods they were eating. Could we pay them for all this? A single ant eats about 2mg per day according to a random website, so you could support a colony of a million ants with 2kg of food per day. Supposing they accepted pay in sugar, or something similarly expensive, 2kg costs around $3. Perhaps you would need to pay them more than subsistence to attract them away from foraging freely, since apparently food-gathering ants usually collect more than they eat, to support others in their colony. So let’s guess $5. My guess is that a million ants could do well over $5 of the above labors in a day. For instance, a colony of meat ants takes ‘weeks’ to remove the meat from an entire carcass of an animal. Supposing somewhat conservatively that this is three weeks, and the animal is a 1.5kg bandicoot, the colony is moving 70g/day. Guesstimating the mass of crumbs falling on the floor of a small cafeteria in a day, I imagine that it’s less than that produced by tearing up a single bread roll and spreading it around, which the internet says is about 50g. So my guess is that an ant colony could clean the floor of a small cafeteria for around $5/day, which I imagine is cheaper than human sweeping (this site says ‘light cleaning’ costs around $35/h on average in the US). And this is one of the tasks where the ants have least advantages over humans. Cleaning the outside of skyscrapers or the inside of pipes is presumably much harder for humans than cleaning a cafeteria floor, and I expect is fairly similar for ants. So at a basic level, it seems like there should be potential for trade with ants - they can do a lot of things that we want done, and could live well at the prices we would pay for those tasks being done. So why don’t we trade with ants? I claim that we don’t trade with ants because we can’t communicate with them. We can’t tell them what we’d like them to do, and can’t have them recognize that we would pay them if they did it. Which might be more than the language barrier. There might be a conceptual poverty. There might also be a lack of the memory and consistent identity that allows an ant to uphold commitments it made with me five minutes ago. To get basic trade going, you might not need much of these things though. If we could only communicate that their all leaving our house immediately would prompt us to put a plate of honey in the garden for them and/or not slaughter them, then we would already be gaining from trade. So it looks like the the AI-human relationship is importantly disanalogous to the human-ant relationship, because the big reason we don’t trade with ants will not apply to AI systems potentially trading with us: we can’t communicate with ants, AI can communicate with us. (You might think ‘but the AI will be so far above us that it will think of itself as unable to communicate with us, in the same way that we can’t with the ants - we will be unable to conceive of most of its concepts’. It seems unlikely to me that one needs anything like the full palette of concepts available to the smarter creature to make productive trade. With ants, ‘go over there and we won’t kill you’ would do a lot, and it doesn’t involve concepts at the foggy pinnacle of human meaning-construction. The issue with ants is that we can’t communicate almost at all.) But also: ants can actually do heaps of things we can’t, whereas (arguably) at some point that won’t be true for us relative to AI systems. (When we get human-level AI, will that AI also be ant level? Or will AI want to trade with ants for longer than it wants to trade with us? It can probably better figure out how to talk to ants.) However just because at some point AI systems will probably do everything humans do, doesn’t mean that this will happen on any particular timeline, e.g. the same one on which AI becomes ‘very powerful’. If the situation turns out similar to us and ants, we might expect that we continue to have a bunch of niche uses for a while. In sum, for AI systems to be to humans as we are to ants, would be for us to be able to do many tasks better than AI, and for the AI systems to be willing to pay us grandly for them, but for them to be unable to tell us this, or even to warn us to get out of the way. Is this what AI will be like? No. AI will be able to communicate with us, though at some point we will be less useful to AI systems than ants could be to us if they could communicate. But, you might argue, being totally unable to communicate makes one useless, even if one has skills that could be good if accessible through communication. So being unable to communicate is just a kind of being useless, and how we treat ants is an apt case study in treatment of powerless and useless creatures, even if the uselessness has an unusual cause. This seems sort of right, but a) being unable to communicate probably makes a creature more absolutely useless than if it just lacks skills, because even an unskilled creature is sometimes in a position to add value e.g. by moving out of the way instead of having to be killed, b) the corner-ness of the case of ant uselessness might make general intuitive implications carry over poorly to other cases, c) the fact that the ant situation can definitely not apply to us relative to AIs seems interesting, and d) it just kind of worries me that when people are thinking about this analogy with ants, they are imagining it all wrong in the details, even if the conclusion should be the same. Also, there’s a thought that AI being as much more powerful than us as we are than ants implies a uselessness that makes extermination almost guaranteed. But ants, while extremely powerless, are only useless to us by an accident of signaling systems. And we know that problem won’t apply in the case of AI. Perhaps we should not expect to so easily become useless to AI systems, even supposing they take all power from humans. Appendix: potentially valuable things things ants can do Clean, especially small loose particles or detachable substances, especially in cases that are very hard for humans to reach (e.g. floors, crevices, sticky jars in the kitchen, buildup from pipes while water is off, the outsides of tall buildings) Chase away other insects Pest control in agriculture (they have already been used for this since about 400AD) Surveillance and spying Investigating hard to reach situations, underground or in walls for instance - e.g. see whether a pipe is leaking, or whether the foundation of a house is rotting, or whether there is smoke inside a wall Surveil buildings for smoke Defend areas from invaders, e.g. buildings, cars (some plants have coordinated with ants in this way) Sculpting/moving things at a very small scale Building house-size structures with intricate detailing. Digging tunnels (e.g. instead of digging up your garden to lay a pipe, maybe ants could dig the hole, then a flexible pipe could be pushed through it) Being used in medication (this already happens, but might happen better if we could communicate with them) Participating in war (attack, guerilla attack, sabotage, intelligence) Mending things at a small scale, e.g. delivering adhesive material to a crack in a pipe while the water is off Surveillance of scents (including which direction a scent is coming from), e.g. drugs, explosives, diseases, people, microbes Tending other small, useful organisms (‘Leafcutter ants (Atta and Acromyrmex) feed exclusively on a fungus that grows only within their colonies. They continually collect leaves which are taken to the colony, cut into tiny pieces and placed in fungal gardens.’Wikipedia: ‘Leaf cutter ants are sensitive enough to adapt to the fungi’s reaction to different plant material, apparently detecting chemical signals from the fungus. If a particular type of leaf is toxic to the fungus, the colony will no longer collect it…The fungi used by the higher attine ants no longer produce spores. These ants fully domesticated their fungal partner 15 million years ago, a process that took 30 million years to complete.[9] Their fungi produce nutritious and swollen hyphal tips (gongylidia) that grow in bundles called staphylae, to specifically feed the ants.’ ‘The ants in turn keep predators away from the aphids and will move them from one feeding location to another. When migrating to a new area, many colonies will take the aphids with them, to ensure a continued supply of honeydew.’ Wikipedia:’Myrmecophilous (ant-loving) caterpillars of the butterfly family Lycaenidae (e.g., blues, coppers, or hairstreaks) are herded by the ants, led to feeding areas in the daytime, and brought inside the ants’ nest at night. The caterpillars have a gland which secretes honeydew when the ants massage them.’’) Measuring hard to access distances (they measure distance as they walk with an internal pedometer) Killing plants (lemon ants make ‘devil’s gardens’ by killing all plants other than ‘lemon ant trees’ in an area) Producing and delivering nitrogen to plants (‘Isotopic labelling studies suggest that plants also obtain nitrogen from the ants.’ - Wikipedia) Get out of our houses before we are driven to expend effort killing them, and similarly for all the other places ants conflict with humans (stinging, eating crops, ..)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/md_jerry-v9wN8wCPLHY-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/md_jerry-v9wN8wCPLHY-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to eat potato chips while typing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/03/how-to-eat-potato-chips.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to eat potato chips while typing" /><published>2023-01-03T02:32:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-03T02:32:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/01/03/how-to-eat-potato-chips</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/03/how-to-eat-potato-chips.html">&lt;p&gt;Chopsticks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;captioned-image-container&quot;&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd25d2ed4-4fe6-47f1-aeeb-52b729f06dbc_3024x4032.png&quot; alt=&quot;eating potato chips with chopsticks&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sometimes I want to eat snacks while I work, honestly because I have a weirdly moving dread of stretches of work-time containing nothing in any way gratifying to me. Possibly because I realistically anticipate that I will not remain working long under those conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But sadly many good snacks are oily, crumby, or otherwise ill-suited to being touched repeatedly interleaved with touching one’s keyboard. I think I usually deal with this by eating much snack while not typing at all for a bit, but sort of acting as though I think I’m going to, then washing my hands, then going back to the typing for a while, then repeating—largely defeating the purpose. I also get around this issue by getting bubble tea, a snack which can be substantially consumed with your mouth. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have often vaguely imagined chopsticks helping, but also imagined that they wouldn’t actually. Today I learned that they work well, at least for potato chips and popcorn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You might think standard Western cutlery would be the first thing to try, but a) it’s not good for hard, crunchy objects, and b) it’s somehow worse to reach to the side with both hands and do a knife-and-fork action than it is to reach with one hand, so if you need multiple implements to manipulate your snack, chopsticks seem superior.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;(For more practical eating advice, see &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meteuphoric.com/2016/06/26/are-you-missing-universal-human-skills/&quot; rel=&quot;&quot;&gt;how to cut and chew meat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. I also learned to drink from a can in the last year or so, but am unlikely to write it up unless I learn that this is a problem for anyone else ever.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="practicaladvice" /><category term="insight" /><summary type="html">Chopsticks.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd25d2ed4-4fe6-47f1-aeeb-52b729f06dbc_3024x4032.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd25d2ed4-4fe6-47f1-aeeb-52b729f06dbc_3024x4032.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Pacing: inexplicably good</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/12/31/pacing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pacing: inexplicably good" /><published>2022-12-31T19:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-12-31T19:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/12/31/pacing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/12/31/pacing.html">&lt;p&gt;Pacing—walking repeatedly over the same ground—&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/oxford-circles-and-planes-19-10-29&quot;&gt;often&lt;/a&gt; feels ineffably good while I’m doing it, but then I forget about it for ages, so I thought I’d write about it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean just going for an inefficient walk—it is somehow different to just step slowly in a circle around the same room for a long time, or up and down a passageway. &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why it would be good, but some ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s good to be physically engaged while thinking for some reason.&lt;/em&gt; I used to do ‘gymflection’ with a friend, where we would do strength exercises at the gym, and meanwhile be reflecting on our lives and what is going well and what we might do better. This felt good in a way that didn’t seem to come from either activity alone. (This wouldn’t explain why it would differ from walking though.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Different working memory setup:&lt;/em&gt; if you pace around in the same vicinity, your thoughts get kind of attached to the objects you are looking at. So next time you get to the green tiles say, they remind you of what you were thinking of last time you were there. This allows for a kind of repeated cycling back through recent topics, but layering different things into the mix with each loop, which is a nice way of thinking. Perhaps a bit like having additional working memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if going for a walk doesn’t really get 1) in a satisfying way, because my mind easily wanders from the topic at hand and also from my surrounds, so it less feels like I’m really grappling with something and being physical, and more like I’m daydreaming elsewhere. So maybe 2) is needed also, to both stick with a topic and attend to the physical world for a while. I don’t put a high probability on this detailed theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="lifeadvice" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">Pacing—walking repeatedly over the same ground—often feels ineffably good while I’m doing it, but then I forget about it for ages, so I thought I’d write about it here. I don’t mean just going for an inefficient walk—it is somehow different to just step slowly in a circle around the same room for a long time, or up and down a passageway.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/kenny-eliason-m_rrkduuHkU-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/kenny-eliason-m_rrkduuHkU-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Worldly Positions archive, briefly with private drafts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/12/30/worldly-positions-archives.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Worldly Positions archive, briefly with private drafts" /><published>2022-12-30T02:56:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-12-30T02:56:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/12/30/worldly-positions-archives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/12/30/worldly-positions-archives.html">&lt;p&gt;I realized it was hard to peruse past &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldlypositions.tumblr.com&quot;&gt;Worldly Positions&lt;/a&gt; posts without logging in to Tumblr, which seemed pretty bad. So I followed Substack’s instructions to import the archives into &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/&quot;&gt;world spirit sock stack&lt;/a&gt;. And it worked pretty well, except that SUBSTACK ALSO PUBLISHED MY UNPUBLISHED WORLDLY POSITIONS DRAFTS! What on Earth? That’s so bad. Did I misunderstand what happened somehow in my rush to unpublish them? Maybe. But they definitely had ‘unpublish’ buttons, so that’s pretty incriminating. &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to have turned out alright for me, since it looks like I just never wrote any drafts that would be too embarrassing to anyone other than myself. And the most embarrassing to myself are probably at the level of bad and abortive poetry. Plus it turned up a few decent drafts to finish, and the adrenaline was a welcome pick-me-up in my current retreat-driven stimulation drought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some good bits of the archive (from pre-&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/worldlypositions.html&quot;&gt;WSSP&lt;/a&gt; times) according to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/mine-craft-20-07-03&quot;&gt;Mine-craft&lt;/a&gt;: the composition of the ego in a procedurally generated sandbox game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/claudius-emanuel-g-s-17-10-20&quot;&gt;The time I rented a robot baby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/tv-night-realer-photography-19-06-11&quot;&gt;Why fiction is more horrifying than war photography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/home-up-and-down-colder-and-warmer-20-02-20&quot;&gt;Home: up and down, colder and warmer&lt;/a&gt;: miscellanious thoughts on e.g. warmth and coldness, the sincerity of historic advertising, and why negativity is deep&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/bay-bridge-having-fun-19-06-06&quot;&gt;How I learned to have fun on command&lt;/a&gt; though I rarely remember to do it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/england-attunement-and-borders-20-01-30&quot;&gt;England: Attunement and borders&lt;/a&gt;, in which I get possible attunement, companionship, and a visa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meta" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I realized it was hard to peruse past Worldly Positions posts without logging in to Tumblr, which seemed pretty bad. So I followed Substack’s instructions to import the archives into world spirit sock stack. And it worked pretty well, except that SUBSTACK ALSO PUBLISHED MY UNPUBLISHED WORLDLY POSITIONS DRAFTS! What on Earth? That’s so bad. Did I misunderstand what happened somehow in my rush to unpublish them? Maybe. But they definitely had ‘unpublish’ buttons, so that’s pretty incriminating.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://static.tumblr.com/010f7823b98a70509677554b6bbb2f46/j5ffzji/yiIoqg5l6/tumblr_static_6naihwpnpqww8okw804s08g_2048_v2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://static.tumblr.com/010f7823b98a70509677554b6bbb2f46/j5ffzji/yiIoqg5l6/tumblr_static_6naihwpnpqww8okw804s08g_2048_v2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>