<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-07T21:46:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/2020-12-07-why-are-delicious-biscuits-obscure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2020-12-07T21:46:22-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-07T21:46:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/2020-12-07-why-are-delicious-biscuits-obscure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/2020-12-07-why-are-delicious-biscuits-obscure.html">&lt;p&gt;I saw a picture of these biscuits (or cookies), and they looked very delicious. So much so that I took the uncharacteristic step of actually making them. They were indeed among the most delicious biscuits of which I am aware. And yet I don’t recall hearing of them before. This seems like a telling sign about something. (The capitalist machinery? Culture? Industrial food production constraints? The vagaries of individual enjoyment?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/91nepe5q84xtbyf/iStock-1088141566.jpg?raw=1&quot; alt=&quot;Kolakakor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why doesn’t the market offer these delicious biscuits all over the place? Isn’t this just the kind of rival, excludable, information-available, well-internalized good that markets are on top of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some explanations that occur to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am wrong or unusual in my assessment of deliciousness, and for instance most people would find a chocolate chip cookie or an Oreo more delicious.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are harder to cook commercially than the ubiquitous biscuits for some reason. e.g. they are most delicious warm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are Swedish, and there are mysterious cultural or linguistic barriers to foods spreading from their original homes. This would also help explain some other observations, to the extent that it counts as an explanation at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliciousness is not a central factor in food spread. (Then what is?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to help investigate, you can do so by carrying out the following recipe and reporting on the percentile of deliciousness of the resulting biscuits. (I do not claim that this is a high priority investigation to take part in, unless you are hungry for delicious biscuits or a firsthand encounter with a moderately interesting sociological puzzle.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kolakakor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Or &lt;em&gt;Kolasnittar&lt;/em&gt;. Adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houseandgarden.co.uk/recipe/caramel-shortbread&quot;&gt;House &amp;amp; Garden’s&lt;/a&gt; account of a recipe in Magnus Nilsson’s “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Nordic-Baking-Book-Magnus-Nilsson/dp/0714876844&quot;&gt;The Nordic Baking Book&lt;/a&gt;”. It’s quite plausible that their versions are better than mine, which has undergone pressure for ease plus some random ingredient substitutions. However I offer mine, since it is the one I can really vouch for.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Takes about fifteen minutes of making, and fifteen further minutes of waiting. Makes enough biscuits for about five people to eat too many biscuits, plus a handful left over. (Other recipe calls it about 40 ‘shortbreads’)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;200 g melted butter (e.g. microwave it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;180 g sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g golden syrup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50g honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;300 g flour, ideally &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.kingarthurbaking.com/items/gluten-free-all-purpose-flour&quot;&gt;King Arthur gluten free flour&lt;/a&gt;, but wheat flour will also do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon bicarbonate of soda (baking soda)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoon ground ginger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 good pinches of salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat oven: 175°C/345°F&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put everything in a mixing bowl (if you have kitchen scales, put the mixing bowl on them, set scales to zero, add an ingredient, reset scales to zero, add the next ingredient, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mix.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taste [warning: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/foodsafety/communication/no-raw-dough.html&quot;&gt;public health officials say not to do this because eating raw flour is dangerous&lt;/a&gt;]. Adjust mixedness, saltiness, etc. It should be very roughly the consistency of peanut butter, i.e. probably less firm than you expect. (Taste more, as desired. Wonder why we cook biscuits at all. Consider rebellion. Consider Chesterton’s fence. Taste one more time.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cover a big tray or a couple of small trays with baking paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the dough into about four logs, around an inch in diameter, spaced several inches from one another and the edges of the paper. They can be misshapen; their shapes are temporary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook for about 15 minutes, or until golden and spread out into 1-4 giant flat seas of biscuit. When you take them out, they will be very soft and probably not appear to be cooked.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As soon as they slightly cool and firm up enough to pick up, start chopping them into strips about 1.25 inches wide and eating them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonus mystery: they are gluten free, egg free, and can probably easily be dairy free. The contest with common vegan and/or gluten free biscuit seems even more winnable, so why haven’t they even taken over that market?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">What it really looks like</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/06/photographs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What it really looks like" /><published>2020-12-06T10:45:22-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-06T10:45:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/06/photographs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/06/photographs.html">&lt;blockquote class=&quot;imgur-embed-pub&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; data-id=&quot;a/lRoMfR0&quot; data-context=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//imgur.com/a/lRoMfR0&quot;&gt;Near Sutro Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A photograph taken during a discussion of how photographs often fail to capture scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that photos often don’t capture what the photographer saw in the scene (perhaps especially if the photographer isn’t really a photographer). But it’s kind of amazing that I think of this as ‘the photograph failed to capture what it was really like’, rather than ‘my perception failed to capture what it was really like, as evidenced by this photograph’!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if it is possible to make a camera that captures scenes the way they look to a person there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a mundane example, it would need to make the moon appear big, when a camera might capture it as tiny. Is there a two dimensional set of pixels that can produce the same sense of how big the moon is, without changing other aspects of the picture to be further away from the perception? Is there such a two dimensional image for any perceived scene?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With sufficiently good what-it-seemed-like-to-the-photographer cameras, we could make substantial progress on bridging the gaping gaps between different minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I suppose you can always edit the colors a bit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="perception" /><summary type="html">Near Sutro Tower</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cultural accumulation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/cultural-accumulation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cultural accumulation" /><published>2020-12-05T21:08:11-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-05T21:08:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/cultural-accumulation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/cultural-accumulation.html">&lt;p&gt;When I think of humans being so smart due to ‘cultural accumulation’, I think of lots of tiny innovations in thought and technology being made by different people, and added to the interpersonal currents of culture that wash into each person’s brain, leaving a twenty year old in 2020 much better intellectually equipped than a 90 year old who spent their whole life thinking in 1200 AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I was chatting to my boyfriend about whether a person who went back in time (let’s say a thousand years) would be able to gather more social power than they can now in their own time. Some folk we know were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/mzgtmmTKKn5MuCzFJ/p/oiuZjPfknKsSc5waC#Discussion_on_the_ease_of_taking_control_of_the_world&quot;&gt;discussing&lt;/a&gt; the claim that some humans would have a shot at literally take over the world if sent back in time, and we found this implausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious differences between a 2020 person and a 1200 AD person, in 1200 AD, is that they have experience with incredible technological advances that the 1200 AD native doesn’t even know are possible. But a notable thing about a modern person is that they famously &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.behance.net/gallery/35437979/Velocipedia&quot;&gt;don’t know what a bicycle looks like&lt;/a&gt;, so the level of technology they might be able to actually rebuild on short notice  in 1200 AD is probably not at the level of a nutcracker, and they probably already had those in 1200 AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does 2020 have complicated technology, if most people don’t know how it works? One big part is specialization: across the world, quite a few people do know what bicycles look like. And more to the point, presumably some of them know in great detail what bicycle chains look like, and what they are made of, and what happens if you make them out of slightly different materials or in slightly different shapes, and how such things interact with the functioning of the bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But suppose the 2020 person who is sent back is a bicycle expert, and regularly builds their own at home. Can they introduce bikes to the world &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bicycle#History&quot;&gt;600 years early&lt;/a&gt;? My tentative guess is yes, but not very ridable ones, because they don’t have machines for making bike parts, or any idea what those machines are like or the principles behind them. They can probably demonstrate the idea of a bike with wood and cast iron and leather, supposing others are cooperative with various iron casting, wood shaping, leather-making know-how. But can they make a bike that is worth paying for and riding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure, and bikes were selected here for being so simple that an average person might know what their machinery looks like. Which makes them unusually close among technologies to simple chunks of metal. I don’t think a microwave oven engineer can introduce microwave ovens in 1200, or a silicon chip engineer can make much progress on introducing silicon chips. These require other technologies that require other technologies too many layers back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if the whole of 2020 society was transported to 1200? The metal extruding experts and the electricity experts and the factory construction experts and Elon Musk? Could they just jump back to 2020 levels of technology, since they know everything relevant between them? (Assuming they are somehow as well coordinated in this project as they are in 2020, and are not just putting all of their personal efforts into avoiding being burned at the stake or randomly tortured in the streets.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big way this might fail is if 2020 society knows everything between them needed to use 2020 artifacts to get more 2020 artifacts, but don’t know how to use 1200 artifacts to get 2020 artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that story, the 1200 people might start out knowing methods for making c. 1200 artifacts using c. 1200 artifacts, but they accumulate between them the ideas to get them to c. 1220 artifacts with the c. 1200 artifacts, which they use to actually create those new artifacts. They pass to their children this collection of c. 1220 artifacts and the ideas needed to use those artifacts to get more c. 1220 artifacts. But the new c. 1220 artifacts and methods replaced some of the old c. 1200 artifacts and methods. So the knowledge passed on doesn’t include how to use those obsoleted artifacts to create the new artifacts, or the knowledge about how to make the obsoleted artifacts. And the artifacts passed on don’t include the obsoleted ones. If this happens every generation for a thousand years, the cultural inheritance received by the 2020 generation includes some highly improved artifacts plus the knowledge about how to use them, but not necessarily any record of the path that got there from prehistory, or of the tools that made the tools that made the tools that made these artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This differs from my first impression of ‘cultural accumulation’ in that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;physical artifacts are central to the process: a lot of the accumulation is happening inside them, rather than in memetic space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;humanity is not accumulating all of the ideas it has come up with so far, even the important ones. It is accumulating something more like a best set of instructions for the current situation, and throwing a lot out as it goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this is how things are, or is my first impression more true?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="history" /><category term="social-dynamics" /><summary type="html">When I think of humans being so smart due to ‘cultural accumulation’, I think of lots of tiny innovations in thought and technology being made by different people, and added to the interpersonal currents of culture that wash into each person’s brain, leaving a twenty year old in 2020 much better intellectually equipped than a 90 year old who spent their whole life thinking in 1200 AD.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://imgur.com/a/ERQ1xlR" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://imgur.com/a/ERQ1xlR" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Distanced Christmas book celebration</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/04/distanced-christmas-book-celebration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Distanced Christmas book celebration" /><published>2020-12-04T22:34:34-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T22:34:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/04/distanced-christmas-book-celebration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/04/distanced-christmas-book-celebration.html">&lt;p&gt;I attended a friend’s wedding this year, that was in the form of a play which everyone was sent in book form, to read at the same time from different places. There were various interactive interludes, including phone calls with strangers I had been algorithmically matched with, and a big group Zoom. I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a child, I had a ‘Christmas book’ that I liked, with lots of different nice things in it, like stories about the nativity, and about the Christmas ceasefire in World War I, and songs, and instructions for making foods and decorations, and descriptions of Christmas in other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Christmas I was mostly alone, since I live in America and my family lives in Australia. I celebrated by myself: I made myself a Christmas stocking full of things like pens and post-it notes and beads and chocolate (with a traditional balloon on it), and had hot chocolate, and opened presents, and then I read a book of essays that I had collected up online beforehand and printed out nicely. The theme was something like, ‘being in touch with far away people, elsewhere and in the past, and in particular trying to see what they are really like, and to remember that they are not like what I think’. There are ways you can be especially close to people by reading their words that are different from the ways you can be close by chatting and eating together, and I hoped to do those ones, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year lots of people are forced to stay at home, so I have plenty of company. But if I were going to celebrate relatively alone at the same time as my friends or family were doing the same thing elsewhere, I like the idea of trying to combine these ideas somehow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="christmas" /><category term="advice" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I attended a friend’s wedding this year, that was in the form of a play which everyone was sent in book form, to read at the same time from different places. There were various interactive interludes, including phone calls with strangers I had been algorithmically matched with, and a big group Zoom. I liked it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to unhurriedly take a short time?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/hurry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to unhurriedly take a short time?" /><published>2020-12-03T13:00:22-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T13:00:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/hurry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/hurry.html">&lt;p&gt;Everything I do feels hurried. And yet if I don’t hurry, everything I do takes forever. Is there some outside the box alternative that other people do? (Aside from least-bad compromises between the two?)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="qandnota" /><summary type="html">Everything I do feels hurried. And yet if I don’t hurry, everything I do takes forever. Is there some outside the box alternative that other people do? (Aside from least-bad compromises between the two?)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://i.imgur.com/jBWS3nH.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://i.imgur.com/jBWS3nH.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Milkmaid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/02/the-milkmaid-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Milkmaid" /><published>2020-12-02T23:19:34-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-02T23:19:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/02/the-milkmaid-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/02/the-milkmaid-review.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/milkmaid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Milkmaid by Johannes Vermeer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Milkmaid, by Johannes Vermeer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had a soft spot for Vermeer, the 17th Century Dutch artist, ever since I was compelled to write about him in high school, and I especially like this painting. I think it’s a particularly good example of how his painting of textures makes them seem almost supernaturally pleasing. I wouldn’t usually think of myself as a huge fan of textures. But here—the seed encrusted bread looks so crisp and solid, I can imagine the sound of my hand knocking some seeds off as I pick it up, or the thud of the loaf if I tapped it. The vivid and visceral cloth of her dress and the minuscule lumpiness of its stitching, please me too. The sheen of the basket canes makes me almost feel the knobbly weave of the baskets. Maybe I am just a big texture fan. Or maybe getting the textures right adds a kind of realism that is particularly satisfying. As I write about it, I note that it is often that I have a vivid sense of the physicality of the object, as well as that physicality being somehow especially rich and enlivening. I wonder if this is related to his commonly credited skill with painting glimmering light (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Vermeer#Theories_of_mechanical_aid&quot;&gt;hypothesized controversially&lt;/a&gt; to have been related to use of an early camera-like device).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is amazing to remember that before cameras, mankind didn’t have any good way to ‘know’ what things really looked like except to look at them and do their best at recording it on paper. (They knew in the sense that they could see it.) In spite of everyone looking at things all the time, you could make major discoveries about what everyday things looked like, at least &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perspective_(graphical)#History&quot;&gt;into the fifteenth century&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the painting from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/rijksstudio/artists/johannes-vermeer/objects#/SK-A-2344,0&quot;&gt;Rijksmuseum&lt;/a&gt; website, which is itself a great thing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="reviw" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/milkmaid.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/milkmaid.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Inbox zero day</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/inbox-zero-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inbox zero day" /><published>2020-12-01T22:53:16-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T22:53:16-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/inbox-zero-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/inbox-zero-day.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I spent the entire day emptying my main work email inbox of all its emails, many of which had lived there for years. Apparently it was last empty around when I got that email in early 2014. I had committed to someone that I would archive anything left in that account without reading it at 10:30 tonight, and thereby give up on getting to it. And I wanted to at least glance at things. The point of all this was to not have the ever-present sense of a giant backlog of things I am supposed to deal with, of which mounds of non-given-up-on emails are one piece. (Another option would be to just give up on everything that was ever pending, but I’m not quite up for it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recorded the time and remaining email count in a spreadsheet as I went along, and watched the expected time to completion at the current rate, to see if it was before or after 10:30pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/emailsgraph.png&quot; alt=&quot;emails graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pretty intense, because most of the time it looked borderline whether I would make it, and tearing through reading a plethora of different things in a race against time for about nine almost consecutive hours is a lot. Overall it was pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some miscellaneous things on this topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My sincere apologies to a large fraction of the people who have ever tried to email me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s nice to go back and remember the flavors of the different times and the different sets of people who have been around. I look forward to the coming times when mingling with sets of people is back on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I get a fair number of extremely strange emails, for some of which I have trouble constructing any plausible circumstance that might have prompted them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s notable how quickly my brain categorizes emails as ‘crankish’ or not. You might think that this would require getting some of the content, but I think a lot of my view on the matter is formed by the time I’ve seen very surface features. Supposing I judge correctly (which seems true if I look at the content, but that could be prejudice), I wonder why there is this strong correlation between content and style.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It seems like people have very different norms for length when writing emails. It’s nice that some people think I have so much concentration, reading speed and spare time that I’m going to make it through any five page essay that someone I don’t know sends my way, but it’s not true. The chance for me reading a thing when I get it drops off fast, maybe reaching 50% at around two sentences, unless some good reason to read it has arisen by then. In the past, I mostly left it in my email at that point, for maybe several years, but going forward I think I’m going to try to just give up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m not sure if it would have been better to read all these emails at the time. Probably yes, because it would have been good for me to actually respond to people. But this way might have been better experientially.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="mundane" /><category term="journal" /><summary type="html">Today I spent the entire day emptying my main work email inbox of all its emails, many of which had lived there for years. Apparently it was last empty around when I got that email in early 2014. I had committed to someone that I would archive anything left in that account without reading it at 10:30 tonight, and thereby give up on getting to it. And I wanted to at least glance at things. The point of all this was to not have the ever-present sense of a giant backlog of things I am supposed to deal with, of which mounds of non-given-up-on emails are one piece. (Another option would be to just give up on everything that was ever pending, but I’m not quite up for it.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Points for anxiety</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/points-for-anxiety.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Points for anxiety" /><published>2020-12-01T02:03:25-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T02:03:25-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/points-for-anxiety</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/points-for-anxiety.html">&lt;p&gt;I have an intermittently crippling anxiety disorder, so I recently started trying a new kind of therapy to mitigate it. I’ve been finding sufficiently great so far that even if it doesn’t work long term I will probably think it was worth it. So I’ll tell you about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://noiseinyourhead.com/&quot;&gt;Reid Wilson’s&lt;/a&gt; ideas, I think as described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Stopping-Noise-Your-Head-Overcome/dp/0757319068&quot;&gt;his book&lt;/a&gt;, though I haven’t read it and most of my understanding comes from my therapist, my friend who also does this, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://noiseinyourhead.com/free-video-series/&quot;&gt;set of humorous videos on Reid Wilson’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the practice, as I practice it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’m anxious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Notice that I am anxious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Connect with my outcome picture’. Which is to say, imagine a really good version of my life. (Usually focusing on details that parallel currently problematic ones. For instance, if I was distracted by the sense of not being able to breathe while hanging out with a friend, I might imagine a version of my life where I hang out with my friends attentively while confidently brushing off all manner of chest sensations, perhaps in the context of a life more broadly full of confidence and attention on things that matter.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be excited for the current bout of anxiety as an opportunity to exercise skills at living in the ‘outcome picture’ version of life in spite of anxiety. This involves having redrawn the goal as living well even in the context of anxiety rather than not being anxious. It also involves thinking of the route to this goal as developing a skill or strength via repeated practice, similar to learning a language or becoming good at bench press. Then because that practice requires a series of anxiety-filled contexts, you are naturally excited if an occasion comes up.
  For example, instead of aiming to never have panic attacks while getting lunch with someone, you are trying to become the kind of person who can keep their attention on the finer points of an argument in spite of maybe feeling like they can’t breathe that well. This is only going to happen via a number of practice occasions with arguments and breathing difficulties. So if one of these comes up, you are pumped.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go back to what I was doing. It doesn’t necessarily need to be in a non-anxious way even, just treating it as practice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I get ten points, I get a cookie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the clear rules for getting a point, and the dispersal of cookies, are both crucial for my own success with this, though my impression is that they are not included in the classic versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I like or think might be good about this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imagining how you want things to be ten or twenty times a day is pretty inspiring in general, anxiety aside. (Anxiety reduction techniques that involve doing something virtuous every time you are anxious seem good in general, if you can make them work. I used to play DDR whenever I was anxious, and I got heaps of exercise and very good at DDR.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can get genuinely excited for being anxious, that alone seems to undermine some of its force.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feeling like anxiety is the thing that is meant to happen, that is a key part of the path to your goal (or at least the path to a point), rather than a sign of things going wrong, also makes it easier to deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empirically it seems to just make me happy somehow. It might be all the imagining my outcome picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="self-improvement" /><category term="anxiety" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I have an intermittently crippling anxiety disorder, so I recently started trying a new kind of therapy to mitigate it. I’ve been finding sufficiently great so far that even if it doesn’t work long term I will probably think it was worth it. So I’ll tell you about it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/pepparkakor.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/pepparkakor.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sincerity trends</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/29/sincerity-trends.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sincerity trends" /><published>2020-11-29T22:22:52-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-29T22:22:52-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/29/sincerity-trends</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/29/sincerity-trends.html">&lt;p&gt;I have the impression that sincerity, earnestness and straightforward conviction used to be more popular flavors of attitude and have been replaced (at least in the public sphere) by more self-conscious, ironic, critical, half-hearted, cool type attitudes. I went hiking with a friend today, and he mentioned the same impression (though I may have got mine from him), and we speculated about the reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does everyone share this impression? Over what time-scales? Do we have good explanations?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="historic-social-trends" /><category term="sociology" /><summary type="html">I have the impression that sincerity, earnestness and straightforward conviction used to be more popular flavors of attitude and have been replaced (at least in the public sphere) by more self-conscious, ironic, critical, half-hearted, cool type attitudes. I went hiking with a friend today, and he mentioned the same impression (though I may have got mine from him), and we speculated about the reasons.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Another point of view on the details</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/28/another-point-of-view-on-the-details.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Another point of view on the details" /><published>2020-11-28T23:39:30-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-28T23:39:30-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/28/another-point-of-view-on-the-details</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/28/another-point-of-view-on-the-details.html">&lt;p&gt;This morning my boyfriend and I did an activity where he followed me around for a couple of hours and observed as I started the day and did some tasks. (I’ve also done something like that before with a friend who was trying out anthropology.) I suggested it this time because I often find it enlightening to hear an outside perspective on things that I do, and his in particular. And it seems rarer to hear about the details and tactics, versus very high level questions: I often know what projects another person thinks are good, but rarely know what they would do if they got an email asking to hang out from an acquaintance, or if they were feeling antsy, or how they would decide where to start on the project in question, or when to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think that it’s easy to have a somewhat silly habit, but then to deal with its oppressiveness by doing it automatically and fast. But then you barely notice it, so it is harder to remember that it’s a problem and fix it. And yet such things build up. And even having someone else watching can make the details of what you are doing—and their defensibility—briefly vivid. For instance, today I quickly noticed myself that I wash my hands way more than is reasonable while making a sandwich, but I do it pretty habitually and don’t even think about it. I just believe that making sandwiches is somehow arduous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good thing about this activity is that where I am focused on the detail of a problem, a new observer can be confused at why I would even think the thing is a problem, or worthy of my time to solve, or why I would assume the constraints that I’m assuming. Which can all be refreshing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I found it helpful and enlightening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But another virtue of this is in the never-ending effort to see what other people’s worlds are like. In hearing someone describe how your world looks to them, you perhaps get to infer something about the landscape of the place that view is coming from.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="self-improvement" /><category term="games" /><summary type="html">This morning my boyfriend and I did an activity where he followed me around for a couple of hours and observed as I started the day and did some tasks. (I’ve also done something like that before with a friend who was trying out anthropology.) I suggested it this time because I often find it enlightening to hear an outside perspective on things that I do, and his in particular. And it seems rarer to hear about the details and tactics, versus very high level questions: I often know what projects another person thinks are good, but rarely know what they would do if they got an email asking to hang out from an acquaintance, or if they were feeling antsy, or how they would decide where to start on the project in question, or when to stop.</summary></entry></feed>