<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-14T03:27:44-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Blog plant</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/14/blog-plant.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog plant" /><published>2020-12-14T02:10:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-14T02:10:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/14/blog-plant</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/14/blog-plant.html">&lt;p&gt;I like to have plants in honor of things I’ve done. I’m not consistent or proportionate about it, and admittedly I also have quite a few plants that I intend to be in honor of things I haven’t yet done. But now that &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/&quot;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt; has apparently functional comments and images and analytics, as well as words on pages on the internet, I declare it fully bloggy, and my &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/10/25/new-blog.html&quot;&gt;effort to make&lt;/a&gt; a blog complete. Here’s my blog plant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201214_082858652.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;blog-plant&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome perspectives on good marginal improvements toward WSSP being a pleasing blog to interact with. (I’m aware that the subscription possibilities are not as salient as they could be.) It is a static site made using Jekyll and kept on Github, with its comments looked after by Disqus and its analytics by Google and its pictures by Photobucket.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="CATEGORY-1" /><category term="CATEGORY-2" /><summary type="html">I like to have plants in honor of things I’ve done. I’m not consistent or proportionate about it, and admittedly I also have quite a few plants that I intend to be in honor of things I haven’t yet done. But now that this blog has apparently functional comments and images and analytics, as well as words on pages on the internet, I declare it fully bloggy, and my effort to make a blog complete. Here’s my blog plant:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201214_082858652.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201214_082858652.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why quantitative methods are heartwarming</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/heartwarming-quantitative-methods.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why quantitative methods are heartwarming" /><published>2020-12-12T12:38:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T12:38:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/heartwarming-quantitative-methods</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/heartwarming-quantitative-methods.html">&lt;p&gt;From Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;If you listened to my podcast w/Michael Sandel, you know we have very different views on whether markets are &amp;quot;degrading&amp;quot;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One thing I didn&amp;#39;t mention to him: This bit in his book cracked me up -- because I remember my friends &amp;amp; I found this aspect of Moneyball SO HEARTWARMING &amp;lt;3 &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/9W6Op30vF8&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/9W6Op30vF8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Galef (@juliagalef) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/juliagalef/status/1337097616639864832?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 10, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t actually seen Moneyball, but it does sound heartwarming, and I have had to hide my tears when someone described a payment app their company was working, so I’m probably in Julia’s category here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I didn’t feel this way though, reading this I might imagine it as some alien nerdly aberration, and not a way that I could feel from the inside, or that would seem the ‘right’ way to feel unless I became brain-damaged. Which I think is all wrong—such feelings seem to me to be a warm and human response to appreciating the situation in certain ways. So I want to try to describe what seems to be going on in my mind when my heart is warmed by quantitative methods and efficient algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using good quantitative methods makes something better, it means that there wasn’t any concrete physical obstacle to it being better in the past. We were just making the wrong choices, because we didn’t know better. And often suffering small losses from it at a scale that is hard to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose the pricing algorithm for ride sharing isn’t as good as it could be. Then day after day there will be people who decide to walk even though they are tired, people who wait somewhere they don’t feel safe for a bit longer, countless people who stand in their hallway a bit longer, people who save up their health problems a bit more before making the expensive trip to a doctor, people who decide to keep a convenient car and so have a little bit less money for everything else. All while someone who would happily to drive each of them at a price they would happily pay lives nearby, suffering for lack of valuable work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not too concerned if we make bad choices in baseball, but in lots of areas, I imagine that there are these slow-accreting tragedies, in thousands or millions or billions of small inconveniences and pains accruing each day across the country or the world. And where this is for lack of good algorithms, it feels like it is for absolutely nothing. Just unforced error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily efforts and suffering for nothing are a particular flavor of badness. Like if someone erroneously believed that it was important for them to count to five thousand out loud at 10am each day, and every day they did this—and if they traveled they made sure there would be somewhere non-disturbing to do it, and if they stayed up late they got up by 10am; and if they were doing something they stepped out—there would be a particular elation in them escaping this senseless waste of their life, perhaps mixed with sorrow for what had been senselessly lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, having found the better method, you can usually just do it at no extra cost forever. So it feels reelingly scalable in a way that a hero fighting a bad guy definitively does not. This feels like suddenly being able to fly, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/11/26/air-walls-and-empty-currents.html&quot;&gt;walk through walls&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, it is some combination of escape from a senseless corrosion of life, effortlessly, at a scale that leaves me reeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that might be going on, is that it is a triumph of what is definitely right over what is definitely wrong. Lots of moral issues are fraught in some way. No humans are absolutely bad and without a side to the story. But worse quantitative methods are just straightforwardly wrong. The only reason for picking baseball players badly is not knowing how to do it better. The only reason for using worse estimates for covid risk is that you don’t have better ones. So a victory for better quantitative methods is an unsullied victory for light over darkness in a way that conflicts between human forces of good and bad can’t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another thing is that a victory for quantitative methods &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; always a victory for people. And if you don’t know who they are, that means that they quietly worked to end some ongoing blight on humanity, and did it, and weren’t even recognized. Often, even the good they did will look like a boring technical detail and won’t look morally important, because saving every American ten seconds doesn’t look like saving a life. And I’m not sure if there is anything more heartwarming than someone working hard to do great good, relieving the world from ongoing suffering, knowing that neither they nor and what they have given will be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="feelings" /><summary type="html">From Twitter:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/1jpz3n0x2nfffih/roofs-from-above.jpg?raw=1" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/1jpz3n0x2nfffih/roofs-from-above.jpg?raw=1" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The institution of email</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/the-institution-of-email.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The institution of email" /><published>2020-12-12T01:25:33-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-12T01:25:33-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/the-institution-of-email</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/12/the-institution-of-email.html">&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a common phenomenon where people get messages, then fail to respond to them, then feel bad. And the rarer strategy of actually dealing with all of one’s emails promptly doesn’t even seem obviously better. Was that how things were with letters or telegrams? Is it just that there are so many messages now, because they are easy to send?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could email, say, have gone a different way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I act as though I’m assuming email involves implied norms, though I didn’t agree to them. For instance, if someone writes me a personal message, I think I should not delete it without reading it, unless they deserve my disregard for some reason. If someone sends me a message asking me to do something, I act like I think I should do it in a timely fashion, if it is a reasonable request. If I write to someone, I feel like I should make it less terse than ‘ok.’. At least, many people seem to constantly feel bad for failing to uphold &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; standards that are I guess implicitly bought into by having an email address. (And not having an email address would be pretty wild.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was this bad luck, and we could instead have developed happier norms? For instance, that there is no expectation that one read emails, or that responding in about a month is proper, or that tersity is expected, like text messages? Or the norm that you are meant to respond within a few seconds, or consider it dead, like verbal speech? Or the norm where if you want to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thicketforte.com/2019/01/23/information-and-money/&quot;&gt;put something in someone else’s to-do list&lt;/a&gt;, you find a slot in their Calendly and send them money for it? My guess is no - the norms are mostly implied by the length and cost and permanence of the form. Could we have a form that better implies happier norms in that case?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="social-institutions" /><category term="why-this" /><summary type="html">There seems to be a common phenomenon where people get messages, then fail to respond to them, then feel bad. And the rarer strategy of actually dealing with all of one’s emails promptly doesn’t even seem obviously better. Was that how things were with letters or telegrams? Is it just that there are so many messages now, because they are easy to send?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/nth1rr9r5mdg31c/mathyas-kurmann-fb7yNPbT0l8-unsplash.jpg?raw=1" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.dropbox.com/s/nth1rr9r5mdg31c/mathyas-kurmann-fb7yNPbT0l8-unsplash.jpg?raw=1" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Flights of wonder</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/11/flights-of-wonder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flights of wonder" /><published>2020-12-11T01:35:54-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-11T01:35:54-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/11/flights-of-wonder</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/11/flights-of-wonder.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I put up the last page in &lt;a href=&quot;http://aiimpacts.org/&quot;&gt;AI Impacts&lt;/a&gt;’ (primarily Ronny Fernandez’s) &lt;a href=&quot;https://aiimpacts.org/are-human-engineered-flight-designs-better-or-worse-than-natural-ones/&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; into how human-made flying machines compare to evolved ones. (Relevant to how we expect human efforts to build minds to compare to evolved minds.) Evolution mostly won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other interesting things I learned in the process of editing this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monarch butterflies &lt;a href=&quot;https://aiimpacts.org/energy-efficiency-of-monarch-butterfly-flight/&quot;&gt;can probably fly&lt;/a&gt; at least 100km on the energy in about a quarter of a raspberry (not counting the energy they get from the wind, which seems to be central to their flying methods. And not to suggest that they eat raspberries, I am just more familiar with those than flower nectar).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdnsciencepub.com/doi/10.1139/z79-180&quot;&gt;People&lt;/a&gt; who estimate monarch butterfly ‘performance parameters’ sometimes do so by attaching plasticine to dead butterflies to get them to the right weight and balance, and then hand-throwing them across the room and noting measurements for those “in which no obvious pitching up or stalling occurred after release” (or at least they did in 1979).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paramotor&quot;&gt;Paramotors&lt;/a&gt; are a thing. They are like a giant fan you wear on your back to turn your paraglider into a powered vehicle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A model airplane &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=The_Spirit_of_Butts%27_Farm&amp;amp;oldid=918639855&quot;&gt;crossed the Atlantic on a gallon of fuel&lt;/a&gt; (this was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aiimpacts.org/are-human-engineered-flight-designs-better-or-worse-than-natural-ones/&quot;&gt;furthest per Joule&lt;/a&gt; of the machines in our collection).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/aerospace/comments/1hein1/great_photo_of_the_gossamer_albatross_from_1980/&quot;&gt;pedal-powered flying machine&lt;/a&gt; crossed the English Channel.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This might be a slightly different one:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/88/Gossamer_Albatross_II_in_flight.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gossamer Albatross with bikes, maybe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="work" /><category term="facts" /><summary type="html">Today I put up the last page in AI Impacts’ (primarily Ronny Fernandez’s) investigation into how human-made flying machines compare to evolved ones. (Relevant to how we expect human efforts to build minds to compare to evolved minds.) Evolution mostly won.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/88/Gossamer_Albatross_II_in_flight.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/88/Gossamer_Albatross_II_in_flight.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unexplored modes of language</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/unexplored-modes-of-language.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unexplored modes of language" /><published>2020-12-09T09:48:56-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-09T09:48:56-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/unexplored-modes-of-language</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/unexplored-modes-of-language.html">&lt;p&gt;English can be communicated via 2D symbols that can be drawn on paper using a hand and seen with eyes, or via sounds that can be made with a mouth and heard by ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two forms are the same language because the mouth sounds and drawn symbols correspond at the level of words (and usually as far as sounds and letters, at least substantially). That is, if I write ‘ambition’, there is a specific mouth sound that you would use if converting it to spoken English, whereas if you were converting it to spoken French, there might not be a natural equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, most popular languages are like this: they have a mouth-sound version and a hand-drawn (or hand-typed) version. They often have a braille version, with symbols that can be felt by touch instead of vision. An exception is sign languages (which are generally not just alternate versions of spoken languages), which use 4-D symbols gestured by hands over time, and received by eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder whether there are more modes of languages that it would be good to have. Would we have them, if there were? It’s not clear from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_sign_language&quot;&gt;a brief perusal of Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; that Europe had sophisticated sign languages prior to about five hundred years ago. Communication methods generally have strong network effects—it’s not worth communicating by some method that nobody can understand, just like it’s not worth joining an empty dating site—and new physical modes of English are much more expensive than for instance new messaging platforms, and have nobody to promote them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncommon modes of language that seem potentially good (an uninformed brainstorm):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;symbols drawn with hands on receiver’s skin, received by touch&lt;/strong&gt;, I’ve heard of blind and deaf people such as Helen Keller using this, but it seems useful for instance when it is loud, or when you don’t want to be overheard or to annoy people nearby, or for covert communication under the table at a larger event, or for when you are wearing a giant face mask.
-&lt;strong&gt;symbols gestured with whole body&lt;/strong&gt; like interpretive dance, but with objective interpretation. Good from a distance, when loud, etc. Perhaps conducive to different sorts of expressiveness, like how verbal communication makes singing with lyrics possible, and there is complementarity between the words and the music.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;symbols gestured with whole body, interpreted by computer, received as written text&lt;/strong&gt; What if keyboards were like a Kinect dance game? Instead of using your treadmill desk while you type with your hands, you just type with your arms, legs and body in a virtual reality whole-body keyboard space. Mostly good for exercise, non-sedentariness, feeling alive, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;drumming/tapping, received by ears or touch&lt;/strong&gt; possibly faster than spoken language, because precise sounds can be very fast. I don’t know. This doesn’t really sound good.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a sign version of English&lt;/strong&gt; this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellhealth.com/signing-exact-english-and-syntax-1046860&quot;&gt;exists, but is rare&lt;/a&gt;. Good for when it is loud, when you don’t want to be overheard, when you are wearing a giant face mask or are opposed to exhaling too much on the other person, when you are at a distance, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;symbols drawn with hands in one place&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. the surface of a phone, or a small number of phone buttons, such that you could enter stuff on your phone by tapping your fingers in place in a comfortable position with the hand you were holding it with, preferably still in your pocket, rather than awkwardly moving them around on the surface while you hold it either with another hand or some non-moving parts of the same hand, and having to look at the screen while you do it. This could be combined with the first one on this list.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What else?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe if there’s a really good one, we could overcome the network effect with an assurance contract. (Or try to, and learn more about why assurance contracts aren’t used more.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="social-innovation" /><category term="language" /><summary type="html">English can be communicated via 2D symbols that can be drawn on paper using a hand and seen with eyes, or via sounds that can be made with a mouth and heard by ears.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Walk to a San Francisco FedEx</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/walk-to-a-san-francisco-fedex.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Walk to a San Francisco FedEx" /><published>2020-12-09T09:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-09T09:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/walk-to-a-san-francisco-fedex</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/walk-to-a-san-francisco-fedex.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I had three work projects so close to done that I might be able to put something up on each, which would usually encourage work enthusiasm. But when I started on the first, I was struck by a strong inclination to stop and do something else. I didn’t immediately, but the inclination remained. And such inclinations make work worse in themselves, because when each new sentence or next motion engenders a little flinch away from it, the whole thing gets so slow and encumbered and hard to concentrate on that it makes sense to be repelled by it. And the thought of moving to the next little bit on the other projects seemed similarly distasteful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting in my chair was likewise aversive, and I thought perhaps a walk would help. (Often I find similar work compelling, so it seems a shame to wrestle myself into a slow and encumbered version of it at a time when I don’t.)  I also had a package to take to FedEx. If I listened to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://alignment-newsletter.libsyn.com/&quot;&gt;Alignment Newsletter Podcast&lt;/a&gt; while I walked and delivered the package, I might even be being extra productive instead of extra unproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took my &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/10/22/P100-PSA.html&quot;&gt;P100 mask&lt;/a&gt; and a packet of snickerdoodle flavored peanut butter and some moderately comfy shoes, in case the three and a half blocks to the pharmacy that FedEx was inside turned out to be too much for flip flops, or I decided to wander around more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached the pharmacy and stood in its small outside queue with my package between my legs and put on my P100. A man at the door let me in and pointed me to a longer inside queue. I waited in it and thought about how hard it was to see the total population of the room, and how much time had passed without the queue moving at all, and how much the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.sfgov.org/stories/s/dak2-gvuj&quot;&gt;San Francisco covid cases were spiking&lt;/a&gt;, then decided to try for a different FedEx down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left my P100 on and walked along faceless, listening to the podcast. Which sounded interesting, but I kept getting distracted. The warm bright sun on every surface sent away my vague image of the locked-down city as wan and enfeebled. Though I wondered if was climatically alarming for San Francisco winter to be such a nice summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed my mask, for reasons that are not entirely clear. Perhaps having one’s face in the public sphere does call for some ongoing attention and composure and care, that I don’t notice until its absence is a relief. Or perhaps it is nice for ones mouth and nose to be seriously removed from the clouds of covid dust, instead of just covered to the point of social acceptability. At any rate, I walked along with my mouth hanging open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the talk of alignment a happy background chatter, I got to thinking about how national policy should deal with different people having different impressions about morality. Morality is hard to detect in a publicly agreeable way. Insofar as a nation reacts to morality, the information reaches the nation via individuals making observations about it. But there are lots of individuals with different observations. People’s policy views are often that the government should enforce morality as they see it. Even though the nation includes people with different morality impressions. The policy game is seen as the game of having your morality implemented. But opinion could instead be at the level of what laws or norms a group of people should have when a subset thinks that doing X is immoral, and another subset wants to do it. Then the answers to object level questions, such as, ‘should people be free to have abortions?’ would fall out of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FedEx place was further than I expected, but a man outside just took the package from me. I waited a moment in case there was any problem with it, and looked at my phone, thinking about where to go next. A man on a bike stopped close to me and said something. I felt protected from having to respond much, due to my giant mask. But I think I gestured friendlily, before walking away. I sensed him watching me. Down the road a bit, I glanced back and saw him still there, looking my way. Then he rolled up next to me. “Can I have your number?” I still lacked the usual compulsion to respond to things people say to me, and my instinctive behavior was somehow akin to a foreigner who doesn’t speak the language. I looked at him vaguely and kept walking. He rolled along, and asked me where I was from, and my name, and if I speak Spanish. He introduced himself. He observed that I was scared of him, and told me that I shouldn’t be. He noted that all men would probably like me, I guess as some kind of point about whether I should be scared of him. I said some things, like ‘Australia’ and ‘I don’t want to talk’. Eventually he rode away, but so slowly I didn’t trust that he was really going. I stepped into the entry of a parking garage and discussed the fact that I was just temporarily hiding from that dude on a bike with a security guard there, who suggested that I call the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to go a different way home. I made eye contact with another guy in a car, who seemed to lean down to look at me more through the passenger window as I passed. I wondered whether mini skirt and apocalypse mask are actually an alluring combo. I admit that I enjoy something about the style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soles of my feet became blistered, and I did the velcro straps up tighter and thought about pain and suffering. I think I could walk on my feet until they were bleeding and raw pretty easily, if I wanted to. They hurt sharply, but it seems more loosely connected to suffering than other pains. I feel like my walking on them shyly is because I’m unsure whether it is ok to damage your feet that much, and that if  I decided to do it, I could do it without flinching. (A recollection of teenagerhood supports this: I vaguely recall my shoes being fairly bloody by about the second day of a four day hike, and marching on fairly unperturbed.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if a no-speaking P100 dance party in the park might be fun, but I guess it is illegal now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="san-francisco" /><category term="journal" /><category term="mundane" /><summary type="html">Today I had three work projects so close to done that I might be able to put something up on each, which would usually encourage work enthusiasm. But when I started on the first, I was struck by a strong inclination to stop and do something else. I didn’t immediately, but the inclination remained. And such inclinations make work worse in themselves, because when each new sentence or next motion engenders a little flinch away from it, the whole thing gets so slow and encumbered and hard to concentrate on that it makes sense to be repelled by it. And the thought of moving to the next little bit on the other projects seemed similarly distasteful.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why are delicious biscuits obscure?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/why-are-delicious-biscuits-obscure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why are delicious biscuits obscure?" /><published>2020-12-07T08:06:40-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-07T08:06:40-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/why-are-delicious-biscuits-obscure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/07/why-are-delicious-biscuits-obscure.html">&lt;p&gt;I saw a picture of these biscuits (or cookies), and they looked very delicious. So much so that I took the uncharacteristic step of actually making them. They were indeed among the most delicious biscuits of which I am aware. And yet I don’t recall hearing of them before. This seems like a telling sign about something. (The capitalist machinery? Culture? Industrial food production constraints? The vagaries of individual enjoyment?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/91nepe5q84xtbyf/iStock-1088141566.jpg?raw=1&quot; alt=&quot;Kolakakor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why doesn’t the market offer these delicious biscuits all over the place? Isn’t this just the kind of rival, excludable, information-available, well-internalized good that markets are on top of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some explanations that occur to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am wrong or unusual in my assessment of deliciousness, and for instance most people would find a chocolate chip cookie or an Oreo more delicious.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are harder to cook commercially than the ubiquitous biscuits for some reason. e.g. they are most delicious warm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They are Swedish, and there are mysterious cultural or linguistic barriers to foods spreading from their original homes. This would also help explain some other observations, to the extent that it counts as an explanation at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliciousness is not a central factor in food spread. (Then what is?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to help investigate, you can do so by carrying out the following recipe and reporting on the percentile of deliciousness of the resulting biscuits. (I do not claim that this is a high priority investigation to take part in, unless you are hungry for delicious biscuits or a firsthand encounter with a moderately interesting sociological puzzle.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kolakakor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Or &lt;em&gt;Kolasnittar&lt;/em&gt;. Adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houseandgarden.co.uk/recipe/caramel-shortbread&quot;&gt;House &amp;amp; Garden’s&lt;/a&gt; account of a recipe in Magnus Nilsson’s “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Nordic-Baking-Book-Magnus-Nilsson/dp/0714876844&quot;&gt;The Nordic Baking Book&lt;/a&gt;”. It’s quite plausible that their versions are better than mine, which has undergone pressure for ease plus some random ingredient substitutions. However I offer mine, since it is the one I can really vouch for.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Takes about fifteen minutes of making, and fifteen further minutes of waiting. Makes enough biscuits for about five people to eat too many biscuits, plus a handful left over. (Other recipe calls it about 40 ‘shortbreads’)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;200 g melted butter (e.g. microwave it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;180 g sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g golden syrup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50g honey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;300 g flour, ideally &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.kingarthurbaking.com/items/gluten-free-all-purpose-flour&quot;&gt;King Arthur gluten free flour&lt;/a&gt;, but wheat flour will also do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon bicarbonate of soda (baking soda)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoon ground ginger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 good pinches of salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat oven: 175°C/345°F&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put everything in a mixing bowl (if you have kitchen scales, put the mixing bowl on them, set scales to zero, add an ingredient, reset scales to zero, add the next ingredient, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mix.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taste [warning: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/foodsafety/communication/no-raw-dough.html&quot;&gt;public health officials say not to do this because eating raw flour is dangerous&lt;/a&gt;]. Adjust mixedness, saltiness, etc. It should be very roughly the consistency of peanut butter, i.e. probably less firm than you expect. (Taste more, as desired. Wonder why we cook biscuits at all. Consider rebellion. Consider Chesterton’s fence. Taste one more time.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cover a big tray or a couple of small trays with baking paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the dough into about four logs, around an inch in diameter, spaced several inches from one another and the edges of the paper. They can be misshapen; their shapes are temporary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook for about 15 minutes, or until golden and spread out into 1-4 giant flat seas of biscuit. When you take them out, they will be very soft and probably not appear to be cooked.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As soon as they slightly cool and firm up enough to pick up, start chopping them into strips about 1.25 inches wide and eating them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonus mystery: they are gluten free, egg free, and can probably easily be dairy free. The contest with common vegan and/or gluten free biscuit seems even more winnable, so why haven’t they even taken over that market?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">I saw a picture of these biscuits (or cookies), and they looked very delicious. So much so that I took the uncharacteristic step of actually making them. They were indeed among the most delicious biscuits of which I am aware. And yet I don’t recall hearing of them before. This seems like a telling sign about something. (The capitalist machinery? Culture? Industrial food production constraints? The vagaries of individual enjoyment?)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://64.media.tumblr.com/677cfd36966af74219450664deb547bf/9f284db7e8490a40-3f/s1280x1920/8e37d3d1547e17df6c38eef25d0536e7ae8466cf.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://64.media.tumblr.com/677cfd36966af74219450664deb547bf/9f284db7e8490a40-3f/s1280x1920/8e37d3d1547e17df6c38eef25d0536e7ae8466cf.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What it really looks like</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/06/photographs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What it really looks like" /><published>2020-12-06T10:45:22-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-06T10:45:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/06/photographs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/06/photographs.html">&lt;blockquote class=&quot;imgur-embed-pub&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; data-id=&quot;a/lRoMfR0&quot; data-context=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//imgur.com/a/lRoMfR0&quot;&gt;Near Sutro Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A photograph taken during a discussion of how photographs often fail to capture scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that photos often don’t capture what the photographer saw in the scene (perhaps especially if the photographer isn’t really a photographer). But it’s kind of amazing that I think of this as ‘the photograph failed to capture what it was really like’, rather than ‘my perception failed to capture what it was really like, as evidenced by this photograph’!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if it is possible to make a camera that captures scenes the way they look to a person there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a mundane example, it would need to make the moon appear big, when a camera might capture it as tiny. Is there a two dimensional set of pixels that can produce the same sense of how big the moon is, without changing other aspects of the picture to be further away from the perception? Is there such a two dimensional image for any perceived scene?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With sufficiently good what-it-seemed-like-to-the-photographer cameras, we could make substantial progress on bridging the gaping gaps between different minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I suppose you can always edit the colors a bit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="perception" /><summary type="html">Near Sutro Tower</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cultural accumulation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/cultural-accumulation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cultural accumulation" /><published>2020-12-05T21:08:11-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-05T21:08:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/cultural-accumulation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/05/cultural-accumulation.html">&lt;p&gt;When I think of humans being so smart due to ‘cultural accumulation’, I think of lots of tiny innovations in thought and technology being made by different people, and added to the interpersonal currents of culture that wash into each person’s brain, leaving a twenty year old in 2020 much better intellectually equipped than a 90 year old who spent their whole life thinking in 1200 AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I was chatting to my boyfriend about whether a person who went back in time (let’s say a thousand years) would be able to gather more social power than they can now in their own time. Some folk we know were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/mzgtmmTKKn5MuCzFJ/p/oiuZjPfknKsSc5waC#Discussion_on_the_ease_of_taking_control_of_the_world&quot;&gt;discussing&lt;/a&gt; the claim that some humans would have a shot at literally take over the world if sent back in time, and we found this implausible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious differences between a 2020 person and a 1200 AD person, in 1200 AD, is that they have experience with incredible technological advances that the 1200 AD native doesn’t even know are possible. But a notable thing about a modern person is that they famously &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.behance.net/gallery/35437979/Velocipedia&quot;&gt;don’t know what a bicycle looks like&lt;/a&gt;, so the level of technology they might be able to actually rebuild on short notice  in 1200 AD is probably not at the level of a nutcracker, and they probably already had those in 1200 AD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does 2020 have complicated technology, if most people don’t know how it works? One big part is specialization: across the world, quite a few people do know what bicycles look like. And more to the point, presumably some of them know in great detail what bicycle chains look like, and what they are made of, and what happens if you make them out of slightly different materials or in slightly different shapes, and how such things interact with the functioning of the bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But suppose the 2020 person who is sent back is a bicycle expert, and regularly builds their own at home. Can they introduce bikes to the world &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bicycle#History&quot;&gt;600 years early&lt;/a&gt;? My tentative guess is yes, but not very ridable ones, because they don’t have machines for making bike parts, or any idea what those machines are like or the principles behind them. They can probably demonstrate the idea of a bike with wood and cast iron and leather, supposing others are cooperative with various iron casting, wood shaping, leather-making know-how. But can they make a bike that is worth paying for and riding?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure, and bikes were selected here for being so simple that an average person might know what their machinery looks like. Which makes them unusually close among technologies to simple chunks of metal. I don’t think a microwave oven engineer can introduce microwave ovens in 1200, or a silicon chip engineer can make much progress on introducing silicon chips. These require other technologies that require other technologies too many layers back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if the whole of 2020 society was transported to 1200? The metal extruding experts and the electricity experts and the factory construction experts and Elon Musk? Could they just jump back to 2020 levels of technology, since they know everything relevant between them? (Assuming they are somehow as well coordinated in this project as they are in 2020, and are not just putting all of their personal efforts into avoiding being burned at the stake or randomly tortured in the streets.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big way this might fail is if 2020 society knows everything between them needed to use 2020 artifacts to get more 2020 artifacts, but don’t know how to use 1200 artifacts to get 2020 artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that story, the 1200 people might start out knowing methods for making c. 1200 artifacts using c. 1200 artifacts, but they accumulate between them the ideas to get them to c. 1220 artifacts with the c. 1200 artifacts, which they use to actually create those new artifacts. They pass to their children this collection of c. 1220 artifacts and the ideas needed to use those artifacts to get more c. 1220 artifacts. But the new c. 1220 artifacts and methods replaced some of the old c. 1200 artifacts and methods. So the knowledge passed on doesn’t include how to use those obsoleted artifacts to create the new artifacts, or the knowledge about how to make the obsoleted artifacts. And the artifacts passed on don’t include the obsoleted ones. If this happens every generation for a thousand years, the cultural inheritance received by the 2020 generation includes some highly improved artifacts plus the knowledge about how to use them, but not necessarily any record of the path that got there from prehistory, or of the tools that made the tools that made the tools that made these artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This differs from my first impression of ‘cultural accumulation’ in that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;physical artifacts are central to the process: a lot of the accumulation is happening inside them, rather than in memetic space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;humanity is not accumulating all of the ideas it has come up with so far, even the important ones. It is accumulating something more like a best set of instructions for the current situation, and throwing a lot out as it goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this is how things are, or is my first impression more true?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="history" /><category term="social-dynamics" /><summary type="html">When I think of humans being so smart due to ‘cultural accumulation’, I think of lots of tiny innovations in thought and technology being made by different people, and added to the interpersonal currents of culture that wash into each person’s brain, leaving a twenty year old in 2020 much better intellectually equipped than a 90 year old who spent their whole life thinking in 1200 AD.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://imgur.com/a/ERQ1xlR" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://imgur.com/a/ERQ1xlR" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Distanced Christmas book celebration</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/04/distanced-christmas-book-celebration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Distanced Christmas book celebration" /><published>2020-12-04T22:34:34-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T22:34:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/04/distanced-christmas-book-celebration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/04/distanced-christmas-book-celebration.html">&lt;p&gt;I attended a friend’s wedding this year, that was in the form of a play which everyone was sent in book form, to read at the same time from different places. There were various interactive interludes, including phone calls with strangers I had been algorithmically matched with, and a big group Zoom. I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a child, I had a ‘Christmas book’ that I liked, with lots of different nice things in it, like stories about the nativity, and about the Christmas ceasefire in World War I, and songs, and instructions for making foods and decorations, and descriptions of Christmas in other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Christmas I was mostly alone, since I live in America and my family lives in Australia. I celebrated by myself: I made myself a Christmas stocking full of things like pens and post-it notes and beads and chocolate (with a traditional balloon on it), and had hot chocolate, and opened presents, and then I read a book of essays that I had collected up online beforehand and printed out nicely. The theme was something like, ‘being in touch with far away people, elsewhere and in the past, and in particular trying to see what they are really like, and to remember that they are not like what I think’. There are ways you can be especially close to people by reading their words that are different from the ways you can be close by chatting and eating together, and I hoped to do those ones, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year lots of people are forced to stay at home, so I have plenty of company. But if I were going to celebrate relatively alone at the same time as my friends or family were doing the same thing elsewhere, I like the idea of trying to combine these ideas somehow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="christmas" /><category term="advice" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I attended a friend’s wedding this year, that was in the form of a play which everyone was sent in book form, to read at the same time from different places. There were various interactive interludes, including phone calls with strangers I had been algorithmically matched with, and a big group Zoom. I liked it.</summary></entry></feed>