<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-17T03:18:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">What is going on in the world?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/whats-going-on.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is going on in the world?" /><published>2021-01-17T01:28:39-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T01:28:39-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/whats-going-on</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/whats-going-on.html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of alternative high level narratives about what is importantly going on in the world—the central plot, as it were—for the purpose of thinking about what role in a plot to take:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The US is falling apart rapidly (on the scale of years), as evident in US politics departing from sanity and honor, sharp polarization, violent civil unrest, hopeless pandemic responses, ensuing economic catastrophe, one in a thousand Americans dying by infectious disease in 2020, and the abiding popularity of Trump in spite of it all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Western civilization is declining on the scale of half a century, as evidenced by its inability to build things it used to be able to build, and the ceasing of apparent economic acceleration toward a singularity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI agents will control the future, and which ones we create is the only thing about our time that will matter in the long run. Major subplots:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;‘Aligned’ AI is necessary for a non-doom outcome, and hard.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Arms races worsen things a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The order of technologies matters a lot / who gets things first matters a lot, and many groups will develop or do things as a matter of local incentives, with no regard for the larger consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Seeing more clearly what’s going on ahead of time helps all efforts, especially in the very unclear and speculative circumstances (e.g. this has a decent chance of replacing subplots here with truer ones, moving large sections of AI-risk effort to better endeavors).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The main task is finding levers that can be pulled at all.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bringing in people with energy to pull levers is where it’s at.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Institutions could be way better across the board, and these are key to large numbers of people positively interacting, which is critical to the bounty of our times. Improvement could make a big difference to swathes of endeavors, and well-picked improvements would make a difference to endeavors that matter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most people are suffering or drastically undershooting their potential, for tractable reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most human effort is being wasted on endeavors with no abiding value.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we take anthropic reasoning and our observations about space seriously, we appear very likely to be in a ‘Great Filter’, which appears likely to kill us (and unlikely to be AI).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone is going to die, the way things stand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most of the resources ever available are in space, not subject to property rights, and in danger of being ultimately had by the most effective stuff-grabbers. This could begin fairly soon in historical terms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nothing we do matters for any of several reasons (moral non-realism, infinite ethics, living in a simulation, being a Boltzmann brain, ..?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are vast quantum worlds that we are not considering in any of our dealings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a strong chance that we live in a simulation, making the relevance of each of our actions different from that which we assume.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is reason to think that acausal trade should be a major factor in what we do, long term, and we are not focusing on it much and ill prepared.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expected utility theory is the basis of our best understanding of how best to behave, and there is reason to think that it does not represent what we want. Namely, Pascal’s mugging, or the option of destroying the world with all but one in a trillion chance for a proportionately greater utopia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Petersburg_paradox#The_paradox&quot;&gt;etc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consciousness is a substantial component of what we care about, and we not only don’t understand it, but are frequently convinced that it is impossible to understand satisfactorily. At the same time, we are on the verge of creating things that are very likely conscious, and so being able to affect the set of conscious experiences in the world tremendously. Very little attention is being given to doing this well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have weapons that could destroy civilization immediately, which are under the control of various not-perfectly-reliable people. We don’t have a strong guarantee of this not going badly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biotechnology is advancing rapidly, and threatens to put extremely dangerous tools in the hands of personal labs, possibly bringing about a ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalpolicyjournal.com/articles/global-public-goods-and-bads/vulnerable-world-hypothesis#:~:text=This%20paper%20introduces%20the%20concept,semi%E2%80%90anarchic%20default%20condition'.&quot;&gt;vulnerable world&lt;/a&gt;’ scenario.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technology keeps advancing, and we may be in a vulnerable world scenario.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The world is utterly full of un-internalized externalities and they are wrecking everything.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are lots of things to do in the world, we can only do a minuscule fraction, and we are hardly systematically evaluating them at all. Meanwhile massive well-intentioned efforts are going into doing things that are probably much less good than they could be.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI is powerful force for good, and if it doesn’t pose an existential risk, the earlier we make progress on it, the faster we can move to a world of unprecedented awesomeness, health and prosperity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are risks to the future of humanity (‘existential risks’), and vastly more is at stake in these than in anything else going on (if we also include catastrophic trajectory changes). Meanwhile the world’s thinking and responsiveness to these risks is incredibly minor and they are taken unseriously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The world is controlled by governments, and really awesome governance seems to be scarce and terrible governance common. Yet we probably have a lot of academic theorizing on governance institutions, and a single excellent government based on scalable principles might have influence beyond its own state.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The world is hiding, immobilized and wasted by a raging pandemic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a draft. What should I add? (If, in life, you’ve chosen among ways to improve the world, is there a simple story within which your choices make particular sense?)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ea" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">Here’s a list of alternative high level narratives about what is importantly going on in the world—the central plot, as it were—for the purpose of thinking about what role in a plot to take:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meditative thinking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/15/meditative-thinking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meditative thinking" /><published>2021-01-15T17:27:29-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-15T17:27:29-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/15/meditative-thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/15/meditative-thinking.html">&lt;p&gt;I got fairly into meditation in 2018. Not in a way where you do a huge amount of meditation, or seek guidance on how to do meditation well, or on whether what you are doing is meditation at all. I don’t think I even graduated from doing meditation largely in five minute bouts. I just really dug a set of mental things which seemed related to meditation. I was riding an ethos. I suppose meditation was a particularly namable point in the space, but not obviously the most exciting part of it, so I ended up being pretty excited about ‘meditation…?’ while not actually meditating that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also remained so ignorant about meditation traditions and previous human meditation experience that you might doubt that I’m talking about the same thing. (I did talk to other people a little, and did about five guided meditations, which seemed like a different kind of thing anyway, but also very awesome.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that said, here’s a kind of meditation I made up. I call it, ‘meditative thinking’. In it, you do all the stuff you would usually do while meditating: be in a meditation-conducive position (I do lying on my back, which I hear is a bad idea, but it is very comfy); set a meditation timer with bells at the start and end (mine also makes water sounds between them, but this probably isn’t crucial); close your eyes; be aware of your breathing; then just go on being aware of stuff in a conspicuously conscious way. But before all this, choose a question to think about. And then, once meditating, think about the question. Maintain the same mental stance as you normally would meditating, insofar as that makes sense. Be aware of your breathing, and your awareness, and your thinking. If you stop thinking about the question, gently bring your awareness back to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still find this good. Though it’s possible that it gets much of its benefit from being a ritualistic way to actually think about a question for five or ten minutes without reflexively opening Facebook because thinking doesn’t correspond to a tab or occupy one’s hands.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meditation" /><category term="practical-advice" /><summary type="html">I got fairly into meditation in 2018. Not in a way where you do a huge amount of meditation, or seek guidance on how to do meditation well, or on whether what you are doing is meditation at all. I don’t think I even graduated from doing meditation largely in five minute bouts. I just really dug a set of mental things which seemed related to meditation. I was riding an ethos. I suppose meditation was a particularly namable point in the space, but not obviously the most exciting part of it, so I ended up being pretty excited about ‘meditation…?’ while not actually meditating that much.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">San Francisco outing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/15/san-francisco-outing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="San Francisco outing" /><published>2021-01-15T02:32:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-15T02:32:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/15/san-francisco-outing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/15/san-francisco-outing.html">&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202446423.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 430px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202446423&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202723913.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 430px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202723913&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202241573.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 430px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202241573&quot; /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_200936571.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_200936571&quot; /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202623152.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 350px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202623152&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202350627(1).jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 350px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202350627(1)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202420653.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 350px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202420653&quot; /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_201815353.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_201815353&quot; /&gt;




&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_201538697(1).jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 320px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_201538697(1)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202319122.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 320px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202319122&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_201511879.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 320px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_201511879&quot; /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202543175(1).jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 360px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202543175(1)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202628869.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 360px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202628869&quot; /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_195743905.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 320px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_195743905&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_201016516.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 320px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_201016516&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_202042963.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;height: 320px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_202042963&quot; /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_203249024.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 750px&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_203249024&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201223_201602726.jpg?width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080&amp;amp;fit=bounds&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;PXL_20201223_201602726&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="photography" /><category term="san-francisco" /><category term="journal" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discussion on the choice of concepts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/13/discussion-on-the-choice-of-concepts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discussion on the choice of concepts" /><published>2021-01-13T18:52:50-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-13T18:52:50-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/13/discussion-on-the-choice-of-concepts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/13/discussion-on-the-choice-of-concepts.html">&lt;p&gt;“The reason that you can currently make toast without doing great damage is just that your toaster is stupid.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Can ‘stupid’ be correctly applied to toasters?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What if I say no?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, if you have a conception of stupidity that can’t be applied to toasters, and one that can, why would you choose the one that can’t?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But I don’t have two—I’m talking about the actual concept”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There isn’t an actual concept, there are a bajillion concepts, and you can use whichever one you want.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s one that people mean”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Not really—each person has a slightly different usage, and probably hasn’t pinned it down. For instance if you ask them if toasters are stupid, they might be unsure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes! They are unsure because they are trying to guess what the real concept is, from their limited collection of exposures to it. If it were about making one up, why would they be uncertain?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They might be uncertain which one they want to make up”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re saying when people say words, they are ascribing meanings to them that they just made up, according to which definition they like most?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, they like definitions that fit with other people’s usage a lot more than other ones.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think they are just guessing what the real meaning is”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There isn’t a real meaning”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ok, what the consensus meaning is”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There isn’t a consensus”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah but they believe there is one”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re like a word meaning nihilist—you want only these ‘real’ word meanings or at least these word meanings of consensus, yet you know they don’t exist. That seems sad.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Maybe, but that doesn’t make it wrong. And also, I was talking about what other people do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What does it matter what other people do? You can use whatever meanings you want.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That seems unfriendly somehow”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What if you do it in a friendly way? For instance, where a meaning is ambiguous, if you choose the best one. For instance, if you say toasters can be stupid?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s more a vibe of do-it-alone responsibility for everything, thinking of others as machinery that happens to be near you, that rings my alarm bells. Leaving the common experience of word usage to stand outside the system, as it were, and push the common stock of concepts in the way that you calculate best. At least it seems somehow lonely and cold”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s a bit dramatic - I think the odd nudge in a good direction is well within the normal human experience of word usage. Plus, often people clearly redefine words somewhat in the context of a specific conversation. Would it be so strange if within our conversation we deemed ‘stupid’ applicable to toasters? Not doing so seems like it will only limit our discussion and edge us toward taking up some further concept like shmoopid to fill the gap.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s not clear at all to me that that is the only bad consequence at stake. For instance, words have all kinds of connotations besides what you explicitly think of them as about. If you just declare that stupid applies to toasters, then try to use it, you’ll doubtless be saying all kinds of things about toasters that you don’t mean. For instance, that that they are mildly reprehensible, and that you don’t like them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know if I would have used it if I didn’t implicitly accept the associations, and this is a risk one seems to always run in using words, even when you would deem them to apply.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hmm. Ok, maybe. This sounds like a lot of work though, and I have done ok not thinking about using my influence over words until this day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You think you have done ok, but word meanings are a giant tragedy of the commons. You might have done untold damage. We know that interesting concepts are endlessly watered down by exaggerators and attention seekers choosing incrementally wider categories at every ambiguity. That kind of thing might be going on all over the place. Maybe we just don’t know what words could be, if we were trying to do them well, instead of everyone being out to advance their own utterings.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="dialogue" /><category term="language" /><summary type="html">“The reason that you can currently make toast without doing great damage is just that your toaster is stupid.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s good about haikus?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/12/haikus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What's good about haikus?" /><published>2021-01-12T23:00:34-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-12T23:00:34-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/12/haikus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/12/haikus.html">&lt;p&gt;Fiction often asks its readers to get through a whole list of evocative scenery to imagine before telling them anything about the situation that might induce an interest in what the fields and the flies looked like, or what color stuff was. I assume that this is fun if you are somehow more sophisticated than me, but I admit that I don’t enjoy it (yet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am well capable of enjoying actual disconnected scenery. But imagining is effort, so the immediate action of staring at the wall, say, seems like a better deal than having to imagine someone else’s wall to be staring at. Plus, a wall is already straining my visual-imaginative capacities, and there are probably going to be all kinds of other things, and some of them are probably going to be called exotic words to hammer in whatever kind of scenic je ne sais quoi is going to come in handy later in the book, so I’m going to have to look them up or think about it while I keep from forgetting the half-built mental panorama constructed so far. It’s a chore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My boyfriend and I have recently got into reading haikus together. They mostly describe what things look like a bit, and then end. So you might think I would dislike them even more than the descriptive outsets of longer stories. But actually I ask to read them together every night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think part of it is just volume. The details of a single glance, rather than a whole landscape survey, I can take in. And combined with my own prior knowledge of the subject, it can be a rich picture. And maybe it is just that I am paying attention to them in a better way, but it seems like the details chosen to bring into focus are better. Haikus are like a three stroke drawing that captures real essence of the subject. My boyfriend also thinks there is often something clean about the images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some by Matsuo Bashō from our book The Essential Haiku, edited by Robert Hass [ETA: line positionings not as in original]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In the fish shop&lt;br /&gt;
the gums of the salt-bream&lt;br /&gt;
look cold
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Early fall—&lt;br /&gt;
The sea and the rice fields&lt;br /&gt;
all one green.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Another year gone—&lt;br /&gt;
hat in my hand,&lt;br /&gt;
sandals on my feet.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
More than ever I want to see&lt;br /&gt;
in these blossoms at dawn&lt;br /&gt;
the god’s face.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The peasant’s child,&lt;br /&gt;
husking rice, stops&lt;br /&gt;
and gazes at the moon.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Year after year&lt;br /&gt;
On the monkey’s face&lt;br /&gt;
A monkey face
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten words&lt;br /&gt;
Draw on my mind&lt;br /&gt;
Cleaner than fifty lines&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="poetry" /><summary type="html">Fiction often asks its readers to get through a whole list of evocative scenery to imagine before telling them anything about the situation that might induce an interest in what the fields and the flies looked like, or what color stuff was. I assume that this is fun if you are somehow more sophisticated than me, but I admit that I don’t enjoy it (yet).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A vastly faster vaccine rollout</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/11/vaccine-rollout-speed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A vastly faster vaccine rollout" /><published>2021-01-11T20:20:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T20:20:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/11/vaccine-rollout-speed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/11/vaccine-rollout-speed.html">&lt;p&gt;When a traveler introduced smallpox to New York City in 1947, the city—and in particular its health commissioner, Israel Weinstein—apparently ran an epic vaccination campaign, reaching 5 million people in the first two weeks.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; That is, four hundred thousand vaccinations per day. San Francisco in two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For covid, the first New York City vaccine &lt;a href=&quot;https://abc7ny.com/covid-vaccine-coronavirus-pfizer-ny/8763858/&quot;&gt;was given&lt;/a&gt; on the 14th of December, and if I understand, by the 10th of January, twenty seven days later, 203,181 doses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-vaccines-new-york/mass-vaccination-sites-open-in-new-york-city-as-covid-19-batters-u-s-idUSKBN29F0NR&quot;&gt;had reportedly been given&lt;/a&gt;. That’s around eight thousand doses per day. A factor of fifty fewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a pretty incredible difference. Why is New York fifty times slower at delivering covid vaccines in 2021 than it was at delivering smallpox vaccines in 1947?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the answer is presumably ‘regression to the mean’: if thousands of different cities at different times try to roll out vaccinations quickly, with a similar basic ability to do so, and there is some random chance in how well it goes, then the one we tell stories about seventy years later will one that got surprisingly lucky. You shouldn’t expect your own effort to go as well as that best one. But—without having done the statistics—I don’t think you should expect your attempt to be fifty times worse. New York didn’t get &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps there are other differences in the problems faced. For instance, the current vaccine needs refrigeration, or we are so late in the disease spread that we can’t all crowd together in around fast-moving vaccinators, or be rounded up in our natural crowded habitats, like classrooms or offices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the 1947 situation looks harder in important ways too. For one thing, there was no time to prepare. The vaccination project began the day that the disease was identified to health commissioner Weinstein. By 2pm, he was apparently holding a news conference publicly asking residents to be vaccinated. With covid, there were about ten months to prepare. For another thing, now people have smartphones with which they can be alerted, and computers and online systems that might be used to coordinate them and tell them what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about this episode from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://art19.com/shows/msnbc-rachel-maddow&quot;&gt;Rachel Maddow Show&lt;/a&gt;, and read about it in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/18/nyregion/nyc-smallpox-vaccine.html&quot;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, both of which bring it up to note the inadequacy in the current vaccine efforts. The New York Times says a rollout like this, “almost certainly couldn’t happen today”, and offers some explanations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complicated relationships between city and other governments these days
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“In 1947, the city was able to act alone, as opposed to navigating a complicated relationship with the governor of New York and the federal government,” said Dr. Irwin Redlener, director of the Pandemic Resource and Response Initiative at Columbia University’s Earth Institute. “The city was able to say, ‘We’re going after this,’ and then make it happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A ‘hollowing out’ of the public health infrastructure
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;But this time, with the coronavirus pandemic, New York faces a logistical hurdle. Experts in infectious disease point to a hollowing out of the public health infrastructure — not just in the city, but across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of public faith in medical science, government and the media
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“This was the height of polio in the United States,” he said. “People had a much better sense of the impact of infectious disease. They saw it all the time, and they were rightly fearful. But they were also optimistic that medical science could conquer this. In 1947, there was tremendous faith in the medical community, unlike today.”…
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  …Yet, [infectious disease experts] believe the biggest obstacle is not distribution but the public’s distrust of government, science and the media.
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  “We’re coming out of a train wreck of messaging,” Dr. Redlener said. “We’ve learned that politics is poison to a public health initiative, especially during a crisis. Honesty and straightforward, clear messaging are absolutely critical.”
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  In 1947, Dr. Weinstein was the only voice with a megaphone. He spoke and people listened.
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  “Back then, there was a much simpler media landscape,” Ms. Sherman said as she laid out the Ad Council’s campaign, which is due to kick off early next year. “In today’s environment, we’re dealing with a highly, highly fragmented media. We’ll be relying on micro-influencers who are the trusted voices.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They seem to favor #3, noting that it is what ‘experts believe’. But it seems so implausible—am I totally misunderstanding the claim? On the current margin, if lack of public trust was making the vaccine rollout even ten times slower, wouldn’t we see campaigns begging us to go out and get the incredibly accessible vaccine, rather than seeing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tampabay.com/news/health/2020/12/30/florida-seniors-begin-swarming-coronavirus-vaccination-sites/&quot;&gt;elderly people camping in outside queues&lt;/a&gt; to get vaccinated, and most people being told that they just can’t have a vaccine for months or a year? Perhaps they mean that ultimately the number of doses given out will be limited by public willingness to receive them? (Which seems surely true, but not necessarily the answer to an interesting question).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NYT’s other suggestions don’t seem immediately wrong, but are too vague for me to understand. I guess I’d like to know how things went differently at an object level. At what point, in 1947, did someone decide that it was their job to gather a volunteer army to administer vaccines, for instance? Do people work in similar roles nowadays? Did they think of this? Did they expect to get into trouble for having a bunch of lay people giving injections? Do they have to fill out a lot of paperwork to recruit them, whereas in 1947 they would have just shouted for them in the street? (I don’t know.) If New York had had these constraints, would their vaccination campaign have looked like ours, or is there more to explain?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose I have several questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is really going on, that can account for a near 50x slowdown?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why does the New York Times have such an unenlightening, vague, and seemingly wrong discussion so close to where one could have a genuinely interesting one?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/R4FX6wDmppvZ2JqpB/where-do-did-stable-cooperative-institutions-come-from&quot;&gt;Are these things related?&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My guess after thinking about it for ten seconds is that the gap in speed is to do with more things being regulated and formalized. The difference in time it would take me to physically cause someone to have a cookie versus to legally sell someone a cookie seems huge enough for this kind of thing to account for large slowdowns, and I do expect creating a massive band of volunteer non-nurses to administer a vaccine to require time-consuming paperwork or to be straight up illegal. How does this explanation sound?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just an idle inquiry, and shouldn’t be just another interesting story for another payload of political disapproval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naively extrapolating, New York City could be fully vaccinated in about seven weeks if we knew how to do what was done in 1947. At the current rate, which will presumably change, vaccinating everyone would take years.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if someone figured out how to replicate even part of what New York did before at Weinstein’s direction? In America alone, around three thousand people are dying each day now, as they wait for the vaccine. My boyfriend’s ninety year old grandmother in Vermont was diagnosed with covid last week. Her center was scheduled to begin vaccinating its residents this Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Regardless of what makes things slower these days, good on everyone who is working to forward the vaccination effort, and also those doing their best to make it appropriately safe. Good luck being fast and right.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. In fact the whole of America vaccinated fewer people in the first two weeks of having a covid vaccine than New York did in 1947:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/cumulative-covid-vaccinations?tab=chart&amp;amp;stackMode=absolute&amp;amp;country=USA~GBR~CHN~CAN~MEX~DEU~ITA&amp;amp;region=World&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 600px; border: 0px none;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also interestingly, others are not doing better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/service-pnp-cph-3c10000-3c10000-3c10400-3c10440v.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photograph shows school children waiting in line for immunization shots at a child health station in New York City, N.Y.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Photograph shows crowd of people waiting to be vaccinated at the Department of Health building, New York City.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photos from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loc.gov/resource/cph.3c10440/&quot;&gt;Office of War Information&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loc.gov/resource/cph.3c36364/&quot;&gt;Al Ravenna at the World Telegram and Sun&lt;/a&gt;, via the Library of Congress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My information about this is all from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/18/nyregion/nyc-smallpox-vaccine.html&quot;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1947_New_York_City_smallpox_outbreak&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://art19.com/shows/msnbc-rachel-maddow&quot;&gt;Rachel Maddow Show&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Naive extrapolation says six years, but this is especially naive since at that rate covid will speed things up by reaching many people before the vaccine does. Plus we should probably expect some speedup over time, if it was going to take that long. Or something different to happen. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="covid" /><category term="technology" /><category term="civilizational-decline" /><summary type="html">When a traveler introduced smallpox to New York City in 1947, the city—and in particular its health commissioner, Israel Weinstein—apparently ran an epic vaccination campaign, reaching 5 million people in the first two weeks.1 That is, four hundred thousand vaccinations per day. San Francisco in two days. My information about this is all from the New York Times, Wikipedia, and the Rachel Maddow Show &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/download.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/download.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The time I got really into poker</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/11/poker.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The time I got really into poker" /><published>2021-01-11T03:49:42-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T03:49:42-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/11/poker</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/11/poker.html">&lt;p&gt;One time I decided it would be good to learn to play poker. I had probably learned to play some form of poker a couple of other times before, and forgotten. One way to play a game a lot is to play it with a computer rather than other people. An iPad turns Agricola from one of the slowest games that casual board gamers might still be bothered to play to something you can play a few quick rounds of over lunch. I downloaded some kind of poker app, and began. It was maybe 9pm, and I was maybe sitting on my bed, in maybe Berkeley. My memories are pretty unclear. The app was green I think, like some kind of casino table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the app there were a series of tables with increasing stakes. The first one was ‘your grandmother’s table’ or something, at which you needed almost no money to play, and were given a lot of advice about what to do. If you won several games there, you could afford a single game at the next table up, and so on. If you lost enough that you could no longer buy in at your higher table, you would drop down, and if you could no longer afford grandmother’s, then you could transfer American dollars to the app-maker in exchange for more fake poker money, and keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the hang of the rules and began to play fast. And I got the hang of not losing and bought my way into higher tables. I played faster. I didn’t pause. The ends of games got the same reflexive flash of choice as any other part of the game. Time passed, and lots and lots of games. My mind started to wander, even while I played. It wandered to a memory of long ago, more vivid and detailed than memories that come when I call for them. How strange. I played very fast. And more memories appeared, intense against the smooth background of mindless poker. I don’t usually remember things for pleasure—recollection is a neutral activity, if not about something particularly upsetting or nice. But these were somehow pleasing. Not because they were about anything that would usually inspire happiness—they were mundane scenes, like a road that I crossed once to get to a gas station, and the look of the gas station, and the feeling of the sky and the car and the other passenger waiting and the afternoon (not a real example necessarily; I forget all of the particulars now)—but in their mere pungent existence, they felt somehow satisfying. I drifted between them and frantic yet peaceful poker. Hours passed. I often wondered what I had just done—what cards I had played, or why—and realized that I had no explicit recollection. More hours passed, and more scenes from younger years projected fragrantly into the flickering virtual cards. I don’t think I consciously explored the strange mental landscape, transfixed as I was by the irresistible torrent of poker moves to be made. I took action after action definitively, yet lived dreamlike above it. After nine hours, with morning beginning to establish itself, I stopped.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="biography" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">One time I decided it would be good to learn to play poker. I had probably learned to play some form of poker a couple of other times before, and forgotten. One way to play a game a lot is to play it with a computer rather than other people. An iPad turns Agricola from one of the slowest games that casual board gamers might still be bothered to play to something you can play a few quick rounds of over lunch. I downloaded some kind of poker app, and began. It was maybe 9pm, and I was maybe sitting on my bed, in maybe Berkeley. My memories are pretty unclear. The app was green I think, like some kind of casino table.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A different dictionary</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/09/a-different-dictionary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A different dictionary" /><published>2021-01-09T09:19:45-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-09T09:19:45-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/09/a-different-dictionary</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/09/a-different-dictionary.html">&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed James Somers &lt;a href=&quot;https://jsomers.net/blog/dictionary&quot;&gt;account&lt;/a&gt; (HT &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/12/19/thesauring.html#comment-5194868155&quot;&gt;Liron Shapira&lt;/a&gt;) of how Webster’s dictionary used to be much more beautiful than dictionaries today, for instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“…Flashing differs from exploding or disploding in not being accompanied with a loud report. To glisten, or glister, is to shine with a soft and fitful luster, as eyes suffused with tears, or flowers wet with dew.”&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Did you see that last clause? “To shine with a soft and fitful luster, as eyes suffused with tears, or flowers wet with dew.” I’m not sure why you won’t find writing like that in dictionaries these days, but you won’t. Here is the modern equivalent of that sentence in the latest edition of the Merriam-Webster: “glisten applies to the soft sparkle from a wet or oily surface &lt;glistening wet=&quot;&quot; sidewalk=&quot;&quot;&gt;.”
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Who decided that the American public couldn’t handle “a soft and fitful luster”? I can’t help but think something has been lost. “A soft sparkle from a wet or oily surface” doesn’t just sound worse, it actually describes the phenomenon with less precision. In particular it misses the shimmeriness, the micro movement and action, “the fitful luster,” of, for example, an eye full of tears — which is by the way far more intense and interesting an image than “a wet sidewalk.”
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It’s as if someone decided that dictionaries these days had to sound like they were written by a Xerox machine, not a person, certainly not a person with a poet’s ear, a man capable of high and mighty English, who set out to write the secular American equivalent of the King James Bible and pulled it off.&lt;/glistening&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My guess is that dictionaries became ‘official’ and so are written in an official style. And that official style is contrary to color and poetry, because these things are in some way personal, showing glints of a specific idiosyncratic soul. And part of the point of officialness is that the entity having it is expansively clean and impersonal, involving specific people only insofar as they can be homogenized and branded and made fungible. You’re not supposed to look them in the eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if this is related to dictionaries being commonly treated as authoritatively defining words rather than documenting a group of people’s efforts to feel around for their meanings. Somers also says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Notice, too, how much less certain the Webster definition seems about itself, even though it’s more complete — as if to remind you that the word came first, that the word isn’t defined by its definition here, in this humble dictionary, that definitions grasp, tentatively, at words, but that what words really are is this haze and halo of associations and evocations, a little networked cloud of uses and contexts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got curious about the author of this dictionary, Noah Webster, and learned about his 1783 &lt;em&gt;Blue backed speller&lt;/em&gt; (or formally, ‘A Grammatical Institute of the English Language’, speller section), which taught children to read and spell. It was the most popular American book at one point, according to Wikipedia, which also makes it sound like Webster might have had a substantial part in making American English different from English English:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His most important improvement, he claimed, was to rescue “our native tongue” from “the clamour[30] of pedantry” that surrounded English grammar and pronunciation. He complained that the English language had been corrupted by the British aristocracy, which set its own standard for proper spelling and pronunciation.[31] Webster rejected the notion that the study of Greek and Latin must precede the study of English grammar. The appropriate standard for the American language, argued Webster, was “the same republican principles as American civil and ecclesiastical constitutions.” This meant that the people-at-large must control the language; popular sovereignty in government must be accompanied by popular usage in language…
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
…As time went on, Webster changed the spellings in the book to more phonetic ones. Most of them already existed as alternative spellings.[33] He chose spellings such as defense, color, and traveler, and changed the re to er in words such as center. He also changed tongue to the older spelling tung, but this did not catch on.[34]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://webstersdictionary1828.com/Dictionary/word&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a version of Webster’s dictionary online, and Somers describes how to add it to your computer (which surprisingly worked for me in spite of his article being from 2014.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="words" /><category term="history" /><category term="sociology" /><category term="poetry" /><summary type="html">I enjoyed James Somers account (HT Liron Shapira) of how Webster’s dictionary used to be much more beautiful than dictionaries today, for instance:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why not? potato chips in a box edition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/why-not-box-of-chips-edition.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why not? potato chips in a box edition" /><published>2021-01-08T11:02:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T11:02:15-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/why-not-box-of-chips-edition</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/why-not-box-of-chips-edition.html">&lt;p&gt;In reviewing my year I came across these photos of a box of potato chips I took in January on a plane. I took them because it seemed so much better to me than chips in a bag:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20200121_220233.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chip box 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20200121_220350.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chip box 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20200121_220257.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chip box 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20200121_220310_(1).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chip box 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corners of the box opened out, so that it was like a bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I wonder, is it actually better or does it just seem so to me? If it is better, why aren’t most chips sold this way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ways it seems better to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you don’t get oil from the bag all over your hand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can see what you are picking up, which is somehow pleasing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and which also allows more delicate grasping, rather than just thrusting your hand into the food, which seems better for sharing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it has a natural surface to sit on, which is more pleasing than a bag that sits on its side&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it would fit neatly in a drawer, instead of taking up a large shapeless space (this is getting minor, but I do imagine it affecting what I would in fact want to buy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further evidence that this is good is that people often pour chips into bowls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A downside is that it seems to involve more packaging, though I’m not sure how much the environmental impacts of cardboard and normal chip packaging compare.  Other foods regularly involve cardboard boxes, along with numerous layers of other packign material, so it would be surprising if that was prohibitively costly. I think the foil-like layer is needed to avoid air getting in and making the chips stale (chips are actually packaged with nitrogen to keep fresh, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mentalfloss.com/article/51993/why-are-potato-chip-bags-always-half-empty&quot;&gt;apparently&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There could easily be costs I don’t know about. For instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.polymersolutions.com/blog/the-science-behind-packaging-the-chip-challenge-flavors/#:~:text=A%20typical%20potato%20chip%20bag,Surlyn%C2%AE%2C%20a%20thermoplastic%20resin.&quot;&gt;apparently&lt;/a&gt; normal chip packaging involves carefully chosen layers of polymer for things like repelling moisture and avoiding package breakage. And some materials will change the taste of ingredients. I also wonder if you could do a similar thing with creative use of entirely normal chip packaging, though there is less of an existence proof there. I’m imagining something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210108_195551123.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chip drawing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="why-not" /><category term="packaging" /><summary type="html">In reviewing my year I came across these photos of a box of potato chips I took in January on a plane. I took them because it seemed so much better to me than chips in a bag:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20200121_220350.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20200121_220350.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Condition-directedness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/condition-directedness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Condition-directedness" /><published>2021-01-08T01:21:42-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T01:21:42-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/condition-directedness</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/condition-directedness.html">&lt;p&gt;In chess, you can’t play by picking a desired end of the game and backward chaining to the first move, because there are vastly more possible chains of moves than your brain can deal with, and the good ones are few. Instead, chess players steer by heuristic senses of the worth of situations. I assume they still back-chain a few moves (‘if I go there, she’ll have to move her rook, freeing my queen’) but just leading from a heuristically worse to a heuristically better situation a short hop away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In life, it is often taken for granted that one should pursue goals, not just very locally, but over scales of decades. The alternative is taken to be being unambitious and directionless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there should also be an alternative that is equivalent to the chess one: heuristically improving the situation, without setting your eye on a particular pathway to a particular end-state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which seems like actually what people do a lot of the time. For instance, making your living room nice without a particular plan for it, or reading to be ‘well read’, or exercising to be ‘fit’ (at least insofar as having a nice living space and being fit and well-read are taken as generally promising situations rather than stepping stones immediately prior to some envisaged meeting, say). Even at a much higher level, spending a whole working life upholding the law or reporting on events or teaching the young because these put society in a better situation overall, not because they will lead to some very specific outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of its commonness, I’m not sure that I have heard of this type of action labeled as distinct from goal-directedness and undirectedness. I’ll call it condition-directedness for now. When people are asked for their five year plans, they become uncomfortable if they don’t have one, rather than proudly stating that they don’t currently subscribe to goal-oriented strategy at that scale. Maybe it’s just that I hang out in this strange Effective Altruist community, where all things are meant to be judged by their final measure on the goal, which perhaps encourages evaluating them explicitly with reference to an envisaged path to the goal, especially if it is otherwise hard to distinguish the valuable actions from doing whatever you feel like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like one could be condition-directed and yet very ambitious and not directionless. (Though your ambition would be non-specific, and your direction would be local, and maybe they are the worse for these things?) For instance, you might work tirelessly on whatever seems like it will improve the thriving of a community that you are part of, and always know in which direction you are pushing, and have no idea what you will be doing in five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether condition-directedness is a good kind of strategy would seem to depend on the game you are playing, and your resources for measuring and reasoning about it. In chess, condition-directedness seems necessary. Somehow longer term plans do seem more feasible in life than in chess though, so it is possible that they are always better in life, at the scales in question. I doubt this, especially given the observation that people often seem to be condition-directed, at least at some scales and in some parts of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(These thoughts currently seem confused to me - for instance, what is up with scales? How is my knowing that I do want to take the king relevant?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by a conversation with John Salvatier.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="life-strategy" /><category term="mental-strategy" /><summary type="html">In chess, you can’t play by picking a desired end of the game and backward chaining to the first move, because there are vastly more possible chains of moves than your brain can deal with, and the good ones are few. Instead, chess players steer by heuristic senses of the worth of situations. I assume they still back-chain a few moves (‘if I go there, she’ll have to move her rook, freeing my queen’) but just leading from a heuristically worse to a heuristically better situation a short hop away.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/elia-pellegrini-NfqDQa6953Q-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/elia-pellegrini-NfqDQa6953Q-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>