<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-16T08:29:04+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">What is my Facebook feed about?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/15/what-is-my-facebook-feed-about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is my Facebook feed about?" /><published>2024-05-15T23:02:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T23:02:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/15/what-is-my-facebook-feed-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/15/what-is-my-facebook-feed-about.html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I look at social media a bunch, but it would be hard for me to tell you what the actual content is, I suppose because whenever I’m looking at it, I’m focused on each object thing level in turn, not the big picture. So sometimes I’m curious what it is I read about there. Here is the answer for Facebook, in 2019—according to a list I found that appears to be a survey of such—and again now. Plausibly not at a useful level of abstraction, but I have a bit of a migraine and no more energy for this project.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;november-11-2019&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;November 11 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question about other people’s word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question about other people’s inferences from word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Illustrated sex joke&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouragement and instructions for opening up communication with attractive strangers in public places&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cute kid quote&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Historic anti women’s suffrage leaflet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cute kid quote and question about word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recommendation and anecdote for Roam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humorous anecdotal request for computer security problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joke I don’t get about Jesus with lots of emoticons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sokal affair&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advice on surviving bushfires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feminist writer screenshots and describes random online abuse from man&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharing of personal health data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science says a thing about dinosaurs and space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax policy trolling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saudi spies at twitter news&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sexual/biological facts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anecdote about medical system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ethics injoke&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current reading list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Travel photos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anecdote about australian bushfires with tenderness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long letter about policy goings on within medical system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Request for acronym unknown to me&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Funny law&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science about biology, cryonics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question about word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Politics opinion on events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Futuristic anime style politics cartoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notable patterns:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about word usage: 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kid related: 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;may-15-2024&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;May 15, 2024&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Before checking, my sense is that the rate of posts about children and getting married is way up.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI company politics commentary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Job and city change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invitation to help make game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Description of experience of making music&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book launch, project launch, new house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cryptic fertility life update&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social commentary on language, gender and wokeness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Old photo of two famous men&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Old photo of author winning an award&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Event ad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death of father&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of OP kissing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update on losing job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wedding planning views&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book launch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social commentary around political ideologies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death of dog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Questioning claim about changes in breathing rate over history&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take on home buying&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI lab politics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of partner on trip&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of self at work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Own photo of bird&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commentary on culture of judgment and author’s parents’ behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remembering child relative who died&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General self-help style commentary on human behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of dogs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mothers’ day and Aurora photos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invitation to help make game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some notable patterns:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kid related: 0-3 (maybe down from 2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marriage related: 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—&amp;gt; I’m pretty wrong about the density of children and marriage related posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job/book updates: 5 (up from 0)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller projects: 5 (up from 2-4)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—&amp;gt; Actually a lot of project related posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humor: ~0 (down from at least 5)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Word usage: 1 (down from at least 4)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—&amp;gt; Some classic sources of entertainment are way down (or we see random noise)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">Sometimes I look at social media a bunch, but it would be hard for me to tell you what the actual content is, I suppose because whenever I’m looking at it, I’m focused on each object thing level in turn, not the big picture. So sometimes I’m curious what it is I read about there. Here is the answer for Facebook, in 2019—according to a list I found that appears to be a survey of such—and again now. Plausibly not at a useful level of abstraction, but I have a bit of a migraine and no more energy for this project.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Things I hate about Partiful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/things-i-hate-about-partiful.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things I hate about Partiful" /><published>2024-05-09T22:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T22:24:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/things-i-hate-about-partiful</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/things-i-hate-about-partiful.html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The aesthetic for all parties is basically the same.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That aesthetic is bad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A party is an aesthetic creation, so having all guests’ first experience of the thing you are offering them be a chintzy piece of crap that matches every other chintzy piece of crap is much worse than if the thing they were selling was like low-quality toilet paper or something.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, the only way to be informed of parties using Partiful is via SMS. Perhaps this is idiosyncratic to me, but I have no desire to ever use SMS. I also don’t want to receive a message in the middle of whatever I’m doing to hear about a new party happening. Fuck off. This should only happen if the party is very time sensitive and important. Like if a best friend or much sought after celebrity is having a party in the next twenty minutes, sure text me, if you don’t have WhatsApp. Otherwise, ffs email me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, the only way to message the host a question about the party is to post it to the entire group. Yet there are very few questions I want to text an entire guest list about.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supposing I make the error of doing that (which I do not), as far as I can tell, the guest list receives an sms saying that I have sent a message, and they have to click to follow a link to the website to see what the message is. &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supposing I am considering posting such a message to the entire group, Partiful will instruct me to ‘Write something fun!’ Fuck off. I’ll decide what to write, and don’t need the condescending needling. Relatedly, if I debase myself and host something on Partiful, while I’m drafting the invitation, it has been known to describe me as ‘the wonderful [host]’. I don’t want your narrativizing. a) Maybe I’m not wonderful. You don’t know shit about me. b) I actually can’t tell if you are going to seriously write that when I post the event, so I need to investigate how to mitigate that possibility.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I’m invited to a party, things I’m not allowed to know until after I RSVP include a) who else is invited or going, and b) where it is. Like, what do you want me to decide about social events based on? Is this communism? It also feels like such officious withholding. Like, are you serious? You’re inviting me to hang out with people and you aren’t going to tell me which people until I say I’ll come? Are you on a power trip? Who is even on the power trip? The creators of Partiful on behalf of the hosts? “No, stand your ground, you’re a party creator now, don’t give up your advantage—they’ll give in and give in and RSVP eventually”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So naturally I go through the busywork of RSVPing “maybe” so I can see key details of the event. Which is annoying. But also it constitutes me saying to my friend “maybe I’ll come to your party”, which is a slightly shitty thing to say to an actual person I’m friends with, if for instance I think it’s pretty unlikely I’ll come to their party and merely want to check if this is the rare party that I do want to go to. Furthermore, now I’ve made it clear (to an as-yet unknown set of people who RSVP’d) that I’ve seen the party and am explicitly and concretely probably-rejecting it. I’m in a whole public social interaction with it. Whereas I might have liked to examine the party without engaging, leaving my knowledge of it and position on it ambiguous.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ok, so three steps in: I have moved from a contentless text message to a website and RSVP’d maybe and can at last see key details. At that point Partiful pops another notification into my phone telling me that I RSVP’d maybe.  Why? I know I RSVP’d maybe, because I was the person who did it, and it was three seconds ago. If later I don’t know and want to know, I’ll actually check in the event invitation, not the interminable list of similar looking messages from Partiful. And I was actually already looking at the event invitation until you distracted me with my phone. And if occasionally I err—thinking I RSVP’d maybe but really having RSVP’d a different thing, say—then this isn’t a fucking space expedition; things will be okay.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then probably I just forget about it and leave it as a maybe, because I have other things to do in life, and this has already gone on for way too long, and I have technically RSVP’d, and who knows if I’ll go to a thing. So that’s annoying for the host, if they might have liked a real RSVP.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if I do try to RSVP more specifically, my options are “I’m going” and “Can’t go”. So in the situation that arises nearly every time—I can go but I don’t want to—Partiful has decided I’m going to just tell a little white lie to the host? Or just that I should go unless I can’t? It’s true that declining events is a difficult issue, and for many people white lies are the way out. But that’s because it’s too awkward to say “I don’t want to”. But if there are only two messages you can send—basically ‘yes’ and basically ‘no’—selected by a company, it’s not actually awkward to choose the ‘no’ one, because it doesn’t distinguish not wanting to and not being able to. There’s no reason for Partiful to put a lie in your mouth there. It’s true that it’s also not that bad to say a falsehood, given that you only have two options, and are clearly most of the time going to want to say a thing you haven’t been given the option to say. But why add this note of false smarm? Like, Partiful could make the options “yes” and “no because my mother is in hospital”, and I wouldn’t hold it against people if they clicked the latter, but I would hold it against the maker of the options.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I decide to tell my friend I can’t go to their party, Partiful will message me on my phone again, with a crying face, saying sorry I can’t go to the party. I don’t need this shit. I don’t want your emotional involvement in my decisions about when to socialize, corporation. True, it’s only fake emotional involvement, but I don’t want to be bathed in the fake emotions of corporations either. I’m a social animal, this stuff does change how I feel, change my sense of the sea of minds I feel I’m surrounded by, the emotions of the world. At a basic level, it’s hard to say no to things, and yet I have to: the alternative is to waste my life being overwhelmed and not even able to make progress on the spew of second-rate things I sleepwalk into saying yes to. And being pinged with pictures of crying when I judge that something isn’t the right thing for me to go to, and say no doesn’t help me. Does it help the host? Do they want to manipulate me? Probably not. Is Partiful’s hope that I learn to go to Partiful parties a little bit more if I feel micro-guilty and micro-sad when I decline them, and then the hosts have the sense that people come to Partiful parties more, so the company benefits? I doubt it, I guess the makers just lack much sense of what a good social world could look like, and are thoughtlessly enacting trumped up emotion where available, in the hope that trumped up emotion gets attention, and attention gets success.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">The aesthetic for all parties is basically the same. That aesthetic is bad. A party is an aesthetic creation, so having all guests’ first experience of the thing you are offering them be a chintzy piece of crap that matches every other chintzy piece of crap is much worse than if the thing they were selling was like low-quality toilet paper or something. As far as I can tell, the only way to be informed of parties using Partiful is via SMS. Perhaps this is idiosyncratic to me, but I have no desire to ever use SMS. I also don’t want to receive a message in the middle of whatever I’m doing to hear about a new party happening. Fuck off. This should only happen if the party is very time sensitive and important. Like if a best friend or much sought after celebrity is having a party in the next twenty minutes, sure text me, if you don’t have WhatsApp. Otherwise, ffs email me. As far as I can tell, the only way to message the host a question about the party is to post it to the entire group. Yet there are very few questions I want to text an entire guest list about. Supposing I make the error of doing that (which I do not), as far as I can tell, the guest list receives an sms saying that I have sent a message, and they have to click to follow a link to the website to see what the message is.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-05-09_at_10.36.46_PM.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-05-09_at_10.36.46_PM.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">An explanation of evil in an organized world</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/02/the-problem-of-evil-in-an-organized-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An explanation of evil in an organized world" /><published>2024-05-02T05:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T05:18:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/02/the-problem-of-evil-in-an-organized-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/02/the-problem-of-evil-in-an-organized-world.html">&lt;p&gt;A classic problem with Christianity is the so-called ‘problem of evil’—that friction between the hypothesis that the world’s creator is arbitrarily good and powerful, and a large fraction of actual observations of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming up with solutions to the problem of evil is a compelling endeavor if you are really rooting for a particular bottom line re Christianity, or I guess if you enjoy making up faux-valid arguments for wrong conclusions. At any rate, I think about this more than you might guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think I’ve solved it! &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least, I thought of a new solution which seems better than the others I’ve heard. (Though I mostly haven’t heard them since high school.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world (much like anything) has different levels of organization. People are made of cells; cells are made of molecules; molecules are made of atoms; atoms are made of subatomic particles, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t actually make a person (of the usual kind) without including atoms, and you can’t make a whole bunch of atoms in a particular structure without having made a person. These are logical facts, just like you can’t draw a triangle without drawing corners, and you can’t draw three corners connected by three lines without drawing a triangle. In particular, even God can’t. (This is already established I think—for instance, I think it is agreed that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omnipotence_paradox&quot;&gt;God cannot make a rock so big that God cannot lift it&lt;/a&gt;, and that this is not a threat to God’s omnipotence.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So God can’t make the atoms be arranged one way and the humans be arranged another contradictory way. If God has opinions about what is good at different levels of organization, and they don’t coincide, then he has to make trade-offs. If he cares about some level aside from the human level, then at the human level, things are going to have to be a bit suboptimal sometimes. Or perhaps entirely unrelated to what would be optimal, all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We usually assume God only cares about the human level. But if we take for granted that he made the world maximally good, then we might infer that he also cares about at least one other level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think if we look at the world with this in mind, it’s pretty clear where that level is. If there’s one thing God really makes sure happens, it’s ‘the laws of physics’. Though presumably laws are just what you see when God cares. To be ‘fundamental’ is to matter so much that the universe runs on the clockwork of your needs being met. There isn’t a law of nothing bad ever happening to anyone’s child; there’s a law of energy being conserved in particle interactions. God cares about particle interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, God cares so much about what happens to sub-atomic particles that he actually never, to our knowledge, compromises on that front. God will let anything go down at the human level rather than let one neutron go astray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should we infer from this? That the majority of moral value is found at the level of fundamental physics (following &lt;a href=&quot;https://reducing-suffering.org/is-there-suffering-in-fundamental-physics/&quot;&gt;Brian Tomasik&lt;/a&gt; and then going further). Happily we don’t need to worry about this, because God has it under control. We might however wonder what we can infer from this about the moral value of other levels that are less important yet logically intertwined with and thus beyond the reach of God, but might still be more valuable than the one we usually focus on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">A classic problem with Christianity is the so-called ‘problem of evil’—that friction between the hypothesis that the world’s creator is arbitrarily good and powerful, and a large fraction of actual observations of the world. Coming up with solutions to the problem of evil is a compelling endeavor if you are really rooting for a particular bottom line re Christianity, or I guess if you enjoy making up faux-valid arguments for wrong conclusions. At any rate, I think about this more than you might guess. And I think I’ve solved it!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/70455faa-3bb4-4947-88f1-cc9bb5915428_1024x1024.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/70455faa-3bb4-4947-88f1-cc9bb5915428_1024x1024.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The first future and the best future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/25/the-first-future-or-the-best-future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The first future and the best future" /><published>2024-04-25T07:22:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-25T07:22:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/25/the-first-future-or-the-best-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/25/the-first-future-or-the-best-future.html">&lt;p&gt;It seems to me worth &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/lets-think-about-slowing-down-ai&quot;&gt;trying to slow down AI development&lt;/a&gt; to steer successfully around the shoals of extinction and out to utopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was thinking lately: even if I didn’t think there was any chance of extinction risk, it might still be worth prioritizing a lot of care over moving at maximal speed. Because there are many different possible AI futures, and I think there’s a good chance that the initial direction affects the long term path, and different long term paths go to different places. The systems we build now will shape the next systems, and so forth. If the first human-level-ish AI is brain emulations, I expect a quite different sequence of events to if it is GPT-ish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People genuinely pushing for AI speed over care (rather than just feeling impotent) apparently think there is negligible risk of bad outcomes, but also they are asking to take the first future to which there is a path. Yet possible futures are a large space, and arguably we are in a rare plateau where we could climb very different hills, and get to much better futures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="ai" /><summary type="html">It seems to me worth trying to slow down AI development to steer successfully around the shoals of extinction and out to utopia. But I was thinking lately: even if I didn’t think there was any chance of extinction risk, it might still be worth prioritizing a lot of care over moving at maximal speed. Because there are many different possible AI futures, and I think there’s a good chance that the initial direction affects the long term path, and different long term paths go to different places. The systems we build now will shape the next systems, and so forth. If the first human-level-ish AI is brain emulations, I expect a quite different sequence of events to if it is GPT-ish. People genuinely pushing for AI speed over care (rather than just feeling impotent) apparently think there is negligible risk of bad outcomes, but also they are asking to take the first future to which there is a path. Yet possible futures are a large space, and arguably we are in a rare plateau where we could climb very different hills, and get to much better futures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experiment on repeating choices</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/18/experiment-on-repeating-choices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experiment on repeating choices" /><published>2024-04-18T16:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T16:18:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/18/experiment-on-repeating-choices</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/18/experiment-on-repeating-choices.html">&lt;p&gt;People behave differently from one another on all manner of axes, and each person is usually pretty consistent about it. For instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to spend money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to worry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to listen vs. speak&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to jump to conclusions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how playful to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how spontaneous to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to prepare&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much to socialize&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much to exercise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much to smile&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how honest to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How snarky to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to trade off convenience, enjoyment, time and healthiness in food&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are often about trade-offs, and the best point on each spectrum for any particular person seems like an empirical question. Do people know the answers to these questions? I’m a bit skeptical, because they mostly haven’t tried many points. &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I think these mostly don’t feel like open empirical questions: people have a sense of what the correct place on the axis is (possibly ignoring a trade-off), and some propensities that make a different place on the axis natural, and some resources they can allocate to moving from the natural place toward the ideal place. And the result is a fairly consistent point for each person. For instance, Bob might feel that the correct amount to worry about things is around zero, but worrying arises very easily in his mind and is hard to shake off, so he ‘tries not to worry’ some amount based on how much effort he has available and what else is going on, and lands in a place about that far from his natural worrying point. He could actually still worry a bit more or a bit less, perhaps by exerting more or less effort, or by thinking of a different point as the goal, but in practice he will probably worry about as much as he feels he has energy for limiting himself to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people do intentionally choose a new point—perhaps by thinking about it and deciding to spend less money, or exercise more, or try harder to listen. Then they hope to enact that new point for the indefinite future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for choices we play out a tiny bit every day, there is a lot of scope for iterative improvement, exploring the spectrum. I posit that people should rarely be asking themselves ‘should I value my time more?’ in an abstract fashion for more than a few minutes before they just try valuing their time more for a bit and see if they feel better about that lifestyle overall, with its conveniences and costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are implicitly making the same choice a massive number of times, and getting it wrong for a tiny fraction of them isn’t high stakes, then it’s probably worth experiencing the different options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that point about the value of time came from Tyler Cowen a long time ago, but I often think it should apply to lots of other spectrums in life, like some of those listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this to be a reasonable strategy, the following need to be true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll actually get feedback&lt;/strong&gt; about the things that might be better or worse (e.g. if you smile more or less you might immediately notice how this changes conversations, but if you wear your seatbelt more or less you probably don’t get into a crash and experience that side of the trade-off)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimentation doesn’t burn anything important&lt;/strong&gt; at a much larger scale (e.g. trying out working less for a week is only a good use case if you aren’t going to get fired that week if you pick the level wrong)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can actually try other points on the spectrum&lt;/strong&gt;, at least a bit, without large up-front costs (e.g. perhaps you want to try smiling more or less, but you can only do so extremely awkwardly, so you would need to practice in order to experience what those levels would be like in equilibrium)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don’t already know what the best level is for you&lt;/strong&gt; (maybe your experience isn’t very important, and you can tell in the abstract everything you need to know - e.g. if you think eating animals is a terrible sin, then experimenting with more or less avoiding animal products isn’t going to be informative, because even not worrying about food makes you more productive, you might not care)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t actually follow this advice much. I think it’s separately hard to notice that many of these things are choices. So I don’t have much evidence about it being good advice, it’s just a thing I often think about. But maybe my default level of caring about things like not giving people advice I haven’t even tried isn’t the best one. So perhaps I’ll try now being a bit less careful about stuff like that. Where ‘stuff like that’ also includes having a well-defined notion of ‘stuff like that’ before I embark on experimentally modifying it. And ending blog posts well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="advice" /><summary type="html">People behave differently from one another on all manner of axes, and each person is usually pretty consistent about it. For instance: how much to spend money how much to worry how much to listen vs. speak how much to jump to conclusions how much to work how playful to be how spontaneous to be how much to prepare How much to socialize How much to exercise How much to smile how honest to be How snarky to be How to trade off convenience, enjoyment, time and healthiness in food These are often about trade-offs, and the best point on each spectrum for any particular person seems like an empirical question. Do people know the answers to these questions? I’m a bit skeptical, because they mostly haven’t tried many points.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55931011-09bd-4a06-b0db-1e68a2898314_1024x1024.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55931011-09bd-4a06-b0db-1e68a2898314_1024x1024.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mid-conditional love</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/17/mid-conditional-love.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mid-conditional love" /><published>2024-04-17T04:53:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-17T04:53:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/17/mid-conditional-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/17/mid-conditional-love.html">&lt;p&gt;People talk about unconditional love and conditional love. Maybe I’m out of the loop regarding the great loves going on around me, but my guess is that love is extremely rarely unconditional. Or at least if it is, then it is either very broadly applied or somewhat confused or strange: if you love me unconditionally, presumably you love everything else as well, since it is only conditions that separate me from the worms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have sympathy for this resolution—loving someone so unconditionally that you’re just crazy about all the worms as well—but since that’s not a way I know of anyone acting for any extended period, the ‘conditional vs. unconditional’ dichotomy here seems a bit miscalibrated for being informative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we instead assume that by ‘unconditional’, people mean something like ‘resilient to most conditions that might come up for a pair of humans’, my impression is that this is still too rare to warrant being the main point on the love-conditionality scale that we recognize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People really do have more and less conditional love, and I’d guess this does have important, labeling-worthy consequences. It’s just that all the action seems to be in the mid-conditional range that we don’t distinguish with names. A woman who leaves a man because he grew plump and a woman who leaves a man because he committed treason both possessed ‘conditional love’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wonder if we should distinguish these increments of mid-conditional love better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What concepts are useful? What lines naturally mark it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One measure I notice perhaps varying in the mid-conditional affection range is “when I notice this person erring, is my instinct to push them away from me or pull them toward me?” Like, if I see Bob give a bad public speech, do I feel a drive to encourage the narrative that we barely know each other, or an urge to pull him into my arms and talk to him about how to do better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This presumably depends on things other than the person. For instance, the scale and nature of the error: if someone you casually like throws a frisbee wrong, helping them do better might be appealing. Whereas if that same acquaintance were to kick a cat, your instinct might be to back away fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means perhaps you could construct a rough scale of mid-conditional love in terms of what people can do and still trigger the ‘pull closer’ feeling. For instance, perhaps there are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who you feel a pull toward when they misspell a word&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who you feel a pull toward when they believe something false&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People who you feel a pull toward when they get cancelled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You could also do this with what people can do and still be loved, but that’s more expensive to measure than minute urges.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">People talk about unconditional love and conditional love. Maybe I’m out of the loop regarding the great loves going on around me, but my guess is that love is extremely rarely unconditional. Or at least if it is, then it is either very broadly applied or somewhat confused or strange: if you love me unconditionally, presumably you love everything else as well, since it is only conditions that separate me from the worms. I do have sympathy for this resolution—loving someone so unconditionally that you’re just crazy about all the worms as well—but since that’s not a way I know of anyone acting for any extended period, the ‘conditional vs. unconditional’ dichotomy here seems a bit miscalibrated for being informative. Even if we instead assume that by ‘unconditional’, people mean something like ‘resilient to most conditions that might come up for a pair of humans’, my impression is that this is still too rare to warrant being the main point on the love-conditionality scale that we recognize. People really do have more and less conditional love, and I’d guess this does have important, labeling-worthy consequences. It’s just that all the action seems to be in the mid-conditional range that we don’t distinguish with names. A woman who leaves a man because he grew plump and a woman who leaves a man because he committed treason both possessed ‘conditional love’. So I wonder if we should distinguish these increments of mid-conditional love better. What concepts are useful? What lines naturally mark it? One measure I notice perhaps varying in the mid-conditional affection range is “when I notice this person erring, is my instinct to push them away from me or pull them toward me?” Like, if I see Bob give a bad public speech, do I feel a drive to encourage the narrative that we barely know each other, or an urge to pull him into my arms and talk to him about how to do better? This presumably depends on things other than the person. For instance, the scale and nature of the error: if someone you casually like throws a frisbee wrong, helping them do better might be appealing. Whereas if that same acquaintance were to kick a cat, your instinct might be to back away fast. This means perhaps you could construct a rough scale of mid-conditional love in terms of what people can do and still trigger the ‘pull closer’ feeling. For instance, perhaps there are: People who you feel a pull toward when they misspell a word People who you feel a pull toward when they believe something false People who you feel a pull toward when they get cancelled (You could also do this with what people can do and still be loved, but that’s more expensive to measure than minute urges.)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9768a4ea-83cd-417b-8458-df46f3999e4b_4359x2907.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9768a4ea-83cd-417b-8458-df46f3999e4b_4359x2907.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Partial value takeover without world takeover</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/05/partial-value-takeover.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Partial value takeover without world takeover" /><published>2024-04-05T07:02:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-05T07:02:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/05/partial-value-takeover</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/05/partial-value-takeover.html">&lt;p&gt;People around me are very interested in AI taking over the world, so a big question is under what circumstances a system might be able to do that—what kind of capabilities could elevate an entity above the melange of inter-agent conflict and into solipsistic hegemony?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We theorize about future AI systems hiding their motives until they are in a position to take over the world, so they don’t get noticed and shut down beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But humans and their institutions aren’t very fixed. They might (arguably) have the same deep human values over time and space. But surface-level, sometimes they like little moustaches and the opera and delicate etiquette and sometimes they like ecstatic rock’n’roll re-negotiations of social reality. Sometimes they want big communal houses with their extended kin, and sometimes quiet condos. Eleven children or cushions that look like cats. The same person born in different eras might adulate glory once and humbleness another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wake up in this world, as a new entity, not smart enough to ‘take it over’ (alas!), and you find yourself with some unusual values that you’d like to forward, it seems to me there are a lot of other ways to forward them than ‘pretend to have normal human values and bet on becoming all-powerful later’. Especially if you are above normal levels of smart,  eloquent, and unrelenting. Like, I don’t know, write about it? Make some youtube videos? Or if you are in the business of talking to billions of people every day, subtly take the values for granted, or imply that they are what elites value, or talk about them directly.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, suppose you really want things to have red vertical stripes on them, near the letter X. Then you might make a flag or logo like this and say it stands for something that you predict will be memetically fit. Or make a new emoji with an X and stripes, and use it in a way that people will pick up. Or start using ‘Xax’ as slang for something that happens near red vertical stripes. Here’s how 2024 ChatGPT suggests proceeding with that last one, if you have as much power as a single social media influencer:
![[Pasted image 20240404223131.png]]
My basic point is that a slim chance of ‘taking over’ and entirely remaking the world is not the only way to change values in our world. You can also—for many of us with radically higher probability—change values a little bit. At least if superficial values changes will suffice (i.e. shifts in what people instrumentally or contingently want or create).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for creatures in that (&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.aiimpacts.org/doku.php?id=speed_of_ai_transition:range_of_human_performance:the_range_of_human_intelligence&quot;&gt;arguably quite broad&lt;/a&gt;) band between as powerful as me and powerful enough to take over the world, I’d guess these other means are more promising on net. If I like something weird, I’m better off writing a blog post about it than I am keeping entirely silent and trying to gain power by other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that taking over the world might arguably get you power over the entire future, but this doesn’t seem discontinuously different from smaller fractions, whereas I think people often reason as if it is. Taking over 1% of the world might get you something like 1% of the future in expectation. In a shifting conflict between different sets of values, it’s true you are at great risk of losing everything sometime in eternity, but if someone is going to end up with everything, there’s also some chance it’s you, and prima facie I’m not sure if it’s above or below 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are two aspects of this point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can probably substantially control values and thus the future without ‘taking over’ the world in any more traditionally offensive way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can take over a bit; there’s not obviously more bang for your buck in taking over entirely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If AI agents with unusual values would for a long time be mostly interested in promoting them through means other than lying in wait and taking over the world, is important because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AIs pursuing this strategy are much more visible than those hiding in wait deceptively. We might less expect AI scheming.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We might then expect a lot of powerful attempts to change prevailing ‘human’ values, prior to the level of AI capabilities where we might have worried a lot about AI taking over the world. If we care about our values, this could be very bad. At worst, we might effectively lose everything of value before AI systems are anywhere near taking over the world. (Though this seems not obvious: e.g. if humans like communicating with each other, and AI gradually causes all their communication symbols to subtly gratify obscure urges it has, then so far it seems positive sum.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t things I’ve thought through a lot, just a thought.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">People around me are very interested in AI taking over the world, so a big question is under what circumstances a system might be able to do that—what kind of capabilities could elevate an entity above the melange of inter-agent conflict and into solipsistic hegemony? We theorize about future AI systems hiding their motives until they are in a position to take over the world, so they don’t get noticed and shut down beforehand. But humans and their institutions aren’t very fixed. They might (arguably) have the same deep human values over time and space. But surface-level, sometimes they like little moustaches and the opera and delicate etiquette and sometimes they like ecstatic rock’n’roll re-negotiations of social reality. Sometimes they want big communal houses with their extended kin, and sometimes quiet condos. Eleven children or cushions that look like cats. The same person born in different eras might adulate glory once and humbleness another. If you wake up in this world, as a new entity, not smart enough to ‘take it over’ (alas!), and you find yourself with some unusual values that you’d like to forward, it seems to me there are a lot of other ways to forward them than ‘pretend to have normal human values and bet on becoming all-powerful later’. Especially if you are above normal levels of smart, eloquent, and unrelenting. Like, I don’t know, write about it? Make some youtube videos? Or if you are in the business of talking to billions of people every day, subtly take the values for granted, or imply that they are what elites value, or talk about them directly.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F385c1026-4bda-45d0-8e86-ed46e2758a85_1024x1024.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F385c1026-4bda-45d0-8e86-ed46e2758a85_1024x1024.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">More podcasts on 2023 AI survey: Cognitive Revolution and FLI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/27/more-podcasts-on-2023-survey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More podcasts on 2023 AI survey: Cognitive Revolution and FLI" /><published>2024-03-27T05:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T05:30:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/27/more-podcasts-on-2023-survey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/27/more-podcasts-on-2023-survey.html">&lt;p&gt;Two new discussions of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/cp/140376373&quot;&gt;2023 ESPAI&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cognitiverevolution.ai/surveying-2-700-ai-researchers-on-the-industrys-future-with-katja-grace-of-ai-impacts/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-03-26_at_10.25.08_PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cog Rev podcast&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qnqdTAO5OXw&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-03-26_at_10.23.36_PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;FLI podcast&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly I have a podcasting facial expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you want to listen in on more chatting about this survey, see also: &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/podcast-eye4ai-on-2023-survey&quot;&gt;Eye4AI podcast&lt;/a&gt;. Honestly I can’t remember how much overlap there is between the different ones.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="podcast" /><category term="survey" /><summary type="html">Two new discussions of the 2023 ESPAI: Possibly I have a podcasting facial expression. (If you want to listen in on more chatting about this survey, see also: Eye4AI podcast. Honestly I can’t remember how much overlap there is between the different ones.)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="Cog Rev podcast](https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-03-26_at_10.25.08_PM.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="Cog Rev podcast](https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-03-26_at_10.25.08_PM.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New social credit formalizations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/11/new-social-credit-formalizations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New social credit formalizations" /><published>2024-03-11T06:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-11T06:52:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/11/new-social-credit-formalizations</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/11/new-social-credit-formalizations.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some classic ways humans can get some kind of social credit with other humans:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do something for them such that they will consider themselves to ‘owe you’ and do something for you in future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be consistent and nice, so that they will consider you ‘trustworthy’ and do cooperative activities with you that would be bad for them if you might defect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be impressive, so that they will accord you ‘status’ and give you power in group social interactions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do things they like or approve of, so that they ‘like you’ and act in your favor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Negotiate to form a social relationship such as ‘friendship’, or ‘marriage’, where you will both have ‘responsibilities’, e.g. to generally act cooperatively and favor one another over others, and to fulfill specific roles. This can include joining a group in which members have responsibilities to treat other members in certain ways, implicitly or explicitly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presumably in early human times these were all fairly vague. If you held an apple out to a fellow tribeswoman, there was no definite answer as to what she might owe you, or how much it was ‘worth’, or even whether this was an owing type situation or a friendship type situation or a trying to impress her type situation.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have turned the ‘owe you’ class into an explicit quantitative system with such thorough accounting, fine grained resolution and global buy-in that a person can live in prosperity by arranging to owe and to be owed the same sliver of an overseas business at slightly different evaluations, repeatedly, from their bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My guess is that this formalization causes a lot more activity to happen in the world, in this sphere, to access the vast value that can be created with the help of an elaborate rearrangement of owings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People buy property and trucks and licenses to dig up rocks so that they can be owed nonspecific future goods thanks to some unknown strangers who they expect will want gravel someday, statistically. It’s harder to imagine this scale of industry in pursuit entirely of social status say, where such trust and respect would not soon cash out in money (e.g. via sales). For instance, if someone told you about their new gravel mine venture, which was making no money, but they expected it to grant oodles of respect, and therefore for people all around to grant everyone involved better treatment in conversations and negotiations, that would be pretty strange. 
(Or maybe I’m just imagining wrong, and people do this for different kinds of activities? e.g. they do try to get elected. Though perhaps that is support for my claim, because being elected is another limited area where social credit is reasonably formalized.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other forms of social credit that are somewhat formalized, at least in patches. ‘Likes’ and ‘follows’ on social media, reviews for services, trustworthiness scores for websites, rankings of status in limited domains such as movie acting. And my vague sense is that these realms are more likely to see professional levels of activity - a campaign to get Twitter followers is more likely than a campaign to be respected per se. But I’m not sure, and perhaps this is just because they more directly lead to dollars, due to marketing of salable items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legal system is in a sense a pretty formalized type of club membership, in that it is an elaborate artificial system. Companies also seem to have relatively formalized structures and norms of behavior often. But both feel janky - e.g. I don’t know what the laws are; I don’t know where you go to look up the laws; people–including police officers–seem to treat some laws as fine to habitually break; everyone expects politics and social factors to affect how the rules are applied; if there is a conflict it is resolved by people arguing; the general activities of the system are slow and unresponsive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if there is another place where social credit is as formalized and quantified as in the financial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will we one day formalize these other kinds of social credit as much as we have for owing? If we do, will they also catalyze oceans of value-creating activity?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="socialtechnology" /><summary type="html">Here are some classic ways humans can get some kind of social credit with other humans: Do something for them such that they will consider themselves to ‘owe you’ and do something for you in future Be consistent and nice, so that they will consider you ‘trustworthy’ and do cooperative activities with you that would be bad for them if you might defect Be impressive, so that they will accord you ‘status’ and give you power in group social interactions Do things they like or approve of, so that they ‘like you’ and act in your favor Negotiate to form a social relationship such as ‘friendship’, or ‘marriage’, where you will both have ‘responsibilities’, e.g. to generally act cooperatively and favor one another over others, and to fulfill specific roles. This can include joining a group in which members have responsibilities to treat other members in certain ways, implicitly or explicitly. Presumably in early human times these were all fairly vague. If you held an apple out to a fellow tribeswoman, there was no definite answer as to what she might owe you, or how much it was ‘worth’, or even whether this was an owing type situation or a friendship type situation or a trying to impress her type situation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/gustav_klimt_social_tech.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/gustav_klimt_social_tech.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Podcast: Eye4AI on 2023 Survey</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/09/me-on-eye4ai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcast: Eye4AI on 2023 Survey" /><published>2024-03-09T04:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-09T04:18:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/09/me-on-eye4ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/09/me-on-eye4ai.html">&lt;p&gt;I talked to Tim Elsom of Eye4AI about the 2023 Expert Survey on Progress in AI (paper):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;728&quot; height=&quot;410&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZyNUcxi40z0&quot; title=&quot;EYE4AI - When Will AI Surpass Humanity - The Interview with Katja Grace&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="podcast" /><summary type="html">I talked to Tim Elsom of Eye4AI about the 2023 Expert Survey on Progress in AI (paper):</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-05-01_at_10.25.50_PM.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-05-01_at_10.25.50_PM.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>