<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-07T02:55:47-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Evening drawing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/evening-drawing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evening drawing" /><published>2021-01-07T01:37:14-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T01:37:14-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/evening-drawing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/evening-drawing.html">&lt;p&gt;This evening I became tempted by a YouTube video of an artist painting a portrait, which led me to be tempted by another such video, and then more of them, and then by one of these artists’ websites, and then by my own pencils and paper. (I did not become tempted by YouTube videos advertising breaking news of some sort of crazy Trump riot, since I decided not to ‘check the internet’ until bed time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some observations on drawing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In my world, art supplies are a kind of archetype of a thing that is viscerally exciting vastly beyond its likelihood of being used (and even further beyond its likelihood of being used well). Like, look at this paper I got! (I did, extensively.) Think of the potential it holds! But actually, for now, it’s sitting under my bed. &lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20201107_055554319.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Colored paper&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is sometimes very hard to draw without poking my tongue out. Not in the sense that that without my tongue out, drawing is hard—I mean, while drawing, it seems infeasible to keep my tongue in my mouth. This feels natural and unsurprising, like how if you stand on one leg it is hard to not fall over, not like an epileptic seizure overcoming my tongue. But stated explicitly, it is pretty weird.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is also frequently very hard to draw without tilting my head from side to side. I first noticed this in high school art class, where I sat drawing and listening to the other students talk. One of them pointed out to another that looking around the room, students were tilting their heads to and fro all over the place. I also overheard an eye-opening discussion of how awesome it was that we were going to war in Iraq imminently, since that might clear space in the ranks of military helicopter pilots, allowing the excited student to fill it. Drawing and overhearing seem like good complementary activities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s hard to really get behind my attempts to draw well, because it doesn’t feel like they are leading anywhere. I would be more into it if it was part of a compelling plan to save the world. Perhaps I don’t really believe in leisure enough to wholeheartedly do it, and don’t disbelieve in it enough to work all of the time. Alas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even without the world perhaps needing saving, drawing feels a bit pointless, since we have photography. But this doesn’t make sense: if you want to create an image of a scene, much better to draw it than to have to create it in real life then photograph it. For instance, most of the time, the scene you want probably isn’t realistic in the sense that it looks exactly like some bit of reality. How about computer graphics then? Yes, but even if arbitrary styles of image could be computer generated, doing this is itself basically just another kind of drawing—you still have to understand what patterns on the page would produce what in the minds of viewers, and you still have to invent ideas worth sending to the minds of viewers. It’s just the interface for putting down colors and shapes is different. That said, usually I just draw people, who might be better photographed, so it’s unclear that these thoughts apply. I feel like there are other good things about it that I haven’t captured. For instance, there are lots of great paintings just attempting to capture what is in front of them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I feel like I learn to draw faces better over the years via taking in insights about what they look like. For instance, ‘there is that little dip above the lip that you can fill with shadow’, or ‘eyes go half way down’, or the very early, ‘mustaches go &lt;em&gt;under&lt;/em&gt; noses, not on top of them’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I basically can’t imagine faces, at least to anywhere near the degree of realism with which I can draw them (checking this now, I’m struggling to imagine a generic smiley face, though arguably succeeding). It’s interesting to me that a person can draw what they can’t imagine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have the intuition that you can learn to draw more easily by looking at someone else’s drawing than you can by looking at a photograph of its subject. I decided to test this, and drew three people—one from a painting, one from a photograph, and one from my head. Can you guess which is which? (If so, how?)
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210107_091952457.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing of a woman's face 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210107_090812677.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing of a woman's face 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210107_091859225.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing of a woman's face 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="journal" /><category term="mundane" /><category term="art" /><summary type="html">This evening I became tempted by a YouTube video of an artist painting a portrait, which led me to be tempted by another such video, and then more of them, and then by one of these artists’ websites, and then by my own pencils and paper. (I did not become tempted by YouTube videos advertising breaking news of some sort of crazy Trump riot, since I decided not to ‘check the internet’ until bed time).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210107_091859225.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210107_091859225.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Centrally planned war</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/06/centrally-planned-war.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Centrally planned war" /><published>2021-01-06T01:30:40-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-06T01:30:40-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/06/centrally-planned-war</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/06/centrally-planned-war.html">&lt;p&gt;We watched &lt;em&gt;Dunkirk&lt;/em&gt;, and wondered how many military deaths are for reasons more of logistics than of facing the enemy. Probably lots - we have heard that war is made of colossal logistical feats, so probably they often fail, and often lives depend on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Imagine organizing a party with hundreds of thousands of people at it. Imagine that is located in an overseas country, where you don’t have a house, and everyone hates you. Imagine that it goes for several years. Imagine it is a very stressful party for the partygoers, but also you are counting on them to carry out some hard and terrifying tasks for you during the party. Imagine you anticipate many deaths during the proceedings.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which made me wonder, why is war so centrally planned? Why wouldn’t all these logistical details be simpler and cheaper in the usual ways if each soldier looked after himself mostly? Similar to how it works better for each person to look after themselves during peacetime, rather than having commanders organize and dictate the whole peaceful existence effort.  Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="war" /><category term="sociology" /><summary type="html">We watched Dunkirk, and wondered how many military deaths are for reasons more of logistics than of facing the enemy. Probably lots - we have heard that war is made of colossal logistical feats, so probably they often fail, and often lives depend on them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intended enjoyment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/intended-enjoyments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intended enjoyment" /><published>2021-01-05T01:10:49-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-05T01:10:49-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/intended-enjoyments</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/intended-enjoyments.html">&lt;p&gt;I am sometimes unsure what is meant to be enjoyed in things, for instance the short story &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2021/01/04/giaconda-smile.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gioconda Smile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;In the mood for love&lt;/em&gt; which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/film/2019/sep/13/100-best-films-movies-of-the-21st-century&quot;&gt;people&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_films_considered_the_best&quot;&gt;often&lt;/a&gt; enjoy a lot. Which seems like it shouldn’t be a problem, as long as I find something to enjoy in them. But it also seems like I would be seriously missing something if I was buying bags of coffee all these years just to appreciate the thick, substantive quality of the paper bag between my teeth as I chewed it. How many of my enjoyments are like this?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="life-strategy" /><category term="culture" /><summary type="html">I am sometimes unsure what is meant to be enjoyed in things, for instance the short story The Gioconda Smile, or In the mood for love which people often enjoy a lot. Which seems like it shouldn’t be a problem, as long as I find something to enjoy in them. But it also seems like I would be seriously missing something if I was buying bags of coffee all these years just to appreciate the thick, substantive quality of the paper bag between my teeth as I chewed it. How many of my enjoyments are like this?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review: The Gioconda Smile</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/03/giaconda-smile.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: The Gioconda Smile" /><published>2021-01-03T21:56:05-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-03T21:56:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/03/giaconda-smile</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/03/giaconda-smile.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Spoiler alert: discusses entire plot of The Gioconda Smile by Aldous Huxley)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading short stories lately, which are often confusing to me, and I frequently wish that the author resolved the actual tension and relieved my actual curiosity more, by including some sort of short note at the end on what they were even trying to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that said, I read Aldous Huxley’s &lt;em&gt;The Gioconda Smile&lt;/em&gt;, and was somewhat confused by it. I mean, it was a story. But since I got it from ‘50 Great Short Stories…a comprehensive selection from the world’s finest short fiction’, I’m expecting it to be somehow surpassingly great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protagonist is a relatively uncaring womanizer, who we first meet making a friendly visit to one woman while another waits in his car, to be dropped off before he gets home to his wife, who he finds disgusting in her aged ill-health. He seems to be largely driven by avoiding boredom and upholding an image of himself as a sophisticated and charming stud. He knows that his tendency to feel loathing in the place of pity toward the unfortunate in general is not ‘comely’, but has abandoned feeling shame about this unfortunate fact of his nature. When his wife dies, he immediately marries his young mistress, on an apparently humor-fueled whim and with little regard for her. He is ever detached, lightheartedly throwing back strategic retorts to questions sent his way, never actually with another person in spirit. He seems intelligent and reasonable aside from being callous to the point of ridiculous imprudence. For instance, if you marry a woman as a ‘practical joke’, this might predictably cause inconvenience to your own life at some point, even if you are dedicatedly indifferent to her welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact the biggest thing that goes wrong is that the intriguing woman he visits but doesn’t dally with—she with the mysterious Gioconda (Mona Lisa) smile—falls in love with him, surreptitiously murders his wife, attempts too late to claim him, then frames him for the murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is this good to read? What would one come to this for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is probably a memorable story, but why is it worth remembering? Has it added anything rich to my life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it perhaps a moralizing story? The protagonist is gratuitously awful, which is some hint. One way it could be this is as a tale of his errors coming back to get him, where by emptily seducing every woman around, he was carelessly pitching powerful passions against one another, and somebody was bound to be crazy enough to do something terrible (his second wife also tries to kill herself, upon realizing that her husband doesn’t love her). But why write that? For people who would feel no moral compunctions about the guy’s behavior in general but may not have considered the pragmatic consequences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way it might be a moral story is that his own joyful amusements are cut short by another’s incredible selfish callousness, which serves him right for his own years of incredible selfish callousness? I don’t know, this doesn’t seem like a very interesting moral saga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it is meant as an interesting, amoral, portrait of a callous but smiling man, coldly charming women as he goes on with his empty existence, until the wake of his own heartlessness flips his boat? I didn’t come away with a vivid sense of his character, but perhaps I wasn’t paying enough attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title suggests that it is actually a portrait of the enigmatically smiling woman in the background, though she is an infrequent character. The protagonist imagines her as having mysterious depths to her personality in a way that his straightforward wife and lover do not, but again I didn’t end up with a well-formed sense of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s for the murder mystery plot? The real murderer wasn’t revealed until the end, but as soon as it became clear that the wife was murdered, it seemed pretty obvious who had done it. For instance, if you assume that it wasn’t the husband (since that would conflict with the narration of his confused perspective) then the other visitor at the time of the poisoning was ol’ Gioconda smile. I guess it could have been an unnamed servant. The protagonist still seems confused about who the murderer could be at this point though, which is a bit strange if the author agrees that it is obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the point is to try to guess the murderer before it comes out that it was a murder? There were clues. For instance, Gioconda was like ‘your wife seems very sick, she could die any time’ and then the wife dies a few hours later. Then when the husband later goes to see Gioconda, she is like, ‘I’m impressed by how you put up with your wife for so long, but I saw that you weren’t really into it, and actually you needed a soul mate; also I love you’. But it seems like you would only guess that this is a murder mystery at that point if your mind happened upon the thought that this is all suspicious, at which point you have also solved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has some insightful observation of psychology. For instance, the protagonist reflecting on Gioconda’s decorations while waiting for her, illuminating both her psychology and his own:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Photographs of Greek statuary, photographs of the Roman Forum, coloured prints of Italian masterpieces, all very safe and well known. Poor, dear Janet, what a prig—what an intellectual snob! Her real taste was illustrated in that water-colour by the pavement artist, the one she had paid half a crown for (and thirty-five shillings for the frame). How often his had heard her tell the story, how often expatiate on the beauties of that skilful imitation of an oleograph! “A real Artist in the streets,” and you could hear the capital A in Artist as she spoke the words. She made you feel that part of his glory had entered into Janet Spence when she tendered him that half-crown for the copy of the oleograph. She was implying a compliment to her own taste and penetration. A genuine Old Master for half a crown. Poor, dear Janet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems richer to me. But The Gioconda Smile was made into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Woman%27s_Vengeance&quot;&gt;multiple&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Gioconda_Smile_(film)&quot;&gt;films&lt;/a&gt;, which seems surprising if the value is in the unspoken thoughts of characters or manner of description, since these are hard to translate into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems likely that I’m missing something.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="review" /><category term="book" /><summary type="html">(Spoiler alert: discusses entire plot of The Gioconda Smile by Aldous Huxley)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On writing like a butterfly</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/02/on-writing-like-a-butterfly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On writing like a butterfly" /><published>2021-01-02T11:06:55-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-02T11:06:55-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/02/on-writing-like-a-butterfly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/02/on-writing-like-a-butterfly.html">&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be interesting to try to write my &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2021/01/01/review-the-diving-bell-and-the-butterfly.html&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Diving_Bell_and_the_Butterfly&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the Diving Bell and the Butterfly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in my head without setting pen to paper until the end, and to convey at least some of it by blinking, since I find the fact that the author wrote the whole book in this way astonishing. Perhaps experiencing that process myself would improve my understanding of things, such that I wouldn’t be astonished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think trying to do this was an even better exercise than I expected, though by the end I was frustrated to the point of tears, and I’m still feeling kind of annoyed, having just put it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Hopefully this was also a vivid and enlightening experience of signing up for annoying projects, which I do often, but usually the annoyance is months later than the agreeing, so I’m not sure that my intuitive anticipations make the connection.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I go and do something anti-annoying, I figure I should write some notes on the experience, while it is fresh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It did feel fairly encumbering. There were nascent sentences that I might have tried to poke in somewhere, then play around with, then look at and move or get rid of, where the prospect of trying to do some equivalent of all that in my head while keeping hold of the broader paragraph was too intimidating, and I watched them go by. And the sentences I did write felt like half my attention was on something like balancing them on the end of a stick and not having them fall on the floor, and really sculpting them would have required too much dexterity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Though I think in some sense they were much more sculpted than usual, because I did think about each one for longer, and often hone it into something more succinct and memorable instead of writing down the first ramble that entered my mind. I’m not sure how that fits with the above observation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It felt mentally strength-building - as if I was exercising a capability that would improve, which was exciting, and I briefly fantasized about a stronger and defter inner world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I started out looking at things around me as I composed, like my resting computer, and the table, and the sea. But after a while, I realized that I was staring intently at a long rug with about as many Persian whorls as paragraphs in my prospective post, and that as I envisaged the current sentence, I was mentally weaving it around some well-placed sub-curls of its paragraph-whorl. Looking away from it, it was harder to remember what I had been saying. (I have noticed before that thinking in the world, I end up appropriating the scenery as some kind of scratch paper - you can’t write on it, but you can actually do a lot with reinterpreting whatever it already contains.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For words with lots of synonyms, I kept selecting one, then forgetting which and having to select again (e.g. ‘lively’ or ‘energetic’ or ‘vigorous’?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I originally set out to compose the whole thing before writing it, but this was fairly hard and seemed somewhat arbitrary, so after composing the basic outline and a few paragraphs, somewhat discouraged by the likelihood of forgetting them again imminently, I decided that I could instead compose chunks at a time rather than having to do it all at once. In the end I did it in paragraph chunks. Which is probably a much easier task than Bauby had, since if someone was coming to transcribe stuff for hours, one probably wants more than one paragraph relatively well prepared.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking lots of thoughts without saying or writing them can feel a particular kind of agitating.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It took about 20 minutes for my boyfriend and I to transcribe a single sentence using roughly the winking method described in the book, for a speed of around 1 word per minute. The scheme was for him to run his finger over an alphabet reorganized by letter frequency, then for me to wink when he reached the desired letter. We added some punctuation, and a ‘pause! let me think!’ signal, and ‘yes’, and ‘no’. These last three got a lot of use. It basically worked as expected, though one time we made an error, and I didn’t know what to do, so I continued from the beginning of the word again, which made the sentence nonsensical, which confused him for a while, but he figured it out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wondered why Bauby and his assistant didn’t use Morse code, or something more efficient. We didn’t try this, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.early-retirement.org/forums/f38/locked-in-syndrome-and-morse-code-61544.html&quot;&gt;some forum users also wonder this&lt;/a&gt;, and one claims that he can wink out about 20 words per minute in Morse code, but that the large amount of blinking involved is ‘pretty tiring’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We made a huge amount of use of my boyfriend guessing the rest of the word, from context and the first few letters. In the book, Bauby describes how people frequently mess that up, or fail to check that they have guessed correctly, or refuse to guess and conscientiously coax forth every letter. This all sounds terrible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m aware that some people probably compose things entirely in their heads all the time (people have all kinds of mental situations - some people can also reliably imagine a triangle without it being more like the feeling of a triangle laid out in a kind of triangle-like space, or breaking apart and becoming a volcano full of red and white flowers), and my notes here probably sound to them like a person saying ‘for a bizarro experience, I tried to walk across the room without holding on to things, but it was obviously a total disaster - knees bending every which way, and imagine balancing a whole floppy and joint-strewn human body on top of two of those things, while moving! Such sympathy I have for those who have lost their walking frames.’ I’m curious to hear from them whether this is what it sounds like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I thought it would be interesting to try to write my review of the Diving Bell and the Butterfly in my head without setting pen to paper until the end, and to convey at least some of it by blinking, since I find the fact that the author wrote the whole book in this way astonishing. Perhaps experiencing that process myself would improve my understanding of things, such that I wouldn’t be astonished.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review: The Diving Bell and the Butterfly</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/01/review-the-diving-bell-and-the-butterfly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: The Diving Bell and the Butterfly" /><published>2021-01-01T04:21:59-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-01T04:21:59-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/01/review-the-diving-bell-and-the-butterfly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/01/review-the-diving-bell-and-the-butterfly.html">&lt;p&gt;I suspect my mind of taking its observations of a person’s physical energy and dexterity as strong evidence about their mental quickness and clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence and the wrongness of this presumption were brought into relief for me by reading Jean-Dominique Bauby’s &lt;em&gt;The Diving Bell and the Butterfly&lt;/em&gt;, on his life with locked-in syndrome. Because realizing that the author’s lively and intelligent voice was issued from a single blinking eye looking out of a mostly inert body felt like seeing a magic trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps it is just that a writing process without vigorous back-and-forth with a mind-expanding piece of paper or virtual paper—a place to lay out one’s words and see them and move them around, without having to keep the entire gameboard in one’s head—sounds mentally paralyzing to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I realize that in all likelihood it is my own mind that is weak and wasted from clinging to these crutches, and that has learned to fear starting out by itself with no piece of paper to reassuringly catch its thoughts and promise that nothing will be forgotten. Bauby’s mind may well have become stronger between his time as eloquent editor of French &lt;em&gt;Elle&lt;/em&gt; and writing this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It probably isn’t the feat of its creation though that makes this enjoyable to read, or makes my mind keep coming back to it. It’s a bright and compelling window into another person’s mind. (The bizarre tragedy of the plot probably doesn’t hurt either.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I found interesting about the book was that the setting of being immobile in a hospital bed doesn’t give the reader many of the clues they might usually use to make out the character of the protagonist. How does he hold himself, when he can hold himself? How does he talk to his partner, when he can do more than blink? What did he want in life, before the goalposts were changed and, as he says, not drooling all the time became a cherished ambition? (We do learn that he is 44 years old, and that if he is going to drool, he would prefer to drool on cashmere.) Yet, I did not have a sense of blankness about his personality. From his narration of the world, I felt that I knew him. However toward the end, he narrates the final day before the stroke that detached his mind and his body mostly. And I realize that if I had met him in that way first, I would have a different impression of him. And I liked the way around that I did meet him. So I wonder, if it would be better to more often meet people’s trains of thought for a while before getting to see their appearance or overt behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I composed each paragraph of this post in my head except about fifteen words of editing, and dictated the first line to my boyfriend via winking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="review" /><category term="book" /><summary type="html">I suspect my mind of taking its observations of a person’s physical energy and dexterity as strong evidence about their mental quickness and clarity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/aaron-burden-B3ZWL4FuKdo-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/aaron-burden-B3ZWL4FuKdo-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mistakes to want</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/mistakes-to-want.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mistakes to want" /><published>2020-12-31T19:01:22-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T19:01:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/mistakes-to-want</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/mistakes-to-want.html">&lt;p&gt;The end of the year is a classic time for reflecting on the year. And a classic part of reflecting is noticing mistakes you have made. I admit that I don’t relish this: having made mistakes, admitting to them, and looking at them further all pain me, and I find it hard to call things mistakes. It’s because to make a mistake would seem to be to make the world worse than it could have been, and thus to indelibly reduce the total goodness of the universe at the end of time, which feels like a big deal and the worst (only?) evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly others don’t have the same mental hangups around such things as I do, or have thought clearly about this earlier, but just in case not, I’ll spell out how it actually isn’t bad at all, even in these terms (or at least offer some somewhat scattered thoughts on the matter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us distinguish between two kinds of mistakes: ‘innocent mistakes’ and ‘evil mistakes’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you made a mistake. Was it a mistake given what you knew and understood at the time? Then that’s an ‘evil mistake’. For instance, if you think kicking dogs is worse than not kicking them, and you kick one anyway to experience what badness feels like. (It sounds kind of strange to call it a mistake, since it was what you intended, but whatever.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your mistake was not an error given your understanding the time, then it’s an ‘innocent mistake’. For instance, if you made an unsuccessful choice about what projects to do, or if you hurt your brother’s feelings because it hasn’t occurred to you that he would be sensitive about his appearance. It is tempting to say that an innocent mistake wasn’t a mistake in the relevant sense. You couldn’t have really done better in your &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/12/28/infinite-possibilities.html&quot;&gt;actual circumstances&lt;/a&gt; of limited knowledge and limited thought, at least not predictably. Your conscience should be clear, at least. You did the best you could, so you do not seem to deserve blame or regret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet if blame and regret are for teaching people, then it seems you should have them, at least if they are the ways for you to notice or feel your mistake. For instance, perhaps your sister should say ‘you were so mean to Bob!’ or you should find your thoughts sadly dwelling on your choice of projects. On the other hand, there is not much point blaming the evil mistake-doer, unless your blame hurts them in a way that might put them off selfishly in the future, supposing that they haven’t come around. Just pointing out that they were bad is no news to them. Regret might help them more, but it’s a bit unclear how, since by the time they are regretting their evil, it seems they have already changed their mind about whether they prefer evil. In sum, blame, regret and genuine moral wrongness seem to come apart: blame and regret are often helpful for the innocent mistake-maker, and less so for the evil mistake-maker, while it is the evil mistake-maker who is a genuine moral failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different way of putting this is that the notion of innocence put forward here is a bit different from the normal one - for instance, if you were thoughtless because you were young and hadn’t thought about not being thoughtless yet, and implicitly didn’t think being thoughtful was worth it, and you hurt someone, then you are innocent in the current sense, but quite possibly a guilty asshole in more common senses. We all agree that you should have the error of your ways pointed out to you, but I’m claiming that you shouldn’t take this as your having genuinely made the world worse than you might have, or feel that it is a true negative mark in some moral ledger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only innocent mistakes are helpful for learning. And only evil mistakes represent having genuinely made the world worse when you could (in the relevant sense) have made it better. So looking back on the year, one can hope without terror to see many innocent mistakes, and no evil mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="life-strategy" /><category term="ethics" /><summary type="html">The end of the year is a classic time for reflecting on the year. And a classic part of reflecting is noticing mistakes you have made. I admit that I don’t relish this: having made mistakes, admitting to them, and looking at them further all pain me, and I find it hard to call things mistakes. It’s because to make a mistake would seem to be to make the world worse than it could have been, and thus to indelibly reduce the total goodness of the universe at the end of time, which feels like a big deal and the worst (only?) evil.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seeing the edge of the world</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/30/the-edge-of-the-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seeing the edge of the world" /><published>2020-12-30T18:26:41-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T18:26:41-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/30/the-edge-of-the-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/30/the-edge-of-the-world.html">&lt;p&gt;A nice thing about looking at the ocean that I noticed today is that it is unusually easy to interpret the view as a close up of the edge of a giant wet ball of rock in space, and thus to more compellingly visualize the fact that I live on one of those, and some of all that that entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pacific Ocean where I am got dark, so here’s the Norwegian Sea 2.5 years ago to illustrate:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/IMG_20180610_234802.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Norwegian sea, probably&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="mental-strategy" /><category term="imaginative-aids" /><summary type="html">A nice thing about looking at the ocean that I noticed today is that it is unusually easy to interpret the view as a close up of the edge of a giant wet ball of rock in space, and thus to more compellingly visualize the fact that I live on one of those, and some of all that that entails.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Desires as film posters</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/29/film-posters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Desires as film posters" /><published>2020-12-29T15:25:29-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T15:25:29-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/29/film-posters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/29/film-posters.html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I like to think of desires as like film posters. You come across them, and they urge you to do something, and present it in a certain way, and induce some inclination to do it. But film posters are totally different from films. If you like a film poster, you don’t have to try to see the film. There is no metaphysical connection between the beauty of a film poster and the correctness of you seeing the film. It’s some evidence, but you have other evidence, and you get to choose. A film poster can be genuinely the most beautiful film poster you’ve ever seen, without the film being a worthwhile use of two hours. That’s largely an orthogonal question. If you put up the poster on your wall and look at it lovingly every day, and never see the film, that doesn’t need to be disappointing—it might be the best choice, and you might be satisfied in choosing it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="mind-strategy" /><summary type="html">Sometimes I like to think of desires as like film posters. You come across them, and they urge you to do something, and present it in a certain way, and induce some inclination to do it. But film posters are totally different from films. If you like a film poster, you don’t have to try to see the film. There is no metaphysical connection between the beauty of a film poster and the correctness of you seeing the film. It’s some evidence, but you have other evidence, and you get to choose. A film poster can be genuinely the most beautiful film poster you’ve ever seen, without the film being a worthwhile use of two hours. That’s largely an orthogonal question. If you put up the poster on your wall and look at it lovingly every day, and never see the film, that doesn’t need to be disappointing—it might be the best choice, and you might be satisfied in choosing it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Measuring up to incredible potential</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/28/measuring-up-to-incredible-potential.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Measuring up to incredible potential" /><published>2020-12-28T10:41:13-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T10:41:13-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/28/measuring-up-to-incredible-potential</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/28/measuring-up-to-incredible-potential.html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/2020/12/28/infinite-possibilities.html&quot;&gt;I wrote&lt;/a&gt; that people often talk as if events are basically determined by people’s values and capabilities, ignoring the difficulty of figuring out which opportunities to take, or even noticing opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think one reason to have a better model is that this one doesn’t account for a substantial category of felt difficulty in being a human, possibly encouraging a general sense that one is ubiquitously failing, what with not seeming to be demonstrably grabbing the best of a vast multitude of possible options at each moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own experience for instance involves often not remembering even the options that I noticed before, and these not seeming that multitudinous, except relative to my pitiful capacity to hold things in my mind. Also, regularly noticing new aspects of the world suggestive of many options whose existence hadn’t even dawned on me previously, even though they would be pretty obvious to a creature for whom logic was free. And mostly being extremely uncertain about what actions will lead to what outcomes. If I habitually model myself as roughly &lt;em&gt;homo economicus&lt;/em&gt;, deftly directing my resources toward my goals, at worst according to my pristine priors, it seems like I am in danger of continually finding my real self incredibly disappointing. Plus, abstracting away parts of the situation that might be rich with potential for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="psychology" /><category term="economics" /><category term="life-strategy" /><summary type="html">Yesterday I wrote that people often talk as if events are basically determined by people’s values and capabilities, ignoring the difficulty of figuring out which opportunities to take, or even noticing opportunities.</summary></entry></feed>