<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-23T14:37:41+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">Podcasts: AGI Show, Consistently Candid, London Futurists</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/23/podcasts-agi-show-consistently-candid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcasts: AGI Show, Consistently Candid, London Futurists" /><published>2024-06-23T14:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-23T14:34:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/23/podcasts-agi-show-consistently-candid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/23/podcasts-agi-show-consistently-candid.html">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who enjoy learning things via listening in on numerous slightly different conversations about them, and who also want to learn more about this&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.aiimpacts.org/p/2023-ai-survey-of-2778-six-things&quot;&gt; AI survey&lt;/a&gt; I led, three more podcasts on the topic, and also other topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The AGI Show&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theagishow.com/2082819/15275026-ep-13-ai-researchers-expect-agi-sooner-w-katja-grace-co-founder-lead-researcher-ai-impacts&quot;&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nbpw90WQmgU&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; (other topics include: my own thoughts about the future of AI and my path into AI forecasting)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consistently Candid&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buzzsprout.com/2319950/15286236&quot;&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt; (other topics include: whether we should slow down AI progress, the best arguments for and against existential risk from AI, parsing the online AI safety debate)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;London Futurists&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xwJx_xqZI3Q&quot;&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt; (other topics include: are we in an arms race? Why is my blog called that?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="podcasts" /><summary type="html">For those of you who enjoy learning things via listening in on numerous slightly different conversations about them, and who also want to learn more about this AI survey I led, three more podcasts on the topic, and also other topics: The AGI Show: audio, video (other topics include: my own thoughts about the future of AI and my path into AI forecasting) Consistently Candid: audio (other topics include: whether we should slow down AI progress, the best arguments for and against existential risk from AI, parsing the online AI safety debate) London Futurists: audio (other topics include: are we in an arms race? Why is my blog called that?)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd81a78e9-60a0-47ed-bde4-dc4a83b594c4_2378x1336.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd81a78e9-60a0-47ed-bde4-dc4a83b594c4_2378x1336.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What if a tech company forced you to move to NYC?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/09/what-if-tech-co-nyc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if a tech company forced you to move to NYC?" /><published>2024-06-09T07:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T07:18:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/09/what-if-tech-co-nyc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/09/what-if-tech-co-nyc.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to me how chill people sometimes are about the non-extinction future AI scenarios. Like, there seem to be opinions around along the lines of “pshaw, it might ruin your little sources of ‘meaning’, Luddite, but we have always had change and as long as the machines are pretty near the mark on rewiring your brain it will make everything amazing”. Yet I would bet that even that person, if faced instead with a policy that was going to forcibly relocate them to New York City, would be quite indignant, and want a lot of guarantees about the preservation of various very specific things they care about in life, and not be just like “oh sure, NYC has higher GDP/capita than my current city, sounds good”.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read this as a lack of engaging with the situation as real. But possibly my sense that a non-negligible number of people have this flavor of position is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">It’s interesting to me how chill people sometimes are about the non-extinction future AI scenarios. Like, there seem to be opinions around along the lines of “pshaw, it might ruin your little sources of ‘meaning’, Luddite, but we have always had change and as long as the machines are pretty near the mark on rewiring your brain it will make everything amazing”. Yet I would bet that even that person, if faced instead with a policy that was going to forcibly relocate them to New York City, would be quite indignant, and want a lot of guarantees about the preservation of various very specific things they care about in life, and not be just like “oh sure, NYC has higher GDP/capita than my current city, sounds good”.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F193cfc4c-5e3a-4f7d-908c-af0753f57951_4480x6586.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F193cfc4c-5e3a-4f7d-908c-af0753f57951_4480x6586.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Podcast: Center for AI Policy, on AI risk and listening to AI researchers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/06/caip-podcast.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Podcast: Center for AI Policy, on AI risk and listening to AI researchers" /><published>2024-06-06T04:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-06T04:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/06/caip-podcast</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/06/caip-podcast.html">&lt;p&gt;I was on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aipolicypod.substack.com/p/7-katja-grace-on-the-future-of-ai&quot;&gt;Center for AI Policy Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. We talked about topics around the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.aiimpacts.org/ai_timelines/predictions_of_human-level_ai_timelines/ai_timeline_surveys/2023_expert_survey_on_progress_in_ai&quot;&gt;2023 Expert Survey on Progress in AI&lt;/a&gt;, including why I think AI is an existential risk, and how much to listen to AI researchers on the subject. Full transcript at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aipolicypod.substack.com/p/7-katja-grace-on-the-future-of-ai&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="podcast" /><category term="ai" /><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">I was on the Center for AI Policy Podcast. We talked about topics around the 2023 Expert Survey on Progress in AI, including why I think AI is an existential risk, and how much to listen to AI researchers on the subject. Full transcript at the link.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is suffering like shit?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/31/is-suffering-like-shit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is suffering like shit?" /><published>2024-05-31T02:03:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-31T02:03:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/31/is-suffering-like-shit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/31/is-suffering-like-shit.html">&lt;p&gt;People seem to find suffering deep. Serious writings explore the experiences of all manner of misfortunes, and the nuances of trauma and torment involved. It’s hard to write an essay about a really good holiday that seems as profound as an essay about a really unjust abuse. A dark past can be plumbed for all manner of meaning, whereas a slew of happy years is boring and empty, unless perhaps they are &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; happy and suggest something dark below the surface. (More thoughts in the vicinity of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/home-up-and-down-colder-and-warmer-20-02-20&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if one day suffering will be so avoidable that the myriad hurts of present-day existence will seem to future people like the problem of excrement getting on everything. Presumably a real issue in 1100 AD, but now irrelevant, unrelatable, decidedly not fascinating or in need of deep analysis.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">People seem to find suffering deep. Serious writings explore the experiences of all manner of misfortunes, and the nuances of trauma and torment involved. It’s hard to write an essay about a really good holiday that seems as profound as an essay about a really unjust abuse. A dark past can be plumbed for all manner of meaning, whereas a slew of happy years is boring and empty, unless perhaps they are too happy and suggest something dark below the surface. (More thoughts in the vicinity of this here.) I wonder if one day suffering will be so avoidable that the myriad hurts of present-day existence will seem to future people like the problem of excrement getting on everything. Presumably a real issue in 1100 AD, but now irrelevant, unrelatable, decidedly not fascinating or in need of deep analysis.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/katjagrace_Excrement_in_the_gutters_of_a_street_in_a_European_c_4f3279b4-a13f-4d1b-be56-c2764d34ac36.pngScreen_Shot_2024-05-09_at_10.36.46_PM.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/katjagrace_Excrement_in_the_gutters_of_a_street_in_a_European_c_4f3279b4-a13f-4d1b-be56-c2764d34ac36.pngScreen_Shot_2024-05-09_at_10.36.46_PM.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Twin Peaks: under the air</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/30/twin-peaks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Twin Peaks: under the air" /><published>2024-05-30T07:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-30T07:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/30/twin-peaks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/30/twin-peaks.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content warning: low content&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~ Feb 2021&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day I decided to try imbibing work-relevant blog posts via AI-generated recital, while scaling the Twin Peaks—large hills near my house in San Francisco, of the sort that one lives near and doesn’t get around to going to. It was pretty strange, all around.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, I was wearing sunglasses. I realize this is a thing people do all the time. Maybe it’s strange for them too, or maybe theirs aren’t orange. Mine were, which really changed the situation. For one thing, the glowing streetscapes felt unreal, like cheap science fiction. But also, all kinds of beauty seemed to want photographing, but couldn’t be seen with my camera. It was funny to realize that I’m surrounded by potential beauty all the time, that I would see if I had different eyes, or different glasses, or different sensory organs all together. Like, the potential for beauty is as real as the beauty I do see. (This is perhaps obvious, but something being obvious doesn’t mean you know it. And knowing something doesn’t mean you realize it. I’d say I knew it, but hadn’t realized it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then my ears were cornered in by these plugs spouting electronic declarations on the nature of coherent agents and such, which added to my sense of my head just not really being in the world, and instead being in a cozy little head cockpit, from which I could look out on the glowing alien landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feet were also strange, but in the opposite direction. I recently got these new sock-shoes and I was trying them out for the first time. They are like well-fitting socks with strong but pliable rubber stuff sprayed on the bottom. Wearing them, you can feel the ground under your feet, as if you were bare-foot. Minus the sharp bits actually lacerating your feet, or the squishy bits sullying them. Walking along I imagined my freed feet were extra hands, holding the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had only been up to Twin Peaks twice before, and I guess I had missed somehow exactly how crazy the view was. It was like standing on a giant breast, with a city-sea-bridge-forest-scape panoramaed around and under you over-realistically. The bridge disappeared into mystical mists and the supertankers swam epically on the vast blue expanse. I tried to photograph it multiple times but failed, partly because my camera couldn’t capture the warm orange tinge of the sea and the bridge rising from the burning mists, and partly for whatever reason that things sometimes look very different in photographs, and partly because I am always vaguely embarrassed photographing things with people looking at me, and there was a steady smattering of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roads had been blocked off to traffic during the pandemic. From a car I don’t realize what vast plateaus winding hillside roads are. For us pedestrians, these were like concert stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people I saw on my way up were either flying down the swooping roads on bikes and skateboards, in a fashion that made me involuntarily rehearse what I would do when they fell off, or flying unrealistically up the swooping roads on bikes, in a fashion that made me appreciate how good the best electric bikes must be now. I noticed as I watched one speed above me in awe that he flew the brand of his bourgeoisie bicycle on the back of his shirt, and wondered if he was just paid by them to ride up and down here all day, in the hope that someone would be so impressed that they would jot down the t-shirt label as the only clue to the rapidly disappearing bike’s identity, then google it later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wandered atop the peaks, and confusingly collected a mob of crows flying above, apparently interested in me specifically. This was reasonably sinister, and in Australia birds can attack you, so I investigated on my phone, while walking hesitantly below the circling birds. At last they descended and alit on the road and guardrail around me, and stood looking at me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f513e0f-03b1-4ca6-99cc-e44ee9ad1936_1200x1600.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;View with ravens staring&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture captures the bizarreness of the situation about as badly as it captures the awesomeness of the scenery. It’s rare to be so much the center of a social situation with so little notion of what is expected of you or the meaning of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think things then just kind of dissipated and I made efficiently for home.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="travel" /><summary type="html">Content warning: low content ~ Feb 2021 The other day I decided to try imbibing work-relevant blog posts via AI-generated recital, while scaling the Twin Peaks—large hills near my house in San Francisco, of the sort that one lives near and doesn’t get around to going to. It was pretty strange, all around.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f513e0f-03b1-4ca6-99cc-e44ee9ad1936_1200x1600.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f513e0f-03b1-4ca6-99cc-e44ee9ad1936_1200x1600.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is my Facebook feed about?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/15/what-is-my-facebook-feed-about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is my Facebook feed about?" /><published>2024-05-15T23:02:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T23:02:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/15/what-is-my-facebook-feed-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/15/what-is-my-facebook-feed-about.html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I look at social media a bunch, but it would be hard for me to tell you what the actual content is, I suppose because whenever I’m looking at it, I’m focused on each object thing level in turn, not the big picture. So sometimes I’m curious what it is I read about there. Here is the answer for Facebook, in 2019—according to a list I found that appears to be a survey of such—and again now. Plausibly not at a useful level of abstraction, but I have a bit of a migraine and no more energy for this project.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;november-11-2019&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;November 11 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question about other people’s word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question about other people’s inferences from word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Illustrated sex joke&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encouragement and instructions for opening up communication with attractive strangers in public places&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cute kid quote&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Historic anti women’s suffrage leaflet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cute kid quote and question about word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recommendation and anecdote for Roam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humorous anecdotal request for computer security problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joke I don’t get about Jesus with lots of emoticons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sokal affair&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advice on surviving bushfires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feminist writer screenshots and describes random online abuse from man&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharing of personal health data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science says a thing about dinosaurs and space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tax policy trolling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saudi spies at twitter news&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sexual/biological facts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anecdote about medical system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ethics injoke&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current reading list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Travel photos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anecdote about australian bushfires with tenderness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long letter about policy goings on within medical system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Request for acronym unknown to me&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Funny law&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science about biology, cryonics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question about word usage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Politics opinion on events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Futuristic anime style politics cartoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notable patterns:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about word usage: 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kid related: 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;may-15-2024&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;May 15, 2024&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Before checking, my sense is that the rate of posts about children and getting married is way up.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI company politics commentary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Job and city change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invitation to help make game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Description of experience of making music&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book launch, project launch, new house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cryptic fertility life update&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social commentary on language, gender and wokeness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Old photo of two famous men&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Old photo of author winning an award&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Event ad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death of father&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of OP kissing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update on losing job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wedding planning views&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book launch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social commentary around political ideologies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death of dog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Questioning claim about changes in breathing rate over history&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take on home buying&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI lab politics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of partner on trip&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of self at work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Own photo of bird&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commentary on culture of judgment and author’s parents’ behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remembering child relative who died&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General self-help style commentary on human behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo of dogs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mothers’ day and Aurora photos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invitation to help make game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some notable patterns:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kid related: 0-3 (maybe down from 2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marriage related: 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—&amp;gt; I’m pretty wrong about the density of children and marriage related posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job/book updates: 5 (up from 0)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller projects: 5 (up from 2-4)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—&amp;gt; Actually a lot of project related posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humor: ~0 (down from at least 5)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Word usage: 1 (down from at least 4)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—&amp;gt; Some classic sources of entertainment are way down (or we see random noise)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">Sometimes I look at social media a bunch, but it would be hard for me to tell you what the actual content is, I suppose because whenever I’m looking at it, I’m focused on each object thing level in turn, not the big picture. So sometimes I’m curious what it is I read about there. Here is the answer for Facebook, in 2019—according to a list I found that appears to be a survey of such—and again now. Plausibly not at a useful level of abstraction, but I have a bit of a migraine and no more energy for this project.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Things I hate about Partiful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/things-i-hate-about-partiful.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things I hate about Partiful" /><published>2024-05-09T22:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T22:24:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/things-i-hate-about-partiful</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/09/things-i-hate-about-partiful.html">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The aesthetic for all parties is basically the same.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That aesthetic is bad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A party is an aesthetic creation, so having all guests’ first experience of the thing you are offering them be a chintzy piece of crap that matches every other chintzy piece of crap is much worse than if the thing they were selling was like low-quality toilet paper or something.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, the only way to be informed of parties using Partiful is via SMS. Perhaps this is idiosyncratic to me, but I have no desire to ever use SMS. I also don’t want to receive a message in the middle of whatever I’m doing to hear about a new party happening. Fuck off. This should only happen if the party is very time sensitive and important. Like if a best friend or much sought after celebrity is having a party in the next twenty minutes, sure text me, if you don’t have WhatsApp. Otherwise, ffs email me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, the only way to message the host a question about the party is to post it to the entire group. Yet there are very few questions I want to text an entire guest list about.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supposing I make the error of doing that (which I do not), as far as I can tell, the guest list receives an sms saying that I have sent a message, and they have to click to follow a link to the website to see what the message is. &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Supposing I am considering posting such a message to the entire group, Partiful will instruct me to ‘Write something fun!’ Fuck off. I’ll decide what to write, and don’t need the condescending needling. Relatedly, if I debase myself and host something on Partiful, while I’m drafting the invitation, it has been known to describe me as ‘the wonderful [host]’. I don’t want your narrativizing. a) Maybe I’m not wonderful. You don’t know shit about me. b) I actually can’t tell if you are going to seriously write that when I post the event, so I need to investigate how to mitigate that possibility.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I’m invited to a party, things I’m not allowed to know until after I RSVP include a) who else is invited or going, and b) where it is. Like, what do you want me to decide about social events based on? Is this communism? It also feels like such officious withholding. Like, are you serious? You’re inviting me to hang out with people and you aren’t going to tell me which people until I say I’ll come? Are you on a power trip? Who is even on the power trip? The creators of Partiful on behalf of the hosts? “No, stand your ground, you’re a party creator now, don’t give up your advantage—they’ll give in and give in and RSVP eventually”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So naturally I go through the busywork of RSVPing “maybe” so I can see key details of the event. Which is annoying. But also it constitutes me saying to my friend “maybe I’ll come to your party”, which is a slightly shitty thing to say to an actual person I’m friends with, if for instance I think it’s pretty unlikely I’ll come to their party and merely want to check if this is the rare party that I do want to go to. Furthermore, now I’ve made it clear (to an as-yet unknown set of people who RSVP’d) that I’ve seen the party and am explicitly and concretely probably-rejecting it. I’m in a whole public social interaction with it. Whereas I might have liked to examine the party without engaging, leaving my knowledge of it and position on it ambiguous.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ok, so three steps in: I have moved from a contentless text message to a website and RSVP’d maybe and can at last see key details. At that point Partiful pops another notification into my phone telling me that I RSVP’d maybe.  Why? I know I RSVP’d maybe, because I was the person who did it, and it was three seconds ago. If later I don’t know and want to know, I’ll actually check in the event invitation, not the interminable list of similar looking messages from Partiful. And I was actually already looking at the event invitation until you distracted me with my phone. And if occasionally I err—thinking I RSVP’d maybe but really having RSVP’d a different thing, say—then this isn’t a fucking space expedition; things will be okay.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then probably I just forget about it and leave it as a maybe, because I have other things to do in life, and this has already gone on for way too long, and I have technically RSVP’d, and who knows if I’ll go to a thing. So that’s annoying for the host, if they might have liked a real RSVP.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But if I do try to RSVP more specifically, my options are “I’m going” and “Can’t go”. So in the situation that arises nearly every time—I can go but I don’t want to—Partiful has decided I’m going to just tell a little white lie to the host? Or just that I should go unless I can’t? It’s true that declining events is a difficult issue, and for many people white lies are the way out. But that’s because it’s too awkward to say “I don’t want to”. But if there are only two messages you can send—basically ‘yes’ and basically ‘no’—selected by a company, it’s not actually awkward to choose the ‘no’ one, because it doesn’t distinguish not wanting to and not being able to. There’s no reason for Partiful to put a lie in your mouth there. It’s true that it’s also not that bad to say a falsehood, given that you only have two options, and are clearly most of the time going to want to say a thing you haven’t been given the option to say. But why add this note of false smarm? Like, Partiful could make the options “yes” and “no because my mother is in hospital”, and I wouldn’t hold it against people if they clicked the latter, but I would hold it against the maker of the options.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I decide to tell my friend I can’t go to their party, Partiful will message me on my phone again, with a crying face, saying sorry I can’t go to the party. I don’t need this shit. I don’t want your emotional involvement in my decisions about when to socialize, corporation. True, it’s only fake emotional involvement, but I don’t want to be bathed in the fake emotions of corporations either. I’m a social animal, this stuff does change how I feel, change my sense of the sea of minds I feel I’m surrounded by, the emotions of the world. At a basic level, it’s hard to say no to things, and yet I have to: the alternative is to waste my life being overwhelmed and not even able to make progress on the spew of second-rate things I sleepwalk into saying yes to. And being pinged with pictures of crying when I judge that something isn’t the right thing for me to go to, and say no doesn’t help me. Does it help the host? Do they want to manipulate me? Probably not. Is Partiful’s hope that I learn to go to Partiful parties a little bit more if I feel micro-guilty and micro-sad when I decline them, and then the hosts have the sense that people come to Partiful parties more, so the company benefits? I doubt it, I guess the makers just lack much sense of what a good social world could look like, and are thoughtlessly enacting trumped up emotion where available, in the hope that trumped up emotion gets attention, and attention gets success.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">The aesthetic for all parties is basically the same. That aesthetic is bad. A party is an aesthetic creation, so having all guests’ first experience of the thing you are offering them be a chintzy piece of crap that matches every other chintzy piece of crap is much worse than if the thing they were selling was like low-quality toilet paper or something. As far as I can tell, the only way to be informed of parties using Partiful is via SMS. Perhaps this is idiosyncratic to me, but I have no desire to ever use SMS. I also don’t want to receive a message in the middle of whatever I’m doing to hear about a new party happening. Fuck off. This should only happen if the party is very time sensitive and important. Like if a best friend or much sought after celebrity is having a party in the next twenty minutes, sure text me, if you don’t have WhatsApp. Otherwise, ffs email me. As far as I can tell, the only way to message the host a question about the party is to post it to the entire group. Yet there are very few questions I want to text an entire guest list about. Supposing I make the error of doing that (which I do not), as far as I can tell, the guest list receives an sms saying that I have sent a message, and they have to click to follow a link to the website to see what the message is.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-05-09_at_10.36.46_PM.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/Screen_Shot_2024-05-09_at_10.36.46_PM.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">An explanation of evil in an organized world</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/02/the-problem-of-evil-in-an-organized-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An explanation of evil in an organized world" /><published>2024-05-02T05:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T05:18:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/02/the-problem-of-evil-in-an-organized-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/02/the-problem-of-evil-in-an-organized-world.html">&lt;p&gt;A classic problem with Christianity is the so-called ‘problem of evil’—that friction between the hypothesis that the world’s creator is arbitrarily good and powerful, and a large fraction of actual observations of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming up with solutions to the problem of evil is a compelling endeavor if you are really rooting for a particular bottom line re Christianity, or I guess if you enjoy making up faux-valid arguments for wrong conclusions. At any rate, I think about this more than you might guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think I’ve solved it! &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least, I thought of a new solution which seems better than the others I’ve heard. (Though I mostly haven’t heard them since high school.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world (much like anything) has different levels of organization. People are made of cells; cells are made of molecules; molecules are made of atoms; atoms are made of subatomic particles, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t actually make a person (of the usual kind) without including atoms, and you can’t make a whole bunch of atoms in a particular structure without having made a person. These are logical facts, just like you can’t draw a triangle without drawing corners, and you can’t draw three corners connected by three lines without drawing a triangle. In particular, even God can’t. (This is already established I think—for instance, I think it is agreed that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omnipotence_paradox&quot;&gt;God cannot make a rock so big that God cannot lift it&lt;/a&gt;, and that this is not a threat to God’s omnipotence.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So God can’t make the atoms be arranged one way and the humans be arranged another contradictory way. If God has opinions about what is good at different levels of organization, and they don’t coincide, then he has to make trade-offs. If he cares about some level aside from the human level, then at the human level, things are going to have to be a bit suboptimal sometimes. Or perhaps entirely unrelated to what would be optimal, all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We usually assume God only cares about the human level. But if we take for granted that he made the world maximally good, then we might infer that he also cares about at least one other level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think if we look at the world with this in mind, it’s pretty clear where that level is. If there’s one thing God really makes sure happens, it’s ‘the laws of physics’. Though presumably laws are just what you see when God cares. To be ‘fundamental’ is to matter so much that the universe runs on the clockwork of your needs being met. There isn’t a law of nothing bad ever happening to anyone’s child; there’s a law of energy being conserved in particle interactions. God cares about particle interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, God cares so much about what happens to sub-atomic particles that he actually never, to our knowledge, compromises on that front. God will let anything go down at the human level rather than let one neutron go astray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should we infer from this? That the majority of moral value is found at the level of fundamental physics (following &lt;a href=&quot;https://reducing-suffering.org/is-there-suffering-in-fundamental-physics/&quot;&gt;Brian Tomasik&lt;/a&gt; and then going further). Happily we don’t need to worry about this, because God has it under control. We might however wonder what we can infer from this about the moral value of other levels that are less important yet logically intertwined with and thus beyond the reach of God, but might still be more valuable than the one we usually focus on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><summary type="html">A classic problem with Christianity is the so-called ‘problem of evil’—that friction between the hypothesis that the world’s creator is arbitrarily good and powerful, and a large fraction of actual observations of the world. Coming up with solutions to the problem of evil is a compelling endeavor if you are really rooting for a particular bottom line re Christianity, or I guess if you enjoy making up faux-valid arguments for wrong conclusions. At any rate, I think about this more than you might guess. And I think I’ve solved it!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/70455faa-3bb4-4947-88f1-cc9bb5915428_1024x1024.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/70455faa-3bb4-4947-88f1-cc9bb5915428_1024x1024.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The first future and the best future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/25/the-first-future-or-the-best-future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The first future and the best future" /><published>2024-04-25T07:22:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-25T07:22:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/25/the-first-future-or-the-best-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/25/the-first-future-or-the-best-future.html">&lt;p&gt;It seems to me worth &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.substack.com/p/lets-think-about-slowing-down-ai&quot;&gt;trying to slow down AI development&lt;/a&gt; to steer successfully around the shoals of extinction and out to utopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was thinking lately: even if I didn’t think there was any chance of extinction risk, it might still be worth prioritizing a lot of care over moving at maximal speed. Because there are many different possible AI futures, and I think there’s a good chance that the initial direction affects the long term path, and different long term paths go to different places. The systems we build now will shape the next systems, and so forth. If the first human-level-ish AI is brain emulations, I expect a quite different sequence of events to if it is GPT-ish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People genuinely pushing for AI speed over care (rather than just feeling impotent) apparently think there is negligible risk of bad outcomes, but also they are asking to take the first future to which there is a path. Yet possible futures are a large space, and arguably we are in a rare plateau where we could climb very different hills, and get to much better futures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="ai" /><summary type="html">It seems to me worth trying to slow down AI development to steer successfully around the shoals of extinction and out to utopia. But I was thinking lately: even if I didn’t think there was any chance of extinction risk, it might still be worth prioritizing a lot of care over moving at maximal speed. Because there are many different possible AI futures, and I think there’s a good chance that the initial direction affects the long term path, and different long term paths go to different places. The systems we build now will shape the next systems, and so forth. If the first human-level-ish AI is brain emulations, I expect a quite different sequence of events to if it is GPT-ish. People genuinely pushing for AI speed over care (rather than just feeling impotent) apparently think there is negligible risk of bad outcomes, but also they are asking to take the first future to which there is a path. Yet possible futures are a large space, and arguably we are in a rare plateau where we could climb very different hills, and get to much better futures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experiment on repeating choices</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/18/experiment-on-repeating-choices.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experiment on repeating choices" /><published>2024-04-18T16:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T16:18:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/18/experiment-on-repeating-choices</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/18/experiment-on-repeating-choices.html">&lt;p&gt;People behave differently from one another on all manner of axes, and each person is usually pretty consistent about it. For instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to spend money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to worry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to listen vs. speak&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to jump to conclusions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how playful to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how spontaneous to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much to prepare&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much to socialize&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much to exercise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much to smile&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how honest to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How snarky to be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to trade off convenience, enjoyment, time and healthiness in food&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are often about trade-offs, and the best point on each spectrum for any particular person seems like an empirical question. Do people know the answers to these questions? I’m a bit skeptical, because they mostly haven’t tried many points. &lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I think these mostly don’t feel like open empirical questions: people have a sense of what the correct place on the axis is (possibly ignoring a trade-off), and some propensities that make a different place on the axis natural, and some resources they can allocate to moving from the natural place toward the ideal place. And the result is a fairly consistent point for each person. For instance, Bob might feel that the correct amount to worry about things is around zero, but worrying arises very easily in his mind and is hard to shake off, so he ‘tries not to worry’ some amount based on how much effort he has available and what else is going on, and lands in a place about that far from his natural worrying point. He could actually still worry a bit more or a bit less, perhaps by exerting more or less effort, or by thinking of a different point as the goal, but in practice he will probably worry about as much as he feels he has energy for limiting himself to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people do intentionally choose a new point—perhaps by thinking about it and deciding to spend less money, or exercise more, or try harder to listen. Then they hope to enact that new point for the indefinite future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for choices we play out a tiny bit every day, there is a lot of scope for iterative improvement, exploring the spectrum. I posit that people should rarely be asking themselves ‘should I value my time more?’ in an abstract fashion for more than a few minutes before they just try valuing their time more for a bit and see if they feel better about that lifestyle overall, with its conveniences and costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are implicitly making the same choice a massive number of times, and getting it wrong for a tiny fraction of them isn’t high stakes, then it’s probably worth experiencing the different options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that point about the value of time came from Tyler Cowen a long time ago, but I often think it should apply to lots of other spectrums in life, like some of those listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this to be a reasonable strategy, the following need to be true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ll actually get feedback&lt;/strong&gt; about the things that might be better or worse (e.g. if you smile more or less you might immediately notice how this changes conversations, but if you wear your seatbelt more or less you probably don’t get into a crash and experience that side of the trade-off)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimentation doesn’t burn anything important&lt;/strong&gt; at a much larger scale (e.g. trying out working less for a week is only a good use case if you aren’t going to get fired that week if you pick the level wrong)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can actually try other points on the spectrum&lt;/strong&gt;, at least a bit, without large up-front costs (e.g. perhaps you want to try smiling more or less, but you can only do so extremely awkwardly, so you would need to practice in order to experience what those levels would be like in equilibrium)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don’t already know what the best level is for you&lt;/strong&gt; (maybe your experience isn’t very important, and you can tell in the abstract everything you need to know - e.g. if you think eating animals is a terrible sin, then experimenting with more or less avoiding animal products isn’t going to be informative, because even not worrying about food makes you more productive, you might not care)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t actually follow this advice much. I think it’s separately hard to notice that many of these things are choices. So I don’t have much evidence about it being good advice, it’s just a thing I often think about. But maybe my default level of caring about things like not giving people advice I haven’t even tried isn’t the best one. So perhaps I’ll try now being a bit less careful about stuff like that. Where ‘stuff like that’ also includes having a well-defined notion of ‘stuff like that’ before I embark on experimentally modifying it. And ending blog posts well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="meteuphoric" /><category term="advice" /><summary type="html">People behave differently from one another on all manner of axes, and each person is usually pretty consistent about it. For instance: how much to spend money how much to worry how much to listen vs. speak how much to jump to conclusions how much to work how playful to be how spontaneous to be how much to prepare How much to socialize How much to exercise How much to smile how honest to be How snarky to be How to trade off convenience, enjoyment, time and healthiness in food These are often about trade-offs, and the best point on each spectrum for any particular person seems like an empirical question. Do people know the answers to these questions? I’m a bit skeptical, because they mostly haven’t tried many points.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55931011-09bd-4a06-b0db-1e68a2898314_1024x1024.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1250,h_833,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_center/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F55931011-09bd-4a06-b0db-1e68a2898314_1024x1024.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>