<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-26T22:12:51-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">What is up with spirituality?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/26/what-is-up-with-spirituality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is up with spirituality?" /><published>2021-01-26T09:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T09:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/26/what-is-up-with-spirituality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/26/what-is-up-with-spirituality.html">&lt;p&gt;What is up with spirituality? I mean, from an atheistic perspective?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, atheists tend to focus on the empirical question of whether there is an all-powerful supernatural creature behind all that we observe. And yeah, there probably isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But having won that point, what does one make of the extreme popularity of religion? I think the usual answer given is something like ‘well, we used to be very ignorant and not have good explanations of natural phenomena, plus we tend to see agents in everything because our agent detection software is oversensitive’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which might explain the question ‘Why would people think a supernatural agent controls things?’. But what seems like only a corner of religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big part of religion—and a thing that also occurs outside religion—seems to be ‘spirituality’—a cluster of things I find hard to describe, but which seem pretty disconnected from explanatory questions of where trees came from or why the crops failed.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some stylized facts about spirituality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People across religions have ‘spiritual experiences’ that involve particular styles of feeling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People can have spiritual attitudes more broadly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spiritual attitudes involve less interest in ‘worldly’ or petty things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spiritual things often involve sacredness and ritual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spiritual feelings are often associated with awe and the word ‘transcendent’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spiritual experiences do not present themselves as about hedonic enjoyment of the experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirituality is connected with ‘meaning’ and tends to feel deep and significant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirituality tends toward an interest in philosophy, especially metaphysics, especially regarding whether everything is one, the nature of selfhood, the possibility and nature of ‘souls’, the nature of love&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Certain drugs seem to induce spiritual or adjacent states&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirituality tends to be fairly positive, in the sense that from a satisfactorily spiritual mental place, one expects the world to seem broadly good or at least compatible with peace&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirituality is related to ideas of connecting with something beyond yourself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirituality is sincere&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirituality is serious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spirituality is normative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I suspect that from a spiritual vantage, this list might seem like a mundane missing of the point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are people into spirituality? Why is it a kind of thing that humans can experience? Why is it a thing they experience so much?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="evolutionary-explanations" /><category term="religion" /><category term="spirituality" /><category term="questions" /><summary type="html">What is up with spirituality? I mean, from an atheistic perspective? In my experience, atheists tend to focus on the empirical question of whether there is an all-powerful supernatural creature behind all that we observe. And yeah, there probably isn’t. But having won that point, what does one make of the extreme popularity of religion? I think the usual answer given is something like ‘well, we used to be very ignorant and not have good explanations of natural phenomena, plus we tend to see agents in everything because our agent detection software is oversensitive’. Which might explain the question ‘Why would people think a supernatural agent controls things?’. But what seems like only a corner of religion. Another big part of religion—and a thing that also occurs outside religion—seems to be ‘spirituality’—a cluster of things I find hard to describe, but which seem pretty disconnected from explanatory questions of where trees came from or why the crops failed.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/annie-spratt-qHWpzufER-A-unsplash(1).jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/annie-spratt-qHWpzufER-A-unsplash(1).jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wordtune review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/26/wordtune.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wordtune review" /><published>2021-01-26T00:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T00:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/26/wordtune</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/26/wordtune.html">&lt;p&gt;Wow, Facebook is advertising &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wordtune.com/&quot;&gt;an AI-driven writing tool&lt;/a&gt; to me. I think this is the first time I’ve seen a mainstream potentially useful product coming from all of this. Let’s see how it does. I’ve started by writing this paragraph quickly myself, and then I will rewrite it using Wordtune, to demonstrate its features. Then I may rewrite it further using its premium features or my more honed writing, all going well.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, Facebook is showing me a machine-learning based writing platform. I believe that this is the first mainstream application of all this. See how it goes. I wrote this paragraph on my own quickly, and then rewrote it using Wordtune to demonstrate its features. Then I may rewrite it using its premium features or using my more refined writing skills, if all goes well.
—Wordtune&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am intrigued by Facebook’s advertisement with regards to an artificial intelligence (AI) writing tool. I’m not aware of any mainstream application arising from these efforts.Let us see how it goes. I created this paragraph quickly myself, and now I’m going to rewrite it using Wordtune to demonstrate all it has to offer. Afterwards, I will be able to incorporate premium features in it or craft it into a more refined style, all going well.
—formal Wordtune&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, Facebook is advertising a writing tool which uses artificial intelligence (AI) that I did not know existed. This is something of a landmark event; I’ve not yet seen a mainstream useful product coming out of anything like this. I’m looking forward to seeing how it goes. I’ve begun by writing this paragraph myself but I will then rewrite it with the aid of Wordtune to illustrate its various features. Then I may rewrite it further using its premium features or my more honed writing, all going well.
—longer Wordtune&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, Facebook’s touting a writing tool powered by artificial intelligence. This is the first time I’ve seen a mainstream use coming from all this. Let’s see what it does. I wrote it quickly, and I’m gonna rewrite it with Wordtune, just so I can show you how it works. After that I’ll maybe rewrite it more using its premium features or my own better skills.
—casual Wordtune&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, Facebook offers me an AI-driven writing tool. This is the first mainstream product I’ve seen from all of this. Let’s see. I first wrote the paragraph, and then I rewrote it with Wordtune, so you can see its features. Then I will retake it using its premium features or my better writing, all going well.
—shorter Wordtune&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook just surprised me with an ad for an AI writing tool. Could it be the first useful mainstream product to come from all this?  Let’s take it for a ride. I wrote this paragraph fast, then asked Wordtune to rewrite it, to show you its moves. I might repeat the demonstration with its other style options, or mine, fate willing.
—me spending more time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Facebook ad for AI-improved writing! GPT-3-like tools enter the mainstream. Let’s try it. I jot five lines, apply Wordtune, and watch. Next I might compare paid features or my own skills.
—me shorter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook takes a break in its endless stream of extremely comfortable-looking bra suggestions and creepy-but-welcome commercials for things I mentioned in conversation or thought of in a dream once or something, to offer me artificial intelligence to automate half my writing process. Wait, what? Is it the future at last? Shit! I like that half of my writing process. Well, let’s see it. I’ll write a shitty paragraph, and then see what this ‘Wordtune’ can do with it. Then maybe I’ll see what I can do with it, to compare (and see if it’s all over for my joyous thesaurus expeditions).
—me, humorous conversational&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="AI" /><category term="review" /><category term="software" /><category term="service" /><summary type="html">Wow, Facebook is advertising an AI-driven writing tool to me. I think this is the first time I’ve seen a mainstream potentially useful product coming from all of this. Let’s see how it does. I’ve started by writing this paragraph quickly myself, and then I will rewrite it using Wordtune, to demonstrate its features. Then I may rewrite it further using its premium features or my more honed writing, all going well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tentative covid surface risk estimates</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/25/tentative-covid-surface-risk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tentative covid surface risk estimates" /><published>2021-01-25T00:25:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T00:25:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/25/tentative-covid-surface-risk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/25/tentative-covid-surface-risk.html">&lt;p&gt;My household previously made some highly uncertain estimates of the covid risk from bringing random objects that other people have recently been touching into our home, for instance salads and groceries an endless stream of Amazon packages. The official guidance is very vague, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/faq.html&quot;&gt;“…not thought to be the main way the virus spreads”&lt;/a&gt;. Our bad estimates were fairly low, so we decided to basically ignore it in our covid risk accounting, except for habitually taking some reasonable precautions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the covid rates here increased by a factor of ten, so we decided it would be good to look at it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I tried to estimate this from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/medrxiv/early/2020/11/01/2020.10.27.20220905.full.pdf&quot;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; (HT Ben Weinstein-Raun and Catherine Olsson) in which a group of researchers swabbed various door handles and trash cans and crosswalk buttons and the like in a small Massachusetts city and measured the covid RNA detectable on them. They also used the amounts they measured to estimate the infectiousness if someone else were to touch the surface and then touch their face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.getguesstimate.com/models/17305&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; I offer you a draft of an elaborate Guesstimate spreadsheet on the topic, in case you are interested in such things.&lt;!--ex--&gt; Hopefully someone is, and will tell me ways that it is wrong, then later I might offer you something reliable. At present, it is probably pretty unreliable, and should only be used insofar as you would otherwise use something even more unreliable. Some non-exhaustive evidence of its unreliableness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I haven’t actually read much of the paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The answers in the spreadsheet have changed substantially while I have felt about as confident in them as I do now&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are numerous places where it seems dubious to me, or where I made up numbers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I try not to be the sort of person who only shares things if they are of high quality, even if the stakes are high&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This calculation is ignoring the efforts everyone is making to be safe, so you might underestimate the risks if surfaces look low risk in this study because supermarket employees are actually constantly wiping them down, for instance. So it should probably be interpreted more like ‘if you take levels of caution similar to those taken with the study surfaces…’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting tentative conclusions so far, rely upon at own risk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a person with covid touching something then you touching it then touching your face is worth extremely roughly 13 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microcovid.org/?distance=sixFt&amp;amp;duration=136&amp;amp;interaction=oneTime&amp;amp;personCount=20&amp;amp;riskProfile=average&amp;amp;setting=plane&amp;amp;subLocation=US_06075&amp;amp;theirMask=basic&amp;amp;topLocation=US_06&amp;amp;voice=silent&amp;amp;yourMask=n95&quot;&gt;microcovids&lt;/a&gt; (uCov) (with 90% confidence of 0.7 to 110 according to my estimate, but I wouldn’t trust that)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus such a touch-touch-face sequence with a random person in San Francisco (where I live) at the moment is ~0.7 uCov (give or take an order of magnitude)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adding further wild guesses about how many touches are involved in acquiring groceries, I get that a 30 item San Francisco grocery trip is worth about 5 uCov (give or take an order of magnitude)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that would mean about two cases from groceries in San Francisco per week, (give or take an order of magnitude) which doesn’t sound crazy to me. (You might think it does sound crazy, because surely we would notice that by now, but I’m pretty uncertain about our collective ability to observe and infer things.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic reasoning is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If an infected person touches a surface, it looks like it has about a 13% chance of becoming detectably infectious by this method (based on 36 samples from grocery store surfaces which are estimated by me to receive very roughly 2 covid-infected touches per day yielding 4 positive samples, along with some complication with distributions that make the arithmetic strange.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Average risk from touching one of these positive-testing surfaces is very roughly 100 microcovids (taking an estimate half way between the average grocery surface infectiousness and the average surface infectiousness, according to the paper)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So if a person with covid touches a surface, then you touch it and then touch your face, this gives us about 13% of 100 microcovids = 13 microcovids (.0013% chance of covid)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome all kinds of comments, e.g. even ‘I want to know why this cell says 27, but I can’t be bothered reading all these things’.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="covid" /><category term="botec" /><summary type="html">My household previously made some highly uncertain estimates of the covid risk from bringing random objects that other people have recently been touching into our home, for instance salads and groceries an endless stream of Amazon packages. The official guidance is very vague, e.g. “…not thought to be the main way the virus spreads”. Our bad estimates were fairly low, so we decided to basically ignore it in our covid risk accounting, except for habitually taking some reasonable precautions. Then the covid rates here increased by a factor of ten, so we decided it would be good to look at it again. So today I tried to estimate this from this paper (HT Ben Weinstein-Raun and Catherine Olsson) in which a group of researchers swabbed various door handles and trash cans and crosswalk buttons and the like in a small Massachusetts city and measured the covid RNA detectable on them. They also used the amounts they measured to estimate the infectiousness if someone else were to touch the surface and then touch their face. Here I offer you a draft of an elaborate Guesstimate spreadsheet on the topic, in case you are interested in such things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Li’l pots</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/24/lil-pots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Li'l pots" /><published>2021-01-24T03:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-24T03:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/24/lil-pots</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/24/lil-pots.html">&lt;p&gt;As a pandemic-era purchaser of foods for a large household of time-thirsty researchers, I can tell you an interesting thing about the demand for cheese in this context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you spend a lot of money on a nice cheese, wrapped up in some fancy foreign label, there is a good chance that it will languish sadly in the back of the fridge for months until someone notices that it is moldy and throws it away, or makes a last-ditch attempt to cut up the whole thing and compel the group to eat it. Maybe on the way there, someone will take a single slice of it once, and move it in a zip-loc bag, where it will remain until the end.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you spend a few dollars on a six-pack of generic single-serve cheese-cubes with nuts, they will fly from the fridge and you will be acknowledged for this triumph of shopping, and more such cheese will be needed by the next grocery order.&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was initially hypothesized by a housemate that this was due to error. The cheese cubes are more expensive per unit of cheese, while also consisting of worse cheese. Which is fairly suggestive of overall worseness. One could further note that they involve substantially more packaging, and take up more space per cheese. So a natural theory is that the cheese-cube eating housemates are erring, due to some kind of short-sighted non-endorsed laziness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m with the cheese-cube eaters, except at least ten times more passionately (for instance, I am writing an essay in favor of the position). It’s not about the quality-adjusted cheese per dollar. Getting out a pre-opened hunk of cheese, examining the color and consistency of its moist edges, awkwardly undressing it further from its tight, torn, damp plastic casing, finding a knife and something to cut it on, cutting some, wrapping the rest again, fitting it back in the fridge, and cleaning up the knife and counter, is an experience. And it’s not a good one. It has all kinds of wetness and ineffectual muscular exertions and tenuous balancing and making hard decisions about risk under uncertainty and washing things. Whereas reaching out your hand for a cheese-cube pack then de-lidding it into the trash—while not an amazing experience—is I’d say overall positive, being substantially comprised of the initial sighting of your desired cheese-cube-pack and then the immediate having of it. At worst it is a very short experience. And it makes perfect sense to prefer twenty seconds of the cheese cube experience to two minutes of the better cheese experience enough to overwhelm the other stakes of the choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have relatively consistent preferences in this direction, whereas the rest of the house seems to vary by food. Others lunch on intermediately aged leftovers ladled from stacked tupperwares, while if I’m not going to make something fresh, I prefer just-add-boiling-water pots of vegetable curry or microwaveable instant rice (I do add butter and herbs though, which is a slight departure from the genre). Others have been known to eat yogurt spooned into a bowl from a giant tub, while I eat from towers of fresh stackable single-serve yogurt pots. Snack foods tend to cater to my interests here better, perhaps because everyone hopes to be more lazy and individualistic for snacks. There are tiny bags of chips and string cheeses and nut butter pouches and apple chips and fruit strips and protein bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My boyfriend affectionately refers to these objects of my desire as ‘li’l pots’ (probably a term he grabbed from some gleeful past exclamation of mine) and often offers me ‘some sort of li’l pot?’ for breakfast, whether it be oatmeal or yogurt or rice pudding or mashed potato to be determined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I claim that this is not about appreciating aesthetic qualities less. It is about appreciating more aesthetic qualities. Packaging can be beautiful and simple and pleasing to use, but it is often painful to behold and also painful to try to open: packets that tear open half way down the side, or can’t be opened at all with normal-range female grip strength, or that naturally explode their contents on nearby objects unless you do something that I haven’t discovered yet, or that cut your hands then leave you holding a small overflowing tub of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arrangement of objects can similarly give pleasure or suffering: my stack of fresh white yogurt bled through with passionfruit, lemon or red berries asks to be reached for, whereas the jumble of giant containers of yogurt and sour cream and cream cheese on top and in front of each other and strewn between with other objects trying to fit somewhere, has no such appeal. String cheeses living upright and individuated are much more appealing than string cheeses attached together in a large string cheese blanket inside another plastic packet horizontally hidden under some other cheeses. Small stacks of different types of protein bar laid out for eating are more pleasing than a rubble of large packages thrown into a drawer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210124_085625042.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snack drawer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And actions can be aesthetically pleasing or not. Peeling a grape with your teeth is pleasing. Breaking through the tin-foil-paper on top of a new jar of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caro_(drink)&quot;&gt;Caro&lt;/a&gt; can be very pleasing. Wrestling an icy firm-like-slightly-decomposing-wood field roast sausage from its skin-tight twisted plastic tubing is not pleasing. Any kind of tearing that is difficult and involves a new liquid appearing that you are not equipped to deal with is not pleasing. Anything that naturally calls for more than two hands is not pleasing unless you are a group of people. Making judgment calls about food safety is not pleasing. Actions that require finding, dirtying, and cleaning multiple objects tend not to be pleasing unless there’s a real payoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just about the time. There are preparation rituals that are beautiful and compelling. I am secretly a bit pleased that our coffee machine is being replaced and we are temporarily relegated to measuring fresh grounds into my beautiful orange French press, then pouring boiling water into the roiling black soup of them, then slowly pressing the mandala-like metal plunger onto them, perhaps watching mysterious currents shooting up the sides of the clear glass tower. I enjoy choosing a cup, and directing a smooth black torrent into its belly. I like shaking the cream carton with vigor, and pouring a dollop of its heavy white cloud into the black depths, to curl and spiral through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is not to say that others should agree with my evaluation of li’l pots. The same series of actions is probably a very different experience for different people. For one person, there might be a single action ‘get out some cheese’, and in a half-conscious flurry it happens, and they are soon focused on the eating of the cheese. For a different person ‘get out some cheese’ means something more like ‘take out the cream cheese and the yogurt and balance them tenuously near the fridge, then reach in and get the intended cheese from a slightly wet and slimy pool on the shelf, then replace the cream cheese and the yogurt, then try to open the cheese while touching only the dry bits, then be unable to rip the plastic on the first three tries but hurt your finger somewhat, then look for scissors to cut it, then fail to find them and look for a knife instead, then use the knife to somewhat recklessly cut the edge of the packet, then try to rip it again from there, then get it suddenly and nearly lose the cheese (in the process grab the wet package and the cheese and give up on that particular separation), then open a cupboard with the least cheesy part of your hand and take out a chopping board and put the cheese on it, then hope that the pool of liquid running from the cheese doesn’t run onto the counter, then wash your hands because of the fridge slime and the cheese water, then cut off some cheese with the knife, then take out a storage container and move the rest of the cheese from its entire now-useless package into the container, then throw out the bag, then wipe up the cheese water that dripped while moving the bag, then move the yogurt and the cream cheese again, then put the cheese block back in the pool of liquid, then replace the yogurt and the cream cheese, then wipe up the cheese water from the counter, then wash the knife, then take your cheese to your room so that you can lie down for a bit before eating the fucking thing.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/PXL_20210124_085413704.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;yogurt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I do have OCD, so my love of indeterminate liquids, contamination, decisions about safety risks, and additional reasons to wash my hands is lower than it might be for a human.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="lifestyle" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">As a pandemic-era purchaser of foods for a large household of time-thirsty researchers, I can tell you an interesting thing about the demand for cheese in this context: If you spend a lot of money on a nice cheese, wrapped up in some fancy foreign label, there is a good chance that it will languish sadly in the back of the fridge for months until someone notices that it is moldy and throws it away, or makes a last-ditch attempt to cut up the whole thing and compel the group to eat it. Maybe on the way there, someone will take a single slice of it once, and move it in a zip-loc bag, where it will remain until the end. If you spend a few dollars on a six-pack of generic single-serve cheese-cubes with nuts, they will fly from the fridge and you will be acknowledged for this triumph of shopping, and more such cheese will be needed by the next grocery order.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who should you expect to spend your life with?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/22/who-spend-time-with.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who should you expect to spend your life with?" /><published>2021-01-22T23:56:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-22T23:56:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/22/who-spend-time-with</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/22/who-spend-time-with.html">&lt;p&gt;Striking things about the figure below, which I got from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/time-use&quot;&gt;Our World in Data&lt;/a&gt;, on time use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People spend increasing time alone over their whole lives, with the exception of roughly their twenties. This surprises me a bit because it seems like people like spending time with other people, and I would expect them to increasingly succeed at it with experience and time to acquire partners and families and friends.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From 31 to 45, people spend more time with children&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on average than they spend with any other category of person, including for instance partners and colleagues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You might think all this children time would be substituting for some partner time, but as the children time swoops downward by three quarters, partner time stays about the same.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People are at a relationship-time-steady-state between about thirty and sixty. I imagine that many people start relationships in that time, so does that mean that they also stop them at about the same rate, or gradually reduce time with their partners at a rate matching others’ forming of new relationships? Are people radically less likely to start relationships after about thirty?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People spend broadly decreasing time with every group except their partner over time, from some early peak for each trend—in the teenage years for friends and family, and in the 20s and 30s for colleagues and children. I wonder how many people just like being alone and with their partners more than most other options, and steadily optimize for that, once they have been sociable enough to find a partner in their early years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coworker time peaks at age 25-30 and goes slowly downward before the retirement descent. Is that from people dropping out of the workforce? Earning themselves a nice private office? Some difference between junior and senior roles?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People spend fairly consistent time with their friends after a decline from 18 to 40. Retirement doesn’t increase it. Spending three hours a day fewer with children doesn’t increase it. I guess those things go to solitude.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/time-spent-with-relationships-by-age-us?tab=chart&amp;amp;stackMode=absolute&amp;amp;region=World&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 600px; border: 0px none;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/&quot;&gt;Our World In Data&lt;/a&gt; seems awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m guessing that this means ‘any children’ rather than ‘their own children’, because the rate for 15 year olds seems high &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="sociology" /><category term="forecasting" /><summary type="html">Striking things about the figure below, which I got from Our World in Data, on time use: People spend increasing time alone over their whole lives, with the exception of roughly their twenties. This surprises me a bit because it seems like people like spending time with other people, and I would expect them to increasingly succeed at it with experience and time to acquire partners and families and friends. From 31 to 45, people spend more time with children1 on average than they spend with any other category of person, including for instance partners and colleagues. You might think all this children time would be substituting for some partner time, but as the children time swoops downward by three quarters, partner time stays about the same. People are at a relationship-time-steady-state between about thirty and sixty. I imagine that many people start relationships in that time, so does that mean that they also stop them at about the same rate, or gradually reduce time with their partners at a rate matching others’ forming of new relationships? Are people radically less likely to start relationships after about thirty? People spend broadly decreasing time with every group except their partner over time, from some early peak for each trend—in the teenage years for friends and family, and in the 20s and 30s for colleagues and children. I wonder how many people just like being alone and with their partners more than most other options, and steadily optimize for that, once they have been sociable enough to find a partner in their early years. Coworker time peaks at age 25-30 and goes slowly downward before the retirement descent. Is that from people dropping out of the workforce? Earning themselves a nice private office? Some difference between junior and senior roles? People spend fairly consistent time with their friends after a decline from 18 to 40. Retirement doesn’t increase it. Spending three hours a day fewer with children doesn’t increase it. I guess those things go to solitude. In other news, Our World In Data seems awesome. I’m guessing that this means ‘any children’ rather than ‘their own children’, because the rate for 15 year olds seems high &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What if we all just stayed at home and didn’t get covid for two weeks?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/what-if-we-stayed-at-home.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if we all just stayed at home and didn't get covid for two weeks?" /><published>2021-01-21T23:14:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T23:14:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/what-if-we-stayed-at-home</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/what-if-we-stayed-at-home.html">&lt;p&gt;I keep thinking about how if at any point we were all able to actually quarantine for two weeks&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at the same time, the pandemic would be over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, if instead of everyone being more or less cautious over a year, we all agreed on single a two week period to hard quarantine. With plenty of warning, so that people had time to stock up on groceries and do anything important ahead of time. And with massive financial redistribution in advance, so that everyone could afford two weeks without work. And with some planning to equip the few essential-every-week-without-delay workers (e.g. nurses, people keeping the power on) with unsustainably excessive PPE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wouldn’t require less total risky activity. If we just managed to move all of the risky activity from one fortnight to the one before it, then that would destroy the virus (and everyone could do as many previously risky activities as they liked in the following fortnight!). It could be kind of like the Christmas week except twice as long and the government would pay most people to stay at home and watch movies or play games or whatever. Maybe the TV channels and celebrities could cooperate and try to put together an especially entertaining lineup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How unrealistic is this? It sounds pretty unrealistic, but what goes wrong?&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some possible things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To actually coordinate that many people, you would need to have serious policing—beyond what is an acceptable alternative to a year-long pandemic—or serious buy-in—beyond what is possible in any normal place of more than ten people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even if you could basically coordinate that many people, you would fail in a few places. And if you fail anywhere, then the disease will gradually build back up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can’t just have everyone buy groceries for a given fortnight at some point in the preceding months, because there aren’t enough groceries in warehouses or enough grocery producers able to spin up extra weeks of grocery production on short notice (I am especially unsure whether this is true).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The people who do really have to work are too many to over-prepare well for it in a month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would cost really a lot of money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would need to be longer than two weeks if you wanted to actually crush the disease, because some people are probably infectious for abnormally long times.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You would need everyone not living alone to stay away from those they live with, to avoid spreading covid within houses, making this a more extreme proposition than it first seems, very hard to police, and basically impossible for households with small children or other very dependent members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s just way too much logistical effort to make this happen well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1, 2 and 7 look like the clearest problems to me. I don’t know enough to say if 3, 4 or 8 are real obstacles, and it seems like the US federal government has sent out a lot of money already, so 5 could at worst be solved by doing this thing at the time the money was sent out. 6 seems true, but I’m not sure if the length it would need to be is out of the question, if the other questions are solved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 is pretty bad even in a community without dependent people, because it requires active effort from everyone to protect themselves within their houses, which seems much less likely to be ubiquitously complied with than a request to not go to effort to do something (i.e. more people will find the energy to stay on their sofas than will find the energy to set up their room to prepare food in it for a fortnight). Then the dependent people who really need to stay with someone else seem even harder to get the end-of-fortnight risk down for. I could imagine dealing with these problems by spreading people out as much as feasible and requiring longer quarantines for pairs. But the difficulty of that—or need for extending the length of the whole thing—seem quite costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 2 and 7, even if you don’t actually stop the pandemic, and you have to have another occasional scheduled ‘firebreak’ in activity, once cases had built up again, it seems like it could hugely reduce the human cost, without more total caution (just moving the caution in time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Also, if you did it for four weeks instead of two, you would only end up with cases where two failures met, i.e. where someone improbably got covid during the first two weeks, then improbably passed it on to another person in the second.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 4, One way you might swing this is to have many of the people who work during the two weeks then do their own hard quarantine in the following two weeks, where they can be replaced by some of the workers with similar skills who were at home during the main round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these depend on scale, and location. For instance, this can clearly often work at the level of a group house, and is probably too ambitious for a large and ideologically diverse nation (especially one that isn’t really organized for people to consistently wear masks after a year). Could it work at the level of a relatively anti-covid city? (The city would then have to limit or quarantine incoming travelers, but that seems doable for many cities.) A small town? A small college campus? A highly religious adult community, where the church was in favor? There are a lot of human groups in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have I got the main reasons this wouldn’t work? Is there some good solution to them that I haven’t seen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Has anyone done something like this? There have been lots of lockdowns, but have there been time-bounded almost-total lockdowns scheduled in advance, with huge efforts to avert people needing to take risks during that particular period (e.g. treating moving risks to the time earlier as great compared to running them that week)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Or however long it takes a person to reliably stop spreading covid, after contracting it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="covid" /><category term="coordination" /><category term="institution-design" /><summary type="html">I keep thinking about how if at any point we were all able to actually quarantine for two weeks1 at the same time, the pandemic would be over. Like, if instead of everyone being more or less cautious over a year, we all agreed on single a two week period to hard quarantine. With plenty of warning, so that people had time to stock up on groceries and do anything important ahead of time. And with massive financial redistribution in advance, so that everyone could afford two weeks without work. And with some planning to equip the few essential-every-week-without-delay workers (e.g. nurses, people keeping the power on) with unsustainably excessive PPE. This wouldn’t require less total risky activity. If we just managed to move all of the risky activity from one fortnight to the one before it, then that would destroy the virus (and everyone could do as many previously risky activities as they liked in the following fortnight!). It could be kind of like the Christmas week except twice as long and the government would pay most people to stay at home and watch movies or play games or whatever. Maybe the TV channels and celebrities could cooperate and try to put together an especially entertaining lineup. How unrealistic is this? It sounds pretty unrealistic, but what goes wrong? Or however long it takes a person to reliably stop spreading covid, after contracting it. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on the inner ring</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/20/the-inner-ring.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on the inner ring" /><published>2021-01-20T18:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T18:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/20/the-inner-ring</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/20/the-inner-ring.html">&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed C. S. Lewis’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lewissociety.org/innerring/&quot;&gt;The Inner Ring&lt;/a&gt;, and recommend you read it. It basically claims that much of human effort is directed at being admitted to whatever the local in-group is, that this happens easily to people, and that it is a bad thing to be drawn in to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some quotes, though I also recommend reading the whole thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the passage I have just read from Tolstoy, the young second lieutenant Boris Dubretskoi discovers that there exist in the army two different systems or hierarchies. The one is printed in some little red book and anyone can easily read it up. It also remains constant. A general is always superior to a colonel, and a colonel to a captain. The other is not printed anywhere. Nor is it even a formally organised secret society with officers and rules which you would be told after you had been admitted. You are never formally and explicitly admitted by anyone. You discover gradually, in almost indefinable ways, that it exists and that you are outside it; and then later, perhaps, that you are inside it.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;!--ex--&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There are what correspond to passwords, but they are too spontaneous and informal. A particular slang, the use of particular nicknames, an allusive manner of conversation, are the marks. But it is not so constant. It is not easy, even at a given moment, to say who is inside and who is outside. Some people are obviously in and some are obviously out, but there are always several on the borderline. And if you come back to the same Divisional Headquarters, or Brigade Headquarters, or the same regiment or even the same company, after six weeks’ absence, you may find this secondary hierarchy quite altered.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There are no formal admissions or expulsions. People think they are in it after they have in fact been pushed out of it, or before they have been allowed in: this provides great amusement for those who are really inside. It has no fixed name. The only certain rule is that the insiders and outsiders call it by different names. From inside it may be designated, in simple cases, by mere enumeration: it may be called “You and Tony and me.” When it is very secure and comparatively stable in membership it calls itself “we.” When it has to be expanded to meet a particular emergency it calls itself “all the sensible people at this place.” From outside, if you have dispaired of getting into it, you call it “That gang” or “they” or “So-and-so and his set” or “The Caucus” or “The Inner Ring.” If you are a candidate for admission you probably don’t call it anything. To discuss it with the other outsiders would make you feel outside yourself. And to mention talking to the man who is inside, and who may help you if this present conversation goes well, would be madness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My main purpose in this address is simply to convince you that this desire is one of the great permanent mainsprings of human action. It is one of the factors which go to make up the world as we know it—this whole pell-mell of struggle, competition, confusion, graft, disappointment and advertisement, and if it is one of the permanent mainsprings then you may be quite sure of this. Unless you take measures to prevent it, this desire is going to be one of the chief motives of your life, from the first day on which you enter your profession until the day when you are too old to care. That will be the natural thing—the life that will come to you of its own accord. Any other kind of life, if you lead it, will be the result of conscious and continuous effort. If you do nothing about it, if you drift with the stream, you will in fact be an “inner ringer.” I don’t say you’ll be a successful one; that’s as may be. But whether by pining and moping outside Rings that you can never enter, or by passing triumphantly further and further in—one way or the other you will be that kind of man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The quest of the Inner Ring will break your hearts unless you break it. But if you break it, a surprising result will follow. If in your working hours you make the work your end, you will presently find yourself all unawares inside the only circle in your profession that really matters. You will be one of the sound craftsmen, and other sound craftsmen will know it. This group of craftsmen will by no means coincide with the Inner Ring or the Important People or the People in the Know. It will not shape that professional policy or work up that professional influence which fights for the profession as a whole against the public: nor will it lead to those periodic scandals and crises which the Inner Ring produces. But it will do those things which that profession exists to do and will in the long run be responsible for all the respect which that profession in fact enjoys and which the speeches and advertisements cannot maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His main explicit reasons for advising against succumbing to this easy set of motives are that it runs a major risk of turning you into a scoundrel, and that it is fundamentally unsatisfying—once admitted to the ingroup, you will just want a further in group; the exclusive appeal of the ingroup won’t actually be appealing once you are comfortably in it; and the social pleasures of company in the set probably won’t satisfy, since those didn’t satisfy you on the outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there is further reason not to be drawn into such things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I controversially and uncertainly claim that even the good of having especially high social status is a lesser kind of good relative to those available from other arenas of existence. Though I suppose it increases your life expectancy somewhat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is roughly zero sum, so hard to wholly get behind and believe in, what with your success being net bad for the rest of the world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To the extent it is at the cost of real craftsmanship and focus on the object level, it will make you worse at your profession, and thus less cool in the eyes of God, or an ideal observer, who are even cooler than your local set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Lewis is also making an interesting maneuver here, beyond communicating an idea. In modeling the behavior of the coolness-seekers, you put them in a less cool position. In the default framing, they are sophisticated and others are naive. But when the ‘naive’ are intentionally so because they see the whole situation for what it is, while the sophisticated followed their brute urges without stepping back, who is naive really?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="essay" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I enjoyed C. S. Lewis’ The Inner Ring, and recommend you read it. It basically claims that much of human effort is directed at being admitted to whatever the local in-group is, that this happens easily to people, and that it is a bad thing to be drawn in to. Some quotes, though I also recommend reading the whole thing: In the passage I have just read from Tolstoy, the young second lieutenant Boris Dubretskoi discovers that there exist in the army two different systems or hierarchies. The one is printed in some little red book and anyone can easily read it up. It also remains constant. A general is always superior to a colonel, and a colonel to a captain. The other is not printed anywhere. Nor is it even a formally organised secret society with officers and rules which you would be told after you had been admitted. You are never formally and explicitly admitted by anyone. You discover gradually, in almost indefinable ways, that it exists and that you are outside it; and then later, perhaps, that you are inside it.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/francesco-ungaro-7gN7Ht39uRk-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/francesco-ungaro-7gN7Ht39uRk-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">On fundamental solitude</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/20/alone-huxley.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On fundamental solitude" /><published>2021-01-20T01:05:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T01:05:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/20/alone-huxley</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/20/alone-huxley.html">&lt;p&gt;A quote from Aldous Huxley that has stuck in my mind more than perhaps any other over the years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We live together, we act on, and react to, one another; but always and in all circumstances we are by ourselves. The martyrs go hand in hand into the arena; they are crucified alone. Embraced, the lovers desperately try to fuse their insulated ecstasies into a single self-transcendence; in vain. By its very nature every embodied spirit is doomed to suffer and enjoy in solitude. Sensations, feelings, insights, fancies—all these are private and, except through symbols and at second hand, incommunicable. We can pool information about experiences, but never the experiences themselves. From family to nation, every human group is a society of island universes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be fairly troubled by this kind of thought. These days I’m more inclined to think of memories of myself, my own writing from yesterday, my sense of a person in my arms, words vibrating my inner ears as light bounces between someone’s eyes and mine, words reaching me across the internet from a stranger, barely understandable lines from thousand year old pages, as more of a piece—physical communications between scattered consciousness. All interpreted with more or less insight and confidence and detail and sense of being an ‘experience’ and not just ‘information’, depending on the quality and nature of the message. But my ‘imagining’ of your mental state, and my ‘knowing’ of my own are both guesses. The sense that they are different is a pragmatic, superficial, quantitative one, not the symptom of a deep metaphysical separation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="philosophy" /><category term="worldspirit" /><summary type="html">A quote from Aldous Huxley that has stuck in my mind more than perhaps any other over the years: “We live together, we act on, and react to, one another; but always and in all circumstances we are by ourselves. The martyrs go hand in hand into the arena; they are crucified alone. Embraced, the lovers desperately try to fuse their insulated ecstasies into a single self-transcendence; in vain. By its very nature every embodied spirit is doomed to suffer and enjoy in solitude. Sensations, feelings, insights, fancies—all these are private and, except through symbols and at second hand, incommunicable. We can pool information about experiences, but never the experiences themselves. From family to nation, every human group is a society of island universes.” I used to be fairly troubled by this kind of thought. These days I’m more inclined to think of memories of myself, my own writing from yesterday, my sense of a person in my arms, words vibrating my inner ears as light bounces between someone’s eyes and mine, words reaching me across the internet from a stranger, barely understandable lines from thousand year old pages, as more of a piece—physical communications between scattered consciousness. All interpreted with more or less insight and confidence and detail and sense of being an ‘experience’ and not just ‘information’, depending on the quality and nature of the message. But my ‘imagining’ of your mental state, and my ‘knowing’ of my own are both guesses. The sense that they are different is a pragmatic, superficial, quantitative one, not the symptom of a deep metaphysical separation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Public selves</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/public-selves.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Public selves" /><published>2021-01-17T17:04:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T17:04:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/public-selves</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/public-selves.html">&lt;p&gt;A question that I return to in life strategy is whether to lean heavily on ‘spending one’s weirdness points wisely’—otherwise put, cowering lonely behind a cardboard cutout of the most forgettable person while proffering optimized propaganda through carefully selected slots—or whether to offer the world a fuller view of oneself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few arguments as I see them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiding allows you to be strategic, showing anything that is good to show, hiding anything that is not. Surely that is better then than any alternative, that must involve showing things that are bad to show, or not showing things that are good to show?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not necessarily! People can tell which strategy you are using, and usually the things that are ‘bad to show’ are bad for &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to show, but other people would be perfectly interested to see them. So it is less cooperative, and people may respond to that, which may on a longer term view be bad for you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also, which strategy you are enacting overall, or what you are doing in the past or future, can change whether something is good or bad to share. For instance, maybe you have personal problems that it would be both nice to have in the open, and helpful for others to know that you also face. If you are usually open about things, mentioning these might be no big deal, and so worth it on net. Whereas if you tend to be private, then suddenly announcing a personal problem will seem like a bigger deal, so the costs might outweigh the benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is something good about actually knowing other people - being part of a global intellectual society of real people, not of robotic fictions created by people. Being open contributes to this world being actual.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are intermediate options too, of course. Are there good principled ones?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What considerations am I missing?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="life-strategy" /><summary type="html">A question that I return to in life strategy is whether to lean heavily on ‘spending one’s weirdness points wisely’—otherwise put, cowering lonely behind a cardboard cutout of the most forgettable person while proffering optimized propaganda through carefully selected slots—or whether to offer the world a fuller view of oneself. A few arguments as I see them: Hiding allows you to be strategic, showing anything that is good to show, hiding anything that is not. Surely that is better then than any alternative, that must involve showing things that are bad to show, or not showing things that are good to show? Not necessarily! People can tell which strategy you are using, and usually the things that are ‘bad to show’ are bad for you to show, but other people would be perfectly interested to see them. So it is less cooperative, and people may respond to that, which may on a longer term view be bad for you. Also, which strategy you are enacting overall, or what you are doing in the past or future, can change whether something is good or bad to share. For instance, maybe you have personal problems that it would be both nice to have in the open, and helpful for others to know that you also face. If you are usually open about things, mentioning these might be no big deal, and so worth it on net. Whereas if you tend to be private, then suddenly announcing a personal problem will seem like a bigger deal, so the costs might outweigh the benefits. There is something good about actually knowing other people - being part of a global intellectual society of real people, not of robotic fictions created by people. Being open contributes to this world being actual. There are intermediate options too, of course. Are there good principled ones? What considerations am I missing?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/john-noonan-QM_LE41VJJ4-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://hosting.photobucket.com/images/i/katjasgrace/john-noonan-QM_LE41VJJ4-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Are the consequences of groups usually highly contingent on their details?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/group-scale.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are the consequences of groups usually highly contingent on their details?" /><published>2021-01-17T04:22:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T04:22:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/group-scale</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/17/group-scale.html">&lt;p&gt;How much of the impact of an organization is covered by it being ‘a group of size M working on X’, relative to the specifics of how and what they do in working on X? What if we also include a single scale of how functional they are?&lt;!--ex--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, does it mostly matter that my research group, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aiimpacts.org/&quot;&gt;AI Impacts&lt;/a&gt;, is a certain size force for AI risk related thinking (with the size determined by the number and competence of people and the functionality of the organization, say), or does it matter whether we write journal articles or news stories or blog posts or research pages, or whether we choose our projects collectively vs. individually, or whether we get most of our feedback internally vs. externally? Maybe most of these things can mostly be translated into ‘functionality’. But the ‘type of thing we are producing’ one doesn’t seem to as easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much does what exactly you are producing matter? It could matter almost entirely or not at all, to my knowledge. For instance, I have some intuition that ‘there are about three small orgs in that space’ is a reasonable description of how much effort is going into a goal, but I also have intuitions that, say, minor differences in the responsiveness or navigability or style of a website can make the difference between it seeming great or annoying or crankish, and being read or not, or liked by different people. Which seems like it should just have a fairly different effect. These seem vaguely in conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally meant for AI Impacts to be an unusual kind of entity, and the form of the output (website of ongoingly updated research pages on modular questions, hierarchically supporting one another) was a key part of the experiment. Which doesn’t imply a strong view on the importance of format—experimentation might make sense if format is so important it is worth searching alternative ones, but it might also make sense if it is so unimportant that it won’t mess anything up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are costs to doing unusual things (e.g. people are confused about what you are doing, other entities aren’t organized to interface with you), so if format is totally unimportant, maybe we should move to more normal things. (Or the same goes if format is important, and this one is clearly worse.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question is also relevant in how you pick organizations to donate to, so maybe people who regularly do that know the answers. Does it mostly matter that you have competent people working on the right cause, or having checked that, do you generally also need to look closely at exactly what they are doing?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="effectivealtruism" /><category term="organizational-strategy" /><summary type="html">How much of the impact of an organization is covered by it being ‘a group of size M working on X’, relative to the specifics of how and what they do in working on X? What if we also include a single scale of how functional they are?</summary></entry></feed>