<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-02T23:35:44-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">world spirit sock puppet</title><subtitle>Inclusive writings of Katja Grace</subtitle><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Milkmaid</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/02/the-milkmaid-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Milkmaid" /><published>2020-12-02T09:30:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-02T09:30:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/02/the-milkmaid-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/02/the-milkmaid-review.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/the-milkmaid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Milkmaid by Johannes Vermeer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.google.com/imgres?imgurl=https%3A%2F%2Fupload.wikimedia.org%2Fwikipedia%2Fcommons%2F2%2F20%2FJohannes_Vermeer_-_Het_melkmeisje_-_Google_Art_Project.jpg&amp;amp;imgrefurl=https%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fwiki%2FThe_Milkmaid_(Vermeer)&amp;amp;tbnid=jnoI3qSCaphJvM&amp;amp;vet=12ahUKEwj90rC0prHtAhUDiZ4KHcIjBLYQMygAegUIARC7AQ..i&amp;amp;docid=tLHuFkKJkzeKGM&amp;amp;w=4000&amp;amp;h=4485&amp;amp;q=the%20milkmaid%20johannes%20vermeer&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj90rC0prHtAhUDiZ4KHcIjBLYQMygAegUIARC7AQ&quot; alt=&quot;The Milkmaid by Johannes Vermeer&quot; style=&quot;margin:25px 0px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="CATEGORY-1" /><category term="CATEGORY-2" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inbox zero day</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/inbox-zero-day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inbox zero day" /><published>2020-12-01T22:53:16-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T22:53:16-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/inbox-zero-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/inbox-zero-day.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I spent the entire day emptying my main work email inbox of all its emails, many of which had lived there for years. Apparently it was last empty around when I got that email in early 2014. I had committed to someone that I would archive anything left in that account without reading it at 10:30 tonight, and thereby give up on getting to it. And I wanted to at least glance at things. The point of all this was to not have the ever-present sense of a giant backlog of things I am supposed to deal with, of which mounds of non-given-up-on emails are one piece. (Another option would be to just give up on everything that was ever pending, but I’m not quite up for it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recorded the time and remaining email count in a spreadsheet as I went along, and watched the expected time to completion at the current rate, to see if it was before or after 10:30pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://worldspiritsockpuppet.com/assets/emailsgraph.png&quot; alt=&quot;emails graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pretty intense, because most of the time it looked borderline whether I would make it, and tearing through reading a plethora of different things in a race against time for about nine almost consecutive hours is a lot. Overall it was pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some miscellaneous things on this topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My sincere apologies to a large fraction of the people who have ever tried to email me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s nice to go back and remember the flavors of the different times and the different sets of people who have been around. I look forward to the coming times when mingling with sets of people is back on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I get a fair number of extremely strange emails, for some of which I have trouble constructing any plausible circumstance that might have prompted them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s notable how quickly my brain categorizes emails as ‘crankish’ or not. You might think that this would require getting some of the content, but I think a lot of my view on the matter is formed by the time I’ve seen very surface features. Supposing I judge correctly (which seems true if I look at the content, but that could be prejudice), I wonder why there is this strong correlation between content and style.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It seems like people have very different norms for length when writing emails. It’s nice that some people think I have so much concentration, reading speed and spare time that I’m going to make it through any five page essay that someone I don’t know sends my way, but it’s not true. The chance for me reading a thing when I get it drops off fast, maybe reaching 50% at around two sentences, unless some good reason to read it has arisen by then. In the past, I mostly left it in my email at that point, for maybe several years, but going forward I think I’m going to try to just give up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m not sure if it would have been better to read all these emails at the time. Probably yes, because it would have been good for me to actually respond to people. But this way might have been better experientially.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="mundane" /><category term="journal" /><summary type="html">Today I spent the entire day emptying my main work email inbox of all its emails, many of which had lived there for years. Apparently it was last empty around when I got that email in early 2014. I had committed to someone that I would archive anything left in that account without reading it at 10:30 tonight, and thereby give up on getting to it. And I wanted to at least glance at things. The point of all this was to not have the ever-present sense of a giant backlog of things I am supposed to deal with, of which mounds of non-given-up-on emails are one piece. (Another option would be to just give up on everything that was ever pending, but I’m not quite up for it.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Points for anxiety</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/points-for-anxiety.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Points for anxiety" /><published>2020-12-01T02:03:25-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T02:03:25-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/points-for-anxiety</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/points-for-anxiety.html">&lt;p&gt;I have an intermittently crippling anxiety disorder, so I recently started trying a new kind of therapy to mitigate it. I’ve been finding sufficiently great so far that even if it doesn’t work long term I will probably think it was worth it. So I’ll tell you about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://noiseinyourhead.com/&quot;&gt;Reid Wilson’s&lt;/a&gt; ideas, I think as described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Stopping-Noise-Your-Head-Overcome/dp/0757319068&quot;&gt;his book&lt;/a&gt;, though I haven’t read it and most of my understanding comes from my therapist, my friend who also does this, and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://noiseinyourhead.com/free-video-series/&quot;&gt;set of humorous videos on Reid Wilson’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the practice, as I practice it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’m anxious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Notice that I am anxious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Connect with my outcome picture’. Which is to say, imagine a really good version of my life. (Usually focusing on details that parallel currently problematic ones. For instance, if I was distracted by the sense of not being able to breathe while hanging out with a friend, I might imagine a version of my life where I hang out with my friends attentively while confidently brushing off all manner of chest sensations, perhaps in the context of a life more broadly full of confidence and attention on things that matter.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be excited for the current bout of anxiety as an opportunity to exercise skills at living in the ‘outcome picture’ version of life in spite of anxiety. This involves having redrawn the goal as living well even in the context of anxiety rather than not being anxious. It also involves thinking of the route to this goal as developing a skill or strength via repeated practice, similar to learning a language or becoming good at bench press. Then because that practice requires a series of anxiety-filled contexts, you are naturally excited if an occasion comes up.
  For example, instead of aiming to never have panic attacks while getting lunch with someone, you are trying to become the kind of person who can keep their attention on the finer points of an argument in spite of maybe feeling like they can’t breathe that well. This is only going to happen via a number of practice occasions with arguments and breathing difficulties. So if one of these comes up, you are pumped.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go back to what I was doing. It doesn’t necessarily need to be in a non-anxious way even, just treating it as practice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I get ten points, I get a cookie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the clear rules for getting a point, and the dispersal of cookies, are both crucial for my own success with this, though my impression is that they are not included in the classic versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I like or think might be good about this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imagining how you want things to be ten or twenty times a day is pretty inspiring in general, anxiety aside. (Anxiety reduction techniques that involve doing something virtuous every time you are anxious seem good in general, if you can make them work. I used to play DDR whenever I was anxious, and I got heaps of exercise and very good at DDR.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can get genuinely excited for being anxious, that alone seems to undermine some of its force.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feeling like anxiety is the thing that is meant to happen, that is a key part of the path to your goal (or at least the path to a point), rather than a sign of things going wrong, also makes it easier to deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empirically it seems to just make me happy somehow. It might be all the imagining my outcome picture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="self-improvement" /><category term="anxiety" /><category term="worldlypositions" /><summary type="html">I have an intermittently crippling anxiety disorder, so I recently started trying a new kind of therapy to mitigate it. I’ve been finding sufficiently great so far that even if it doesn’t work long term I will probably think it was worth it. So I’ll tell you about it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sincerity trends</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/29/sincerity-trends.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sincerity trends" /><published>2020-11-29T22:22:52-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-29T22:22:52-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/29/sincerity-trends</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/29/sincerity-trends.html">&lt;p&gt;I have the impression that sincerity, earnestness and straightforward conviction used to be more popular flavors of attitude and have been replaced (at least in the public sphere) by more self-conscious, ironic, critical, half-hearted, cool type attitudes. I went hiking with a friend today, and he mentioned the same impression (though I may have got mine from him), and we speculated about the reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does everyone share this impression? Over what time-scales? Do we have good explanations?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="historic-social-trends" /><category term="sociology" /><summary type="html">I have the impression that sincerity, earnestness and straightforward conviction used to be more popular flavors of attitude and have been replaced (at least in the public sphere) by more self-conscious, ironic, critical, half-hearted, cool type attitudes. I went hiking with a friend today, and he mentioned the same impression (though I may have got mine from him), and we speculated about the reasons.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Another point of view on the details</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/28/another-point-of-view-on-the-details.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Another point of view on the details" /><published>2020-11-28T23:39:30-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-28T23:39:30-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/28/another-point-of-view-on-the-details</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/28/another-point-of-view-on-the-details.html">&lt;p&gt;This morning my boyfriend and I did an activity where he followed me around for a couple of hours and observed as I started the day and did some tasks. (I’ve also done something like that before with a friend who was trying out anthropology.) I suggested it this time because I often find it enlightening to hear an outside perspective on things that I do, and his in particular. And it seems rarer to hear about the details and tactics, versus very high level questions: I often know what projects another person thinks are good, but rarely know what they would do if they got an email asking to hang out from an acquaintance, or if they were feeling antsy, or how they would decide where to start on the project in question, or when to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think that it’s easy to have a somewhat silly habit, but then to deal with its oppressiveness by doing it automatically and fast. But then you barely notice it, so it is harder to remember that it’s a problem and fix it. And yet such things build up. And even having someone else watching can make the details of what you are doing—and their defensibility—briefly vivid. For instance, today I quickly noticed myself that I wash my hands way more than is reasonable while making a sandwich, but I do it pretty habitually and don’t even think about it. I just believe that making sandwiches is somehow arduous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good thing about this activity is that where I am focused on the detail of a problem, a new observer can be confused at why I would even think the thing is a problem, or worthy of my time to solve, or why I would assume the constraints that I’m assuming. Which can all be refreshing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I found it helpful and enlightening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But another virtue of this is in the never-ending effort to see what other people’s worlds are like. In hearing someone describe how your world looks to them, you perhaps get to infer something about the landscape of the place that view is coming from.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="worldlypositions" /><category term="self-improvement" /><category term="games" /><summary type="html">This morning my boyfriend and I did an activity where he followed me around for a couple of hours and observed as I started the day and did some tasks. (I’ve also done something like that before with a friend who was trying out anthropology.) I suggested it this time because I often find it enlightening to hear an outside perspective on things that I do, and his in particular. And it seems rarer to hear about the details and tactics, versus very high level questions: I often know what projects another person thinks are good, but rarely know what they would do if they got an email asking to hang out from an acquaintance, or if they were feeling antsy, or how they would decide where to start on the project in question, or when to stop.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Hunchback of Notre Dame as a 1996 taste datapoint</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/hunchback-of-notre-dame-and-taste.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hunchback of Notre Dame as a 1996 taste datapoint" /><published>2020-11-27T22:22:05-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T22:22:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/hunchback-of-notre-dame-and-taste</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/hunchback-of-notre-dame-and-taste.html">&lt;p&gt;My household watched the 1996 Disney version of &lt;em&gt;The Hunchback of Notre Dame&lt;/em&gt; recently. A notable thing about it to me was that the humor seemed in such poor taste. Which made me wonder, was 1996 just culturally different? Slapstick humor includes an emaciated old man imprisoned in a cylindrical cage tumbling over and over while someone runs on top of it, before he escapes, only to accidentally fall into some stocks. Ha! During a song, romantic rivals are jovially represented as hanging in the gallows. Various jokes are made around two men being sentenced to hanging without trial or ability to speak (‘any last words? didn’t think so’). Maybe I’m wrong that this would all seem weird to current viewers, and instead I’m just out of touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘G’ rated Disney film also seemed as if it was from a different culture in other ways, for instance the overt sexuality, its combination with religion, and the seriousness of the violence and hatred. At one point Frollo grabs Esmerelda in an apparent attempt to imprison her, but then presses his face into her hair and breathes in the smell. At other times he sings that his burning desire for her is turning him to sin, before asking the Virgin Mary to destroy her and send her to burn in hell if she won’t have him. “Destroy Esmeralda…And let her taste the fires of hell…Or else let her be mine and mine alone…Hellfire, Dark fire…Now gypsy, it’s your turn…Choose me or, Your pyre…Be mine or you will burn”. Later in his attempts to find Esmerelda, and also to bring about a genocide against the gypsies, he locks a family in their house and sets fire to it. Another time he burns her at the stake himself, until she is rescued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder whether these things also seemed strange at the time, or if norms have changed since 1996 (or if I’m wrong about what they are like now). I recently listened to the audiobook of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Better_Angels_of_Our_Nature&quot;&gt;The Better Angels of our Nature&lt;/a&gt;, which made me more aware of how norms around violence have changed in the long run, so I am curious about whether I can see it happening at the scale of my life. For instance, apparently only &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cat-burning&quot;&gt;a couple of hundred years ago&lt;/a&gt; normal people would find burning a cat alive good entertainment. In twenty-five years, do we also get to see another tenth of that much change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at critical response in Wikipedia, it sounds fairly positive, though there was indeed some controversy (including protests?) over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thefreelibrary.com/'Hunchback+of+Naughty+Dame'+row.-a061166779&quot;&gt;sexuality&lt;/a&gt; as well as apparently the possibility of ‘homosexual undertones’ (which seems like a clearer case of norms having changed quickly). &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20141205050748/http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1996-06-21/entertainment/9606210128_1_eraser-special-effects-star&quot;&gt;Gene Siskel, writing in in 1996&lt;/a&gt;, actually remarks on the tastefulness of the humor! (‘These ideas are presented with effective songs and, yes, tasteful bits of humor’.) Roger Ebert &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/the-hunchback-of-notre-dame-1996&quot;&gt;loved it 4/4 much&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I didn’t find evidence of people complaining much about its tastefulness in modern times either, so perhaps it’s just me or a more local cultural difference (I think a couple of my housemates also mentioned finding the humor to be bad).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="reviews" /><summary type="html">My household watched the 1996 Disney version of The Hunchback of Notre Dame recently. A notable thing about it to me was that the humor seemed in such poor taste. Which made me wonder, was 1996 just culturally different? Slapstick humor includes an emaciated old man imprisoned in a cylindrical cage tumbling over and over while someone runs on top of it, before he escapes, only to accidentally fall into some stocks. Ha! During a song, romantic rivals are jovially represented as hanging in the gallows. Various jokes are made around two men being sentenced to hanging without trial or ability to speak (‘any last words? didn’t think so’). Maybe I’m wrong that this would all seem weird to current viewers, and instead I’m just out of touch.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/Luce-notre-dame.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/Luce-notre-dame.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">No need to refrigerate</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/no-need-to-refrigerate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No need to refrigerate" /><published>2020-11-26T23:42:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T23:42:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/no-need-to-refrigerate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/no-need-to-refrigerate.html">&lt;p&gt;If you are wondering whether a food needs refrigerating, you look at the label until you either see an instruction to refrigerate it, or have looked at the label enough to exclude the possibility of it containing that instruction somewhere. This seems clearly worse worse than the label just always saying whether or not the food needs refrigerating, so the procedure terminates as soon as you find that sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s only a tiny bit worse—only a few seconds are at stake each time—but it is so clearly worse, it is interesting to me that it remains in the worse state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how would I expect it to get better? Here are some partial mechanisms by which I might expect things to get better usually, which this is evidence about the strength of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The market&lt;/strong&gt;: people would be marginally more likely to buy a product with slightly more helpful labeling, e.g. they might pay an extra cent for saving several seconds of their time.
  &lt;em&gt;I don’t feel surprised that this doesn’t work. For one thing, it would take the customer a large fraction of the time saved for each item to check whether it has the more useful label. Is there some theoretical reason that this should turn out ok in a&lt;/em&gt; homo economicus &lt;em&gt;utopia?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brand affect and loyalty&lt;/strong&gt;: people won’t check ahead of time whether a product will save them a second later, but after finding a product slightly more annoying to deal with, they will like the brand slightly less, and be less likely to buy it in future, even though the object they receive is identical.
  &lt;em&gt;I don’t intuitively expect it to work on its own, I think in part because I expect people to interpret very small things in light of the larger vibe they are getting from a product. For instance, if it was helpful in several ways, they might interpret a helpful label as more of that, whereas if it was in other ways minimalist, this might detract from that vibe. I don’t have an argument against it working in theory, but at a very small scale, since it is a very small problem for a customer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People being thoughtful and nice&lt;/strong&gt;: maybe even without incentives, it basically doesn’t cost more to have more helpful writing on your label, so why not do it?
  &lt;em&gt;My guess is that people writing labels don’t think of it. I’m not sure how reasonable that is, because I haven’t emotionally comprehended how many people are thinking about what to write on labels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some sort of feedback from users of labels&lt;/strong&gt;: if the problem with 3) was lack of knowledge, then the customer seems like the most likely person to bridge that gap.
  &lt;em&gt;Probably if you have users test a simmer sauce or something, you don’t go far enough down the details of their response to catch things like this? And nobody writes to the company to complain about something this small. Virtually all people have better things to think about than even noticing this cost.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others? (I expect I could think of some, but it is my bed time.) Happy Thanksgiving!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="societal-functioning" /><category term="institution-design" /><summary type="html">If you are wondering whether a food needs refrigerating, you look at the label until you either see an instruction to refrigerate it, or have looked at the label enough to exclude the possibility of it containing that instruction somewhere. This seems clearly worse worse than the label just always saying whether or not the food needs refrigerating, so the procedure terminates as soon as you find that sentence.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/supermarket.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/supermarket.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Air walls and empty currents</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/air-walls-and-empty-currents.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Air walls and empty currents" /><published>2020-11-26T00:32:33-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T00:32:33-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/air-walls-and-empty-currents</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/26/air-walls-and-empty-currents.html">&lt;p&gt;There is an experience archetype in my world that goes like this: you have been carefully navigating around a landscape of walls, or inching forward against an overwhelming current. Intently battling hard obstacles. Then you tentatively try walking right into a wall, and realize that they are all actually just air, and you can just walk straight through them. Or you find a turn of mind where you can just stand up straight against the wrenching current—not through huge effort and force, but through the current suddenly losing all physical relevance to your free motions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this familiar? What circumstances are like this?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="psychology" /><category term="other-minds" /><summary type="html">There is an experience archetype in my world that goes like this: you have been carefully navigating around a landscape of walls, or inching forward against an overwhelming current. Intently battling hard obstacles. Then you tentatively try walking right into a wall, and realize that they are all actually just air, and you can just walk straight through them. Or you find a turn of mind where you can just stand up straight against the wrenching current—not through huge effort and force, but through the current suddenly losing all physical relevance to your free motions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/current.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/current.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Salience costs and other lives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/24/salience-costs-and-other-lives.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Salience costs and other lives" /><published>2020-11-24T23:29:12-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-24T23:29:12-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/24/salience-costs-and-other-lives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/24/salience-costs-and-other-lives.html">&lt;p&gt;Alice has a car that can only drive at 65mph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob has a car that can drive at 70mph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time they both drive 70 miles to the city, Alice spends almost five extra minutes driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Bob’s car breaks down, he borrows Alice’s car. Driving it, he constantly has his foot on the accelerator, to no avail. The visceral slowness is encumbering and distracting. He spends more than an hour overcome with frustration, plus that extra five minutes driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob finds it hard to believe that Alice puts up with this, and supposes she must be really struggling in life, or making errors of judgment, if she hasn’t got a new car already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways that you can fail to appreciate how bad other people’s problems are. But I think you can also systematically fail to appreciate how bad they aren’t, for the person. What is salient in moving from your world to theirs is not necessarily salient in theirs, so when most of the cost is from the salience, you might be overestimating it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="psychology" /><category term="interpersonal-dynamics" /><summary type="html">Alice has a car that can only drive at 65mph.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/cars.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/cars.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Room cleaning haikus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/poetry-cleanup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Room cleaning haikus" /><published>2020-11-23T23:15:30-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-23T23:15:30-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/poetry-cleanup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/poetry-cleanup.html">&lt;p&gt;Autumn clothes&lt;br /&gt;
from old websites&lt;br /&gt;
in my drying machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thin cardboard box&lt;br /&gt;
with pictures of face creams&lt;br /&gt;
now roaming nearby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handful of tissues&lt;br /&gt;
collected from drifts&lt;br /&gt;
many tears and lunches&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Careful library&lt;br /&gt;
of things&lt;br /&gt;
I haven’t gotten around to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where would I keep this&lt;br /&gt;
very big pad of paper&lt;br /&gt;
if I were Critch?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t eat the pepparkakor&lt;br /&gt;
just because they are there&lt;br /&gt;
I did and regret nothing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moldy washcloth&lt;br /&gt;
my mother gave to me&lt;br /&gt;
I wash it&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katja Grace</name></author><category term="poetry" /><category term="journal" /><summary type="html">Autumn clothes from old websites in my drying machine</summary></entry></feed>